<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/" xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/" xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"><channel><title> חדשות המדע </title><atom:link href="https://www.sciencenews.org/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org<description> עיתונאות עצמאית מאז 1921</description><lastbuilddate> יום ה&#39;, 24 באוגוסט 2023 18:28:09 +0000</lastbuilddate><language> en-US</language><sy:updateperiod> מדי שעה</sy:updateperiod><sy:updatefrequency> 1</sy:updatefrequency><generator> https://wordpress.org/?v=6.2.2</generator><item><title> כיצד בינה מלאכותית מחדדת תמונות ראייה תרמית מטושטשות</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/ai-thermal-night-vision<dc:creator><![CDATA[Luis Melecio-Zambrano]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Thu, 24 Aug 2023 18:00:00 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Artificial Intelligence]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3130641 </guid><description><![CDATA[A thermal imaging technique uses a special camera and AI to create clear images and accurately gauge distances of objects, even in pitch-blackness]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<p>הדמויות המטושטשות והרפאים הנראות בדרך כלל בתמונות תרמיות עשויות להפוך לנחלת העבר. על ידי שילוב של בינה מלאכותית וראייה תרמית, מדענים יכולים ליצור תמונות חדות ומפורטות - אפילו בחושך. הטכניקה יכולה יום אחד לעזור לשפר את יכולתם של כלי רכב בנהיגה עצמית לנווט בלילה.<br><br> הדמיה תרמית, המשמשת לעתים קרובות במערכות ראיית לילה, פועלת על ידי זיהוי מקורות חום. תמונות האינפרא אדום מטושטשות בגלל תופעה שנקראת רוחות רפאים. חום מחפץ מציף את כל הפרטים על מרקם החפץ, בדומה להדלקת אור מקשה על פענוח כל תחריט על נורה.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> הפיזיקאי התיאורטי Fanglin Bao מאוניברסיטת פרדו במערב לאפייט, הודו, ועמיתיו השתמשו במצלמה תרמית שיכולה להבחין בין אורכי גל שונים של אור אינפרא אדום. החוקרים זיווגו את המצלמה הזו לתוכנת מחשב המשתמשת בבינה מלאכותית כדי להתיר מידע מהמכשיר כדי לחשוף את הטמפרטורה, המרקם וסוג החומר של עצמים בתמונה. טכניקה זו <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-023-06174-6" target="_blank" rel="noopener">ציירה תמונות בהירות ומפורטות מתוך סצנות לילה חשוכות</a> , כך מדווח הצוות ב-26 ביולי ב- <em>Nature</em> .</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> &quot;אין הגבלה של תנאי מזג אוויר קשים או תרחישי לילה&quot;, אומר מהנדס החשמל מוחמד עלי פארוק מאוניברסיטת גאלווי באירלנד, שלא היה מעורב במחקר. &quot;אתה יכול לקבל נתונים טובים מאוד וחדים מאוד גם בתנאי תאורה חלשים.&quot;</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> הטכניקה יכולה גם למדוד מרחק בערך באותו דיוק כמו השיטות הנוכחיות המבוססות על מצלמה. המשמעות היא שניתן להשתמש בו בכלי <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/self-driving-cars-see-better-cameras-mimic-mantis-shrimp-vision">רכב בנהיגה עצמית</a> , שצריכים לדעת מתי לבלום כדי להימנע מגרימת תאונה ( <em>SN: 10/12/18</em> ).</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> כלי רכב נוכחיים בנהיגה עצמית מודדים לעתים קרובות מרחק על ידי הקפצת אותות מאובייקטים, בדומה לאופן שבו עובד הסונאר. מכוניות אוטונומיות רבות ששולחות אותות עלולות לבלבל אחת את השנייה. מכיוון שהטכניקה החדשה לא צריכה לשלוח אות, זה יכול להיות בטוח יותר להתקדם בעולם עם יותר מכוניות בנהיגה עצמית, אומרים החוקרים.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> למרות זאת, הטכנולוגיה לא תעבור ברחובות סואנים בזמן הקרוב. המצלמה כבדה, כחצי מטר מכל צד ויקרה - היא עולה למעלה ממיליון דולר, אומר באו. ולכידת כל תמונה נמשכת בערך שנייה, וזה איטי מדי עבור רכב בנהיגה עצמית שצריך להגיב למצבים בזמן אמת.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> ובכל זאת, באו מצפה לראות גרסאות של טכנולוגיה זו עשויות להשפיע על כלי רכב או רובוטים בנהיגה עצמית בעתיד. &quot;לנו בני האדם יש הטיה אבולוציונית כלפי האור&quot;, הוא אומר. &quot;אבל מסתבר שבינה מלאכותית יכולה להתגבר על הדיכוטומיה ארוכת השנים הזו בין יום ללילה.&quot;</p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/082323_lmz_hadar_feat-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="298192" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/082323_lmz_hadar_feat-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title> פינגווינים קיסריים איבדו בשנה שעברה אלפי אפרוחים כתוצאה מהמסת קרח</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/antarctica-emperor-penguins-endangered-climate<dc:creator><![CDATA[Luis Melecio-Zambrano]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Thu, 24 Aug 2023 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Climate]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3130622 </guid><description><![CDATA[In 2022, groups of emperor penguins in western Antarctica lost almost all their chicks to receding sea ice, signaling the threat of climate change. ]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<p>אלפי פינגווינים קיסריים במערב אנטארקטיקה איבדו את גוזליהם בשנה שעברה, בעיקר בגלל נסיגת קרח הים, כך עולה מנתוני לוויין.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> במהלך השנתיים האחרונות, קרח הים <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/antarctic-sea-ice-record-low-2023">הגיע לשפל שיא</a> ברחבי אנטארקטיקה ( <em>SN: 7/5/23</em> ). אבל בזמן שהסתכל על תמונות לוויין בשנת 2022, הבחין הגיאוגרף פיטר פרטוול שהקרח באזור אחד נמס במיוחד בתחילת השנה. הוא ועמיתיו רצו למדוד את ההשפעה של אובדן הקרח הזה - בים בלינגסהאוזן מול מערב אנטארקטיקה - על פינגווינים קיסריים ( <em>Aptenodytes forsteri</em> ) באזור.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> אז החוקרים בחנו <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/emperor-penguin-poop-satellite-images-space-new-colonies">תמונות לוויין</a> של מושבות כדי לקבוע את גורל עונת הרבייה ( <em>SN: 8/4/20</em> ). מתוך חמש המושבות שנצפו, <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s43247-023-00927-x" target="_blank" rel="noopener">ארבע כנראה איבדו את כל הגוזלים שלהם</a> , כך מדווח הצוות ב-23 באוגוסט ב- <em>Communications Earth &amp; Environment</em> .</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> הפינגווינים הקיסריים מסתמכים על קרח ים יציב לאורך עונת הרבייה שלהם, שנמשכת מאפריל עד ינואר. כאשר ביצה בוקעת, הגוזל שזה עתה נולד חייב לברוח, מאבד את נוצותיו הפלומות כדי לקבל את פרווה עמיד למים.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> בשנת 2022, קרח ים התפרק לפני שכמה מושבות סיימו לברוח. ללא נוצות עמידות למים, ציפורים עופות לא היו מסוגלות לשרוד, אומר פרטוול. מבין הצעירים מכ-10,000 זוגות המתרבים באזור, &quot;אנחנו חושבים שכ-850 מהאפרוחים שרדו&quot;, אומר Fretwell, מהסקר האנטארקטי הבריטי בקיימברידג&#39;, אנגליה. </p><figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" width="677" height="450" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/082323_lmz_emperor_penguin_fail_inline-677x450.jpg" alt="פינגווינים קיסרים בוגרים מתאספים עם צעירים - הניתנים להבחנה בנוצותיהם האפורות והפלומות - על מדף הקרח הברוט של אנטארקטיקה." class="wp-image-3130624" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/082323_lmz_emperor_penguin_fail_inline-677x450.jpg 677w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/082323_lmz_emperor_penguin_fail_inline-576x383.jpg 576w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/082323_lmz_emperor_penguin_fail_inline-280x186.jpg 280w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/082323_lmz_emperor_penguin_fail_inline.jpg 680w" sizes="(max-width: 677px) 100vw, 677px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3130624">פינגווינים קיסריים בוגרים מתאספים עם צעירים - הניתנים להבחנה בנוצותיהם האפורות והפלומות - על מדף הקרח החום של אנטארקטיקה. המושבה שם סבלה שלוש שנים של כישלון רבייה מ-2016 עד 2018.</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3130624">כריסטופר וולטון</span></figcaption></figure><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> מושבות פינגווינים יכולות להתאושש מעונת רבייה אחת כושלת, אומרת אנני שמידט, אקולוגית של עופות ים ב-Blue Point Conservation Science בפטלומה, קליפורניה, שלא הייתה מעורבת במחקר החדש. והחוקרים בחנו רק כמה מושבות פינגווינים קיסריות של ה-62 ברחבי אנטארקטיקה.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> כמה מאותן מושבות אחרות חוו גם עונות רבייה גרועות לאחרונה. על מדף הקרח ברונט של אנטארקטיקה, מושבת הפינגווינים הקיסריים השנייה בגודלה בעולם באותה תקופה סבלה <a href="https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/antarctic-science/article/emperors-on-thin-ice-three-years-of-breeding-failure-at-halley-bay/4CA1A77971A4CD5D5CB823EBF338FAA9" target="_blank" rel="noopener">שלוש שנים של כישלון רבייה</a> מ-2016 עד 2018 לאחר שסערות שברו שם את הקרח הימי, דיווחו פרטוול ועמית בעבר. בין כשל רבייה להגירה המונית לאתר אחר, המושבה כמעט נעלמה.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> כישלון חוזר, או נפוץ יותר, עלול לאיים על מושבות ובסופו של דבר, על פינגווינים קיסריים בכללותם.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> המחקר החדש, המתעד כישלון רבייה על פני מספר מושבות בו זמנית, &quot;הוא התצפית הראשונה שעולה בקנה אחד עם הציפיות הגרועות ביותר של מה שיכול לקרות&quot; כאשר כדור הארץ ממשיך להתחמם, אומר שמידט. &quot;אני מודאג - זה לא סימן טוב.&quot; ההערכות האחרונות צופים כי האקלים המשתנה והמסת קרח הים <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0006320719309899" target="_blank" rel="noopener">עלולים לחתוך את אוכלוסיית הפינגווינים הקיסריים ביותר ממחצית</a> עד שנת 2100.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> למרות התחזית העגומה הזו לגבי פינגווינים קיסרים, לפרטוול עדיין יש תקווה. &quot;אם נוכל להאט את ההתחממות הגלובלית... נוכל לשנות את גורלו של הפינגווין הקיסר&quot;, הוא אומר. &quot;אבל חלון ההזדמנויות הזה הולך וקטן, אז אנחנו באמת צריכים לפעול עכשיו.&quot;</p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/082323_lmz_emperor_penguin_fail_feat-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="1240882" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/082323_lmz_emperor_penguin_fail_feat-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title> איך מכשיר אחד יכול לעזור לשנות את רשת החשמל שלנו</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/one-device-transform-power-electical-grid-inverter<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alexandra Witze]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Thu, 24 Aug 2023 13:11:11 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Climate]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3130504 </guid><description><![CDATA[As coal-fired power plants are retired, grid-forming inverters may be key to a future that relies on solar and wind power.]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<p class="has-drop-cap">מקולורדו לוושינגטון, מאוהיו ועד פנסילבניה, תחנות כוח פחמיות מושבתות. ארצות הברית בדרך לפרוש מחצית מהיכולת שלה לייצר חשמל מפחם עד 2026. זוהי ירידה מהירה להפליא משיא הפחם ב-2011 - ומהווה צעד מרכזי במעבר לאנרגיה נקייה <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/net-zero-carbon-emissions-climate">ולמאבק בשינויי האקלים</a> .</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> אבל יש חסרון מפתיע לפרוש תחנות כוח גדולות וישנות. מפעלים אלו עוזרים לשמור על יציבות רשת החשמל. ככל שיותר מהם עוברים לא מקוון, משהו אחר חייב להתקדם כדי לעשות את העבודה הזו.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> רשת חשמל היא רשת מורכבת הכוללת מערכות המייצרות חשמל, כמו תחנת כוח גרעינית או טורבינת רוח, ומערכות האוגרות ומעבירות כוח, כמו סוללות וקווי הולכה. רשת יכולה להפסיק לתפקד מכל מספר סיבות, כגון עץ נופל על קו חשמל או גל חום שמכריע את קיבולת המערכת. בארצות הברית, חשמל פועם דרך הרשת כמו פעימות לב בתדר סטנדרטי של 60 הרץ. התדירות הזו יכולה להשתנות אם הביקוש גדל מעבר להיצע או אם משהו במערכת כמו גנרטור גדול הולך לא מקוון. אפילו הפרעה קטנה בפעימות הלב של 60 הרץ יכולה לגרום לאפקטים של גלים שהרשת מתקשה להתאושש מהם.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> תחנות כוח גדולות נועדו לעזור לרשת להיות עמידה בפני השפעות האדווה הללו. האינרציה של הגנרטורים המסתובבים שלהם קונה זמן במקרה של הפסקת חשמל בלתי צפויה, והם מכוונים ללא הרף את תפוקת הכוח שלהם על סמך התדר ברשת, ומשמרים הכל יציב. אבל רשת חשמל שמשלבת כמויות גדולות של אנרגיה מתחדשת, כמו טורבינות רוח ופאנלים סולאריים, עובדת אחרת לגמרי. היא מסתמכת על מכשירים הידועים כממירים כדי להמיר את זרם ישר, או DC, חשמל המיוצר על ידי מתקני רוח ושמש לזרם חילופין, או AC, חשמל עבור הרשת. ומערכות אנרגיה מתחדשת המערבות ממירים אינן מתנהגות כמו תחנות כוח מסורתיות. &quot;אנחנו מתמודדים עם מערכת פיזית אחרת לגמרי&quot;, אומרת פטרישיה הידלגו-גונסלס, מהנדסת חשמל באוניברסיטת קליפורניה, סן דייגו.</p><div class="wp-block-sciencenews-content-sidebar" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><h3 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> עליית האנרגיה המתחדשת</h3><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> יותר חשמל בארה&quot;ב מגיע כעת ממקורות מתחדשים. סביר להניח שממירים יוצרי רשת ישחקו תפקיד גדול בהכנסת האנרגיה בבטחה לרשת החשמל. </p><iframe
		title="לְשַׁבֵּץ"
		class="sn-responsive-iframe"
		id="sn-responsive-iframe-1"
		src="https://flo.uri.sh/visualisation/14725245/embed"
		width="100%"
		height="600"
		layout="responsive"
		frameborder="0"
		allowfullscreen
	></iframe></div><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> אז חוקרים חיפשו דרכים לשמור על יציבות הרשת מכיוון שתחנות כוח גדולות יוצאות לפנסיה ואנרגיה מתחדשת מהווה אחוז גדול יותר מייצור החשמל בארה&quot;ב. ייתכן שהתשובה טמונה בסוג מיוחד של מהפך, הידוע כממירי רשת. חלקי הציוד החשמלי הללו, שגודלם נע בין קטן ממיקרוגל לגדול כמו מיכל משלוח, מתוכנתים במיוחד לעבוד בממשק בין משהו שמייצר או אוגר חשמל - כמו טורבינות רוח, פאנלים סולאריים וסוללות - לבין רֶשֶׁת. באופן מכריע, הם מסוגלים לשלוט בזרימת האנרגיה המתחדשת לרשת במהירות ובתגובה, בדרכים המחקות את השליטה מתחנות כוח גדולות.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> על ידי הוספת כמה מהפכים היוצרים רשת לתוך רשת חשמל קיימת, מהנדסים יכולים לעזור להחליף את הפונקציות שאבדו כאשר המפעלים הגדולים יוצאים לפנסיה. לממירים ליצירת רשת יש גם יתרונות נוספים, כגון הפעלה מחדש אוטומטית של רשת שיצאה במצב לא מקוון. זה יכול להפוך את החברה לעמידה יותר להפסקות החשמל שמגיעות <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/summer-extreme-heat-waves-jet-stream">עם מזג אוויר קיצוני</a> הניזון משינויי אקלים, כגון גלי חום והוריקנים ( <em>SN: 2/15/20, עמ&#39; 22</em> ).</p><div class="wp-block-sciencenews-content-sidebar" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><h3 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> שמש ורוח רואים בום</h3><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> כמות החשמל בארה&quot;ב המופקת מאנרגיה סולארית ורוח גדלה באופן דרמטי במהלך העשור האחרון. </p><iframe
		title="לְשַׁבֵּץ"
		class="sn-responsive-iframe"
		id="sn-responsive-iframe-2"
		src="https://flo.uri.sh/visualisation/14725201/embed"
		width="100%"
		height="600"
		layout="responsive"
		frameborder="0"
		allowfullscreen
	></iframe></div><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> מהו מהפך ליצירת רשת?</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> תחשוב על מהפך היוצר רשת כעל אמא ברווז עם חבורה של ברווזונים תינוקות משתרכים אחריו, אומר דומיניק גרוס, מהנדס חשמל באוניברסיטת ויסקונסין-מדיסון. מהפך יוצר רשת יכול להזרים מתח לרשת ולאחר מכן להתאים את התדר שלו בהתאם לכמות הכוח הזורם במערכת. מקורות חשמל אחרים הזורמים לרשת, הברווזונים התינוקות, יכולים אז להסתנכרן עם אותו מהפך יוצר רשת, בדיוק כפי שעשו עם זרימת החשמל שפועמה מתחנות כוח.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> זה נותן לממירים היוצרים רשת תפקיד מפתח בהכנסת יותר אנרגיה מתחדשת לרשת החשמל. יצרנים כולל ג&#39;נרל אלקטריק, סימנס, טסלה והיטאצ&#39;י כבר מייצרים את המכשירים הללו, והם היו בשימוש במשך עשרות שנים ברשתות חשמל מבודדות, כמו באיים קטנים. כיום, השימוש בהם מתרחב במהירות ברחבי העולם כאשר חברות חשמל גדולות פונות למכשירים כדי להתמודד עם הפריחה באנרגיה מתחדשת.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> הוספת יכולות של יצירת רשת למערכות חשמל מתחדשות היא צעד ראשון קל שיכול לעשות הבדל דרמטי בבניית רשת איתנה לעתיד, אומרת ג&#39;וליה מטבוסיאן, המהנדסת הראשית ב-Energy Systems Integration Group באוסטין, טקסס. &quot;יש לנו באמת את חלון ההזדמנויות הזה עכשיו&quot;, היא אומרת.</p><div class="wp-block-sciencenews-content-sidebar" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><h3 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> רשת החשמל העתידית</h3><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> תחנות כוח פחמיות וגז טבעי הן עמוד השדרה של רשת החשמל האמריקאית של ימינו. חוות רוח וסולריות ממלאות תפקיד קטן יותר ומשתמשות בממירים העוקבים אחר רשת (כתומים) כדי להכניס יותר חשמל לסירוגין למערכת. אבל ממירי רשת (כחול) יכולים לעזור לפנות מקום לרשת עתידית הנשענת בעיקר על אנרגיה מתחדשת. ברשת העתידית, בכל בית יכולים להיות פאנלים סולאריים, ולרכבים חשמליים תהיה טעינה דו-כיוונית, שתאפשר להם להחזיר אנרגיה לרשת. </p><figure class="wp-block-image "><picture class="sn-responsive-image"><source srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/082623_electical-grid_inline1_desktop.jpg 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/082623_electical-grid_inline1_desktop-579x383.jpg 579w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/082623_electical-grid_inline1_desktop-281x186.jpg 281w" width="680" height="450" media="(min-width: 600px)" sizes="(max-width: 1023px) 100vw, 680px"></source><source srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/082623_electical-grid_inline1_mobile.jpg 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/082623_electical-grid_inline1_mobile-579x383.jpg 579w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/082623_electical-grid_inline1_mobile-281x186.jpg 281w" width="680" height="450"></source><img src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/082623_electical-grid_inline1_mobile.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large" alt="" decoding="async" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/082623_electical-grid_inline1_mobile.jpg 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/082623_electical-grid_inline1_mobile-579x383.jpg 579w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/082623_electical-grid_inline1_mobile-281x186.jpg 281w" sizes="(max-width: 1023px) 100vw, 680px" data-attachment-id="3130507" data-permalink="https://www.sciencenews.org/082623_electical-grid_inline1_mobile" data-orig-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/082623_electical-grid_inline1_mobile.jpg" data-orig-size="680,450" data-comments-opened="0" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="082623_electical-grid_inline1_mobile" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/082623_electical-grid_inline1_mobile-579x383.jpg" data-large-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/082623_electical-grid_inline1_mobile.jpg" /></picture><figcaption> <span class="credit mobile-credit wp-credit-3130507">סי צ&#39;אנג</span> <span class="credit desktop-credit wp-credit-3130506">סי צ&#39;אנג</span> </figcaption></figure><div style="text-transform: uppercase;line-height: 12px;font-size: 10px;letter-spacing: 0.75px;text-align:right;direction:rtl"> מקור: NREL; ב&#39; קרופוסקי</div></div><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> אם יש לך פאנלים סולאריים בבית, כנראה שיש לך מהפך במוסך שלך. חברות אנרגיה משתמשות בממירים דומים בחוות רוח ואנרגיה סולארית כדי להמיר כמויות גדולות של חשמל DC לחשמל AC כדי להזין את הרשת. אבל רובם הם מה שמכונה <em>ממירי</em> רשת. הם כמו הברווזונים התינוקיים שנגררים אחרי אמם - הם יכולים לעשות כמה דברים בעצמם אבל הם לא מסוגלים להפעיל את המערכת כמו ברווז מבוגר.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> עם זאת, מהפך יוצר רשת יכול לחוש את השינויים ברשת ולהגיב בזמן אמת כדי להתאים את התדר שלו, מה שמזרים כוח פחות או יותר לפי הצורך כדי לייצב את הרשת. פלוריאן דורפלר, מהנדס חשמל ב-ETH ציריך, משווה קבוצה של ממירים יוצרים רשת ברשת חשמל לחבורה של גלגלי אופניים מסתובבים המחוברים ברצועה אלסטית. אם אחד הגלגלים מתחיל להאט מעט מסיבה כלשהי, הרצועה האלסטית תעביר מומנטום מהאחרים ותחזיר אותו לסנכרון עם הקבוצה.</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> מי משתמש בממירי רשת?</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> ממירי רשת אינם חדשים לגמרי; הם שימשו ברחבי העולם במשך עשרות שנים למטרות מסוימות. בארצות הברית, הם נמצאים בעיקר במיקרו-רשתות, מערכות חשמל קטנות המספקות אזורים מבודדים כמו איים או מתקנים קטנים.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> בשנות ה-2010, למשל, קבוצה של חוקרים ואנשי מקצוע בתעשייה בנתה מיקרו-רשת ששילבה ממירי רשת בכלא סנטה ריטה בדבלין, קליפורניה. המיקרו-גרייד השתמשה בפאנלים סולאריים על הגג, חמש טורבינות רוח, תא דלק ואחסון סוללות ליצור מערכת חשמל עצמאית שפעלה לשימוש יומיומי אך תוכל גם להמשיך לפעול באופן עצמאי מרשת החשמל הראשית במקרה של הפסקה - חיונית לשמירה על האבטחה. רשתות מיקרו אחרות המשתמשות בממירים יוצרי רשת כוללות בסיס צבאי באי קוואי בהוואי ובאי הקריבי סנט יוסטטיוס.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> האתגר כעת הוא להתרחב מאותן מערכות קטנות ומתקיימות בעצמן לרשתות חשמל גדולות יותר המשלבות הרבה אנרגיה מתחדשת. כמה מדינות החלו במאמץ זה, והוסיפו מהפכים יוצרי רשת למערכות שלהם.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> אוסטרליה היא אולי המובילה בעולם, עם שלושה מתקני אנרגיה מתחדשת גדולים הכוללים מהפכים יוצרי רשת שנכנסו לאחרונה לפעילות ועוד שלושה מתקנים כאלה בעבודות, בהיקף כולל של 480 מגה וואט של הספק. כמה מהם נמצאים בדרום אוסטרליה, שם כוח הרוח פרח בשנים האחרונות. בדצמבר הודיעה הסוכנות האוסטרלית לאנרגיה מתחדשת שהיא משקיעה <a href="https://www.energy.gov.au/news-media/news/arena-backs-8-grid-scale-batteries-worth-27-billion#:~:text=The%20Australian%20Renewable%20Energy%20Agency,with%20grid%2Dforming%20inverter%20technology." target="_blank" rel="noopener">176 מיליון דולר אוסטרלי</a> (כ-118 מיליון דולר) בשמונה פרויקטים נוספים להפקת אנרגיה מתחדשת באמצעות טכנולוגיות ליצירת רשתות. בסך הכל שמונה הפרויקטים הללו נועדו להפיק 2 ג&#39;יגה וואט של חשמל - פי 10 מהיכולת ליצירת רשת של המדינה עד כה וצעד &quot;פורץ דרך&quot; בכיוון הנכון, אומר מטבוסיאן.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> בריטניה גם משקיעה בחמישה פרויקטים חדשים, כולל מתקן של 300 מגה-וואט בסקוטלנד שאמור להסתיים ב-2024. לעומת זאת, ארצות הברית עשתה מעט ברמה הלאומית כדי לעודד אימוץ של ממירים יוצרי רשת, אפילו שכן ייצור אנרגיה מתחדשת הוכפל בערך בעשור האחרון וכיום מהווה יותר מ-20 אחוז מייצור החשמל במדינה. &quot;ארה&quot;ב כנראה נמצאת 10 שנים מאחורי העקומה&quot;, אומר דורפלר.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> יכול להיות שזה משתנה. משרד האנרגיה של ארה&quot;ב מממן מאמץ של 25 מיליון דולר כדי לעבוד על איך להכניס יותר ממירים יוצרי רשת למערכת החשמל בארה&quot;ב. הקונסורציום, המכונה UNIFI, ל&quot;יכולת הדדית אוניברסלית לממירי רשת&quot;, נמצא במחקר השני מתוך חמש שנות מחקר. היא <a href="https://www.nrel.gov/docs/fy21osti/73476.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">מובלת על ידי המעבדה הלאומית לאנרגיה מתחדשת</a> y בגולדן, קולו, יחד עם אוניברסיטת טקסס באוסטין והמכון לחקר החשמל החשמלי בפאלו אלטו, קליפורניה.</p><div class="wp-block-sciencenews-content-sidebar alignleft" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><h3 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> רשתות על הקצה</h3><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> רשתות החשמל מציגות את גילן - והן פגיעות במיוחד להשפעות המדורגות שעלולות לבוא עם מזג אוויר קיצוני. הנה הצצה לכמה אירועים אחרונים שדחקו את הרשתות לקצה. </p><figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="675" height="450" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/082623_electical-grid_sidebar-675x450.jpg" alt="תמונה של כביש מהיר בטקסס מכוסה בשלג מפברואר 2021 כאשר הקפאה עמוקה שיתקה את רשת החשמל של המדינה." class="wp-image-3130509" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/082623_electical-grid_sidebar-675x450.jpg 675w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/082623_electical-grid_sidebar-575x383.jpg 575w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/082623_electical-grid_sidebar-279x186.jpg 279w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/082623_electical-grid_sidebar.jpg 680w" sizes="(max-width: 675px) 100vw, 675px" /><figcaption> <span class="credit wp-credit-3130509">BRETT COOMER/ <em>HOUSTON CHRONICLE</em> VIA AP</span></figcaption></figure><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <strong>פברואר 2021</strong><br> הקפאה עמוקה ברובה של טקסס (המוצגת למעלה) שיתקה את הציוד החשמלי והוציאה חלק גדול מהרשת של המדינה במצב לא מקוון, והובילה למאות מקרי מוות.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <strong>ספטמבר 2021</strong><br> הוריקן אידה הוציא את החשמל ליותר ממיליון אנשים בלואיזיאנה, בין השאר בגלל קווי תמסורת שלא יכלו לעמוד במהירויות הרוח של ההוריקן.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <strong>מאי 2022</strong><br> סופת רוח עזה ברחבי אונטריו וקוויבק, קנדה, הפילה את קווי החשמל ובסופו של דבר הותירה כמעט מיליון בני אדם ללא חשמל.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <strong>יוני 2022</strong><br> תקלה בתחנת כוח במערב טקסס גרמה לכשלים נוספים ברחבי הרשת של טקסס, כולל דפיקה של 1.7 ג&#39;יגה וואט של ייצור חשמל סולארי במצב לא מקוון.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <strong>ינואר 202</strong> 3<br> עלייה במתח השביתה את הרשת הלאומית של פקיסטן, והותירה יותר מ-200 מיליון איש ללא חשמל.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <strong>יוני 2023</strong><br> כיפת חום מעל צפון מקסיקו וטקסס כמעט דחפה את דרישת החשמל של מקסיקו לחרוג מההיצע שלה.</p></div><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> עד כה, UNIFI התמקדה בנושאים בסיסיים כמו יצירת הנחיות מוצעות לאופן שבו חברות צריכות לבנות ממירי רשת. עד כה, יצרנים ברחבי העולם ייצרו סוגים משלהם של ממירים ליצירת רשת עם מעט תיאום ביניהם. בדצמבר, UNIFI פרסמה טיוטת תקנים שנועדו לשמש צעד ראשון לקראת קוד רשת לאומי הכולל מפרטים טכניים לציוד; גרסה שנייה ומעודכנת צפויה עד סוף השנה.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> UNIFI הביאה לאחרונה קומץ ממירים ליצירת רשת, שנרכשו מיצרנים שונים, למעבדת קולורדו של NREL. שם חוקרים בודקים אותם במערכת חשמל של 1 מגה וואט כדי לראות איך הם מסתדרים בעבודה באותה רשת. מאמץ דומה של UNIFI בודק את הביצועים של מספר גדול יותר של מהפכים ליצירת רשת מתוצרת שני יצרנים שונים במערכת של 20 מגה וואט בקוואי.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> המטרה היא לראות האם ממירים מיצרנים שונים יכולים להשתלב בצורה חלקה ברשת חשמל גדולה, וכמה עבודת תכנות תידרש כדי לגרום להם לשחק יפה אחד עם השני. &quot;איך גורמים למיליוני מהדברים האלה לעבוד ביחד, בשיתוף פעולה, בהקשר של מערכות רשת בקנה מידה גדול?&quot; שואל גרוס, שעובד עם UNIFI. בדיקות כאלה הן רק צעדים מוקדמים להדביק את ארצות הברית עם מדינות אחרות שכבר יש להן ממירים יוצרי רשת הפועלים ברשתות החשמל הגדולות שלהן.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> UNIFI מקווה להעלות את הפרופיל של ממירים יוצרי רשת ולספק הדרכה למה שהוא כיום נוף של המערב הפרוע של חברות שונות המייצרות אותם. אבל זה יצטרך לנוע מהר כדי לעשות את ההבדל. &quot;אנחנו ממש מדברים על שינוי של כל משק החשמל תוך 15 שנה&quot;, אומר בן קרופוסקי, מנהל המרכז להנדסת מערכות חשמל ב-NREL והמנהל הארגוני של UNIFI. &quot;לקח 140, 150 שנה לבנות את מה שיש לנו היום. אז זה רק שינוי מונומנטלי בגזרת החשמל&quot;.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> ממירים במערכת פאנל סולארי ביתית טיפוסית יכולים לעלות כמה אלפי דולרים, כאשר העלות גבוהה יותר עבור מערכות בקנה מידה תעשייתי. אבל ציוד ליצירת רשת אינו בהכרח יקר יותר לייצור מאשר ציוד העוקב לרשת. היצרנים גובים קצת יותר כדי לכסות את עלויות המחקר והפיתוח שלהם, אבל ההבדל הוא מינימלי עבור התועלת שהושגה, אומר Matevosyan. אפילו כשמדינות מסוימות מעודדות חברות אנרגיה להכניס טכנולוגיות ליצירת רשתות, היא אומרת שכל מי שבונה כיום רכיבי רשת צריך לשלב אותם כדבר מובן מאליו. &quot;זה פשוט הגיוני שיצרו רשת&quot;, היא אומרת. &quot;אתה יכול להוכיח את זה לעתיד.&quot;</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> מהן השאלות הפתוחות?</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> גם כאשר מאמצים ממירים יוצרי רשת, ישנן שאלות מחקר שעדיין לא קיבלו תשובה. אתגר אחד הוא שעדיין לא ברור כמה ממירים ברשתות העתיד יצטרכו ליצור רשת. חישובים תיאורטיים מצביעים על כך שרשתות מסוימות יפעלו בסדר גמור בהשגת 60 עד 70 אחוז מהכוח שלהן ממקורות מתחדשים באמצעות ממירים העוקבים אחר רשת. אבל אחרים עלולים לקרוס ב-20 אחוז בלבד ויצטרכו להיות יותר ממירים יוצרי רשת בתערובת, אומר גרוס.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> המספר עבור כל רשת יהיה תלוי בגורמים כגון גיל הרשת, יציבות וגיאומטריה. רשת מחוברת בצפיפות של מתקני ייצור חשמל כמו באירופה עשויה להזדקק לאחוז קטן בהרבה של ממירים יוצרי רשת מאשר רשת ארוכה ומתוחה כמו זו שלאורך החוף האוסטרלי.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> רשת החשמל בארה&quot;ב היא למעשה שלוש רשתות נפרדות, בחלקים המזרחיים והמערביים של המדינה ובטקסס, כולן עם צרכי אינוורטר משתנים. וחלק ממפעילי החשמל עשויים לבחור לנתק את מפעלי הפחם או הגז שלהם, אך לשמור על כמה מתקנים גרעיניים או הידרואלקטרים ​​גדולים, שימשיכו לתמוך בסינכרון של הרשת וידרשו פחות ממירים יוצרי רשת. </p><figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="680" height="510" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/082623_electical-grid_inline3.jpg" alt="תמונה של חווה סולארית המספקת חשמל לאי הקריבי סנט יוסטטיוס." class="wp-image-3130508" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/082623_electical-grid_inline3.jpg 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/082623_electical-grid_inline3-511x383.jpg 511w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/082623_electical-grid_inline3-600x450.jpg 600w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/082623_electical-grid_inline3-248x186.jpg 248w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/082623_electical-grid_inline3-263x197.jpg 263w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/082623_electical-grid_inline3-560x420.jpg 560w" sizes="(max-width: 680px) 100vw, 680px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3130508">האי הקריבי סנט אוסטטיוס (מוצגת חווה סולארית) תלוי במיקרו-רשת המשתמשת בממירים יוצרי רשת.</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3130508">ROBERTKENNESY/WIKIMEDIA COMMONS ( <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">CC BY-SA 4.0</a> )</span></figcaption></figure><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> גבולות מחקר אחרים כוללים גילוי דרכים חדשות לאבחון ולתקן בעיות ברשת. קצר חשמלי ברכיב רשת, למשל, יכול להזרים לפתע כמויות גדולות של זרם, נחשול שתחנות כוח מסורתיות יכולות להתמודד איתו באופן אוטומטי על ידי ניתוק החלק התקול. ממירי רשת אינם יכולים לסבול קוצים גדולים בזרם, מה שמקשה על פתרון הבעיות הללו בזמן אמת. &quot;איך לעשות זאת בצורה יעילה ובטוחה היא עדיין שאלת מחקר גדולה&quot;, אומר רודריגו הנריקז-אובה, מהנדס חשמל במאונטיין וויו, קליפורניה, שעובד עם UNIFI.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> כמה מדענים, כולל דורפלר, חוקרים כיצד רשת חשמל עם הרבה מהפכים היוצרים רשת יכולה לספק חשמל בדרכים חדשות. על ידי נקיטת צעדים נוספים כדי לייעל את האופן שבו הממירים פועלים יחד, החוקרים יכולים לקרב את המערכת למה שיש המתארים כתחנת כוח וירטואלית - שבה הרבה התקני אנרגיה מתחדשת בקנה מידה קטן מתפקדים ביעילות כתחנת כוח מסורתית אחת. המשמעות עשויה להיות תכנות ממירים כך שיוציאו במהירות מתח מהסוללה ויזרקו אותו כדי להפוך את הרשת לחזקה יותר בפני תנודות בלתי צפויות. טכניקות למידת מכונה עשויות לעזור, על ידי הכשרת ממירים על נתונים מהעולם האמיתי כדי לכוונן פעולות.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> כמובן, ישנם אתגרים רבים אחרים לבניית הרשת של העתיד, כמו למצוא דרכים טובות יותר לאחסן חשמל מחוות שמש וחוות רוח, כיצד לבנות את קווי ההולכה הדרושים וכיצד להאיץ את החיבור של מתקני חשמל מתחדשים. הרשת, פגומה כעת עקב בעיות רגולטוריות.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Hidalgo-Gonzalez אומר שרשת החשמל של העתיד צריכה להיות חזקה יותר ועמידה יותר עבור כולם. רשת החשמל של ארה&quot;ב של היום מטפחת הרבה אי שוויון חברתי. הוא נוטה להיות חלש ופחות אמין, למשל, בקהילות בעלות הכנסה נמוכה יותר הפגיעות למזג אוויר קיצוני מאשר בקהילות עשירות יותר. בשנת 2021, למשל, הוריקן אידה הפיל את הכוח ליותר ממיליון אנשים בלואיזיאנה, כשכמה קהילות בעלות הכנסה נמוכה לא קיבלו אותו בחזרה במשך שבועות.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> אנרגיה מתחדשת, מחוזקת על ידי ממירים יוצרי רשת, יכולה למלא תפקיד גדול בהפיכת הרשת לגמישה ושוויונית יותר, אומר הידלגו-גונסלס. &quot;אנחנו צריכים ללכת ממש מהר&quot;, היא אומרת, &quot;אם אנחנו רוצים להתייחס ברצינות לשינויי האקלים&quot;.</p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/082623_electical-grid_feat-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="124079" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/082623_electical-grid_feat-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title> נחיתת הירח המוצלחת של הודו באה בעקבות כישלונות אחרונים של מדינות אחרות</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/india-chandrayaan-moon-landing<dc:creator><![CDATA[Katherine Kornei]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Wed, 23 Aug 2023 16:29:42 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Space]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3130597 </guid><description><![CDATA[The Chandrayaan-3 mission delivered a lander and rover to the moon. Attempts by other countries this year show that getting there is still a challenge.]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<p>החלל קשה, כמו שנאמר.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> בזמן שבני האדם התאמצו לשגר את עצמם ואת המכונות שלהם אל מעבר לכדור הארץ, העיקרון הזה הוכח שוב ושוב. ניסיונות אחרונים לגעת בירח - הישג שהושג לראשונה לפני כמעט 60 שנה על ידי הגשושית הרובוטית לונה-9 של ברית המועצות לשעבר - היו רצופים במיוחד בכישלון.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> אבל ב-23 באוגוסט, חללית הודית, לראשונה, נחתה בהצלחה על פני הירח.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> משימת צ&#39;אנדרייאן-3, שהושקה ב-14 ביולי, העבירה את הנחתת ויקראם ואת הרובר הפראגיאן לקוטב הדרומי של הירח, אזור <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/ice-moon-poles-ancient-volcano-eruption-water">שנחשב כמכיל קרח מים</a> ( <em>SN: 24/5/22</em> ).</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> מאגרים כאלה של קרח מים יספקו מקור מכריע של מי שתייה לא רק עבור כל תושבי הירח העתידיים, אלא גם מימן לדלק. זה היה הניסיון השני של המדינה לנחיתה על הירח, לאחר <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/india-moon-lander-vikram-isro">התרסקות הנחתת של Chandrayaan-2 בשנת 2019</a> ( <em>SN: 20/9/19</em> ).</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> הנחיתה של ויקראם מעבירה את הודו לקבוצה נדירה של אומות שביצעו בהצלחה &quot;נחיתה רכה&quot; - בניגוד ל&quot;נחיתה קשה&quot; בלתי מבוקרת - על הירח: ארצות הברית, ברית המועצות לשעבר <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/china-landed-moon-missions-apollo-top-science-stories-2019-yir">וסין</a> ( <em>SN: 12/16 /19</em> ). הצלחת המשימה, לעומת זאת, באה בעקבות הכישלונות האחרונים.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> ב-19 באוגוסט התרסקה הגשושית הרוסית לונה-25 אל הירח. החללית בגודל מכונית סובבה את הירח במשך מספר ימים, כאשר לפי סוכנות החלל הרוסית, התקשורת אבדה לאחר שהכלי ירה במנועיה במהלך תמרוני נחיתה מוקדמים. לונה-25 נועד לקרבת מכתש בוגוסלבסקי ליד הקוטב הדרומי של הירח, שם הוא היה בוחן את פני הירח ואת האטמוספירה הקלושה.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> מוקדם יותר השנה, ב-25 באפריל, התרסקה גם מטוס הנחתת Hakuto-R Mission 1 של יפן על פני הירח. לפי ispace, החברה הפרטית שפיתחה את המשימה, ההתרסקות אירעה בגלל שהתוכנה המשולבת חישבת לא נכון את גובה הנחתת מעל פני הירח. הנחתת הייתה אמורה לגעת במכתש אטלס בצידו הקרוב של הירח ולחקור את אבק הירח.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> למרות קרבתו היחסית של קצת פחות מ-400,000 קילומטרים, הירח הוא <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/israel-moon-mission-spacecraft-crash">יעד מאתגר עבור חלליות המבקשות לנחות</a> ( <em>SN: 4/11/19</em> ). זה בעיקר בגלל שלשכן השמימי הקרוב שלנו אין אווירה.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> מנגנון המעבר להאטת עצם יורד על פני כדור הארץ - מצנח - הוא אפוא חסר תועלת, אומר דייב וויליאמס, מדען ירח וכוכבי הלכת במרכז טיסות החלל גודארד של נאס&quot;א בגרינבלט, מד. &quot;הדרך היחידה להאט את עצמך היא עם רקטות&quot;. זה המקום שבו הדברים מסתבכים, הוא אומר, שכן ירי רקטה פירושו שליטה על הכיוון והדחף שלה, בין היתר.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> כוח המשיכה של הירח, אמנם רק כשישית מזה של כדור הארץ, הוא חזק מספיק כדי להשפיע לרעה על חללית נכה בנפילה חופשית, אומר וויליאמס. (לחללית שנוחתת על כוכב שביט או אסטרואיד קל יותר כי שדות הכבידה של הגופים האלה הם בדרך כלל כל כך חלשים שיש סכנה קטנה להתרסקות.)</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> יש גם את האתגר של קביעת אתר נחיתה בטוח. אזור שנראה חלק כשהוא נראה ממסלול עשוי למעשה להיות זרוע בולדרים או מכשולים אחרים, אומר וויליאמס. תוכנה של חללית חייבת להיות מסוגלת להעריך את השטח בעצמה.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> ההסתמכות על מפעילים אנושיים על פני כדור הארץ אינה ריאלית, אומר וויליאמס, מכיוון שיש פיגור ארוך מדי בתקשורת בגלל מהירות האור הסופית. &quot;אתה תמיד בפיגור של 2.5 שניות.&quot;</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> למרות זאת, הירח נותר יעד מושך, וב-26 באוגוסט, יפן תנסה שוב. סוכנות החלל של המדינה אמורה לשגר את משימת הנחתת החכמה שלה לחקירת ירח, או SLIM, ממרכז החלל טנגשימה. לא הוכרז תאריך נחיתה, אבל אם הכל ילך כשורה, הגשושית - שתוכננה כהדגמה טכנולוגית - תגיע בסופו של דבר ליד מכתש שיולי בצידו הקרוב של הירח.</p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/082323_kk_moon-landing_feat-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="185749" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/082323_kk_moon-landing_feat-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title> הפאזל הגנטי של כרומוזום Y הושלם סוף סוף</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/new-dna-telomere-chromosomes-pangenome<dc:creator><![CDATA[Tina Hesman Saey]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Wed, 23 Aug 2023 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Genetics]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3130586 </guid><description><![CDATA[New analyses of the human Y chromosome reveal millions of new bases and different locations for the same gene in different people.]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<p>כרומוזום ה-Y האנושי, האחראי על קביעת המין הגברי, עבר סוף סוף בדיקה מקצה לקצה.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> החוקרים רצפו את הכרומוזום, המכיל גנים רבים המעורבים בייצור זרע ובפוריות, מזכר ממוצא אירופאי. הבנייה החדשה של טלומר לטלומר, או קצה לקצה, <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-023-06457-y" target="_blank" rel="noopener">מוסיפה יותר מ-30 מיליון בסיסי DNA</a> לכרומוזום Y שהורכב בעבר, כך מדווח הצוות באינטרנט ב-23 באוגוסט ב- <em>Nature</em> . זהו החלק האחרון של <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/new-human-pangenome-biology-dna-diversity">הפנגנום האנושי</a> , מאמץ לקטלג את כל ה-DNA האנושי ( <em>SN: 5/10/23</em> ).</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> כרומוזום Y הוא הקטן ביותר מבין הכרומוזומים האנושיים. &quot;בעבר, אנשים חשבו שזו רק מגרש גרוטאות לחומר גנומי אנושי, וזה משרת רק מטרה אחת... לקבוע מין זכר&quot;, אומר יון-פאי כריס לאו, גנטיקאי אנושי מאוניברסיטת קליפורניה, סן פרנסיסקו, שלא היה מעורב בעבודה. כמו הקומיקאי רודני דינגרפילד, כרומוזום Y לא זוכה לכבוד, הוא אומר.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> אבל ברור שה-Y עושה יותר מאשר קביעת מין זכר, אומר לאו. חלק מהזכרים מאבדים את כרומוזום Y מחלק מהתאים שלהם. האובדן מעמיד אותם <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/men-who-lose-y-chromosome-have-high-risk-cancer">בסיכון לסרטן</a> , מחלת אלצהיימר ומחלות אחרות ( <em>SN: 26/10/14</em> ). כרומוזום Y ייחוס מלא באמת יאפשר לחוקרים להבין טוב יותר את התפקיד שהכרומוזום ממלא בגוף, הוא אומר.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> למרות שהוא קטן, כרומוזום Y הפחיד חוקרים רבים מכיוון שיש לו כל כך הרבה פיסות DNA שחוזרות על עצמן, אומר אדם פיליפי, חוקר ביואינפורמטיקה במכון הלאומי לחקר הגנום האנושי של ארה&quot;ב בבת&#39;סדה, מד., שהוביל את הפרויקט.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> ישנם רצפים חוזרים ונשנים של אותיות DNA, או בסיסים - אבני הבניין נושאות המידע של ה-DNA - מונחים מקצה לקצה ונמתחים למיליוני בסיסים כמו שורות אינסופיות לכאורה של חלקי פאזל זהים. בחלקים מסוימים של הכרומוזום יש את חלקי הפאזל הפוכים. וכמה קטעי DNA מכילים פלינדרומים; אותיות ה-DNA נקראות אותו דבר בשני הכיוונים. אז יש עותקים מרובים של גנים בודדים.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> כל החזרה הזו מקשה לדעת לאן בדיוק בפאזל הולך חלק מסוים, אז מדענים שמרו את החלקים החוזרים האלה לסוף, אומר פיליפי. &quot;כשאתה מרכיב שוב את הפאזל שלך אתה תמיד שומר את החלקים החוזרים על עצמם, כמו הדשא או העצים או השמים, לסוף.&quot;</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> מחקר נפרד, שפורסם גם הוא באינטרנט ב-23 באוגוסט ב- <em>Nature</em> , רשם את כל כרומוזום ה-Y מ-43 אנשים, כולל 21 ממוצא אפריקאי. מחקר זה מצא שאורכו של כרומוזום המין הזכרי יכול <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-023-06425-6" target="_blank" rel="noopener">להשתנות</a> מאדם לאדם במיליוני בסיסי DNA, כלומר אצל אנשים מסוימים, לכרומוזום יש עותקים נוספים של גנים מסוימים או פיסות DNA אחרות. לדוגמה, לזכרים עשויים להיות בין 23 ל-39 עותקים של גנים TSPY, המעורבים בייצור זרע, מצאו החוקרים.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> כרומוזומי Y מלאים ממספר אנשים עזר לפילפי ועמיתיו להבהיר תעלומה. לכרומוזום הייחוס הישן היה הגן TSPY2 ממוקם ליד קצה אחד של הכרומוזום. אבל גרסת הטלומרים לטלומרים הראתה אותו קרוב לצנטרומר - החלק הצבוט של הכרומוזום - ולאחור בהשוואה להתייחסות.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “We confirmed that it was correct in our assembly, so then we were just assuming that it was an error in the old assembly,” Phillippy says. But the second study showed that both versions were right. TSPY2 has jumped around on the chromosome. Some people have it at one location, while others have it at the other.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Having multiple copies of TSPY genes, and the varying location of TSPY2, may affect the genes&#39; activity and effect on sperm production, Lau says. Some previous studies have hinted that varying numbers of copies may affect fertility, while other studies have found no relationship. The more precise information from the new studies may help settle the debate, or at least give researchers more clues about how the genes influence sperm production, he says.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The new research may help scientists learn more about the evolution of the Y chromosome, Phillippy says. And eventually, studying its genes and their variants may lead to a better understanding of fertility and treatments for infertility, he says, but such medical applications are probably years away.</p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/082223_ti_y_chromosome_feat-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="100853" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/082223_ti_y_chromosome_feat-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title> Some leaves in tropical forests may be getting too hot for photosynthesis</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/leaves-tropical-forests-photosynthesis-heat-limit<dc:creator><![CDATA[Nikk Ogasa]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Wed, 23 Aug 2023 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Climate]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3130583 </guid><description><![CDATA[Climate change may be forcing some tropical leaves to stop photosynthesis and die. It’s still unclear what effect this will have on entire forests.]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<p>Like people, leaves have their limits when it comes to heat.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Scientists first reported in 1864 that the leaves of some plants could survive up to 50° Celsius, only to perish beyond that threshold. More than 150 years later, researchers are making similar findings. In 2021, a study of 147 tropical tree species reported that the average temperature beyond which photosynthesis failed was <a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1111/pce.14060" target="_blank" rel="noopener">46.7° C</a> .</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Now, in the upper canopies of Earth&#39;s tropical forests, roughly <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-023-06391-z" target="_blank" rel="noopener">1 in every 10,000 leaves</a> experiences temperatures at least once a year that may be too high for photosynthesis, researchers report August 23 in <em>Nature</em> .</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> That might seem a paltry sum, but a photosynthetic breakdown could harm entire forests if climate change is not halted, the scientists warn. A rise of about 4 degrees C above current temperatures in tropical forests could potentially cause wide swaths of leaves to die en masse, simulations suggest. Still, the researchers acknowledge that the prediction comes with uncertainties.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “One small possibility that we&#39;re suggesting … is an incredibly dire tipping point” beyond which tropical forests perish, Christopher Doughty, an ecologist at Northern Arizona University in Flagstaff, said at an August 21 news briefing. But “there&#39;s a lot we don&#39;t know.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> When leaves get too hot, their photosynthetic machinery — proteins that convert light energy into sugars — breaks down. Keen to figure out whether tropical forests were approaching such a threshold, Doughty and colleagues obtained data collected by <a href="https://www.jpl.nasa.gov/missions/ecosystem-spaceborne-thermal-radiometer-experiment-on-space-station-ecostress" target="_blank" rel="noopener">ECOSTRESS</a> , a thermal sensor aboard the International Space Station, which captures vegetation temperatures on Earth&#39;s surface in 70-meter pixels <strong>.</strong> That&#39;s about the area that two large tropical trees could fill.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The team compared the data with measurements from devices on the planet&#39;s surface. These included an instrument in the Amazon, mounted 64 meters high on a tower, as well as swarms of sensors taped to the bottoms of leaves in Brazil, Puerto Rico, Panama and Australia.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The analysis revealed a mosaic of temperatures in forest canopies. During periods when forests were hot and their soils were dry, temperatures across the canopy could reach an average peak of 34° C. But there was variability; some tracts exceeded 40° C.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The comparison also revealed a detail unseen by ECOSTRESS — a scatter within the mosaic. Individual leaf temperatures varied in single forest tracts, with some leaves reaching temperatures that far exceeded the tract average. About 0.01 percent of the time, upper canopy leaves sweltered at temperatures above the 46.7° C threshold, the team found.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The researchers also analyzed data from leaf-warming experiments in Brazil, Puerto Rico and Australia. These experiments showed that each degree of ambient warming had a disproportionate impact on leaf temperatures. For example, when Amazon leaves were subjected to an additional 2 degrees C of ambient warming, maximum leaf temperatures rose from 42.8° to 50.9° C.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The team used the experimental data, along with the satellite and ground-based data, to simulate the future of tropical forests under climate change. Most forests could endure about 4 degrees C of warming above current levels before trees lose all their leaves, and potentially die, the simulations suggest. That amount of warming might be possible by 2100 in a worst-case scenario in which greenhouse gas emissions continue rising through the century, the researchers say.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Still, there&#39;s a lot of uncertainty. That&#39;s in part because the adaptive capabilities of different tree species and how the deaths of individual leaves impact a tree&#39;s mortality aren&#39;t well understood.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The study may even overestimate vulnerability by “assuming that when leaves hit this critical temperature, they die,” says ecologist Christopher Still of Oregon State University in Corvallis. That&#39;s possible, he says, but we don&#39;t fully understand how long it takes various temperatures to kill different species&#39; leaves.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Predicting the future of these forests will also require more insights into what&#39;s unfolding beneath the canopy, says ecologist Marielle Smith of Bangor University in Wales. “There is still a question mark over the role of small trees and understory leaves, which aren&#39;t going to be as hot.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Among tropical forests, the Amazon may be most vulnerable to the type of reckoning predicted by the researchers. “There&#39;s more trees dying [there] now than there were 10 years ago or 20 years ago. We don&#39;t see that in Africa,” Doughty said. That could be because “temperatures are a bit hotter … in the Amazon than in Africa.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Some researchers have been warning for years that climate change and deforestation could trigger <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/amazon-tipping-trouble-climate-cerrado">large parts of the Amazon</a> to transform into savanna and shrubland ( <em>SN: 6/16/23</em> ).</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “This is a glimpse into a potential tipping point. It&#39;s not saying that the tropical forests are now going to be savannas tomorrow,” study coauthor and ecologist Joshua Fisher of Chapman University in Orange, Calif., said at the briefing. “We can now see this insight … and because we can see that, it means we can act.”</p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/082223_no_tropical_photosynthesis_feat-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="1753833" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/082223_no_tropical_photosynthesis_feat-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title> Pre-Inca people stomped salutes to their thunder god on a special dance floor</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/inca-stomped-salutes-thunder-god-dance-floor<dc:creator><![CDATA[Bruce Bower]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Tue, 22 Aug 2023 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Archaeology]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3130496 </guid><description><![CDATA[Excavation of a drumlike platform in the Andes turned up a structure seemingly designed to absorb shocks and emit resonant sounds when stomped upon.]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<p>Roughly a century before the Inca empire came to power in AD 1400, blasts of human-produced thunder may have rumbled off a ridge high in the Andes Mountains.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> New evidence indicates that people who lived there around 700 years ago stomped rhythmically on a special dance floor that amplified their pounding into a thunderous boom as they worshipped a thunder god.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Excavations at a high-altitude site in Peru called Viejo Sangayaico have revealed how members of a regional farming and herding group, the Chocorvos, constructed this reverberating platform, says archaeologist Kevin Lane of the University of Buenos Aires. Different layers of soil, ash and guano created a floor that absorbed shocks while emitting resonant sounds when people stomped on it. This ceremonial surface <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0278416523000314" target="_blank" rel="noopener">worked like a large drum</a> that groups of 20 to 25 people could have played with their feet, Lane reports in the September <em>Journal of Anthropological Archaeology</em> .</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> These findings, from a ridgetop ritual area that faces a nearby mountain peak, provide a rare glimpse of <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/ancient-trumpets-played-eerie-notes">the role played by sound and dance in ancient societies</a> ( <em>SN: 11/18/10</em> ).</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> While working at Viejo Sangayaico in 2014, Lane&#39;s team first noticed that one of two open-air platforms located in a ritual area sounded hollow when people walked on it.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> A later excavation of part of the platform uncovered six sediment deposits consisting of various mixes of silty clay, sand, ash and other materials. Ashy layers within a section of guano from animals such as llamas and alpacas included small cavities that helped to generate drumlike sounds from the platform&#39;s surface, Lane says.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> His team acoustically tested the platform by stomping on it one at a time and in groups of two to four while measuring the noise produced. The same was done while a circle of four people stomp-danced across the platform.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The resulting sounds ranged in intensity from 60 to 80 decibels, roughly equivalent to between a loud conversation and a noisy restaurant, Lane says. Larger groups of Chocorvos dancers, possibly accompanied by singing and musical instruments, would have raised a much bigger racket.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Spanish historical documents describe Chocorvos beliefs in thunder, lightning, earthquake and water deities. Supernatural convictions may have inspired ancient ceremonies at Viejo Sangayaico that included stomp dancing aimed at emulating a thunder god&#39;s signature blasts, Lane suggests. In line with that suggestion, remains of a possible temple near the percussive platform included pottery pieces displaying snake images that, in the local Quechua language, refer to water or rivers and, in some instances, lightning.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Pre-Inca stomp dancing may also have influenced a dance practiced by the Chorcovos and other Andean groups in the mid-1500s, after Spanish conquest of the Incas in 1532, Lane suspects. The Chorcovos had been subjects of the Inca Empire for most of its run. As part of a resistance movement against Spanish culture called <em>Taki Onqoy</em> , Andeans danced and trembled ecstatically in circles, possibly to evoke spirits of their traditional deities.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Finding another percussive platform along with artifacts related to water and lightning rituals at other ancient Andean sites would better support Lane&#39;s argument that sound-amplifying platforms provided a way to honor a thunder god as part of broader ceremonial events, says anthropological archaeologist Kylie Quave. To that end, researchers can now excavate platforms at other sites to check for guano layers and other elements of drumlike dance floors, says Quave, of George Washington University in Washington, DC</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Whether makers of the Viejo Sangayaico platform designed it to amplify sounds, Chocorvos people could have discovered the surface&#39;s drumlike properties and then used it for ceremonial dancing, says Miriam Kolar, an archaeoacoustics researcher at Stanford University.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Evidence of other sound-altering structures has also been found at Andean sites older than Viejo Sangayaico, Kolar says. Conch-shell horns found in a ceremonial center at <a href="https://culturalacoustics.org/#about" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a roughly 3,000-year-old site called Chavin de Huántar</a> could have produced a range of sounds, from nearly pure tones to loud roars, that were emphasized in ceremonially important passages and ventilation shafts, Kolar and colleagues have found.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> People today who live near Viejo Sangayaico say that another ancient site in the area contains a similar platform that resonates underfoot. Lane and colleagues have yet to visit that site.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Finding more sound-amplifying platforms will depend on “having your ear attuned to how different parts of a site sound,” Lane says, “which is something that archaeologists rarely do.”</p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/081823_bb_stomp_feat.jpg-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="1600410" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/081823_bb_stomp_feat.jpg-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title> Health risks can persist at least 2 years after COVID-19, new data suggest</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/health-risks-persist-2-years-covid-19<dc:creator><![CDATA[Betsy Ladyzhets]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Mon, 21 Aug 2023 16:02:03 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Health & Medicine]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3130511 </guid><description><![CDATA[U.S. veterans who tested positive for COVID-19 in 2020 remain at higher risk for many long COVID conditions, from heart disease to gastrointestinal issues. ]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<p>The risk of experiencing such health issues as diabetes, fatigue or blood clots can persist for at least two years after a coronavirus infection, a new study suggests.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> That finding is based on the health records of about 140,000 US veterans infected with SARS-CoV-2 early in the pandemic, compared with nearly 6 million more who did not test positive for the virus that causes COVID-19. Researchers used veterans&#39; new diagnoses of health issues, lab results and prescription records to identify health problems that emerged starting a month after getting COVID-19.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Even two years after their infections, people who had COVID-19 were at <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41591-023-02521-2" target="_blank" rel="noopener">higher risk for many health issues</a> — ranging from heart disease to gastrointestinal problems, the team reports August 21 in <em>Nature Medicine.</em></p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Patients who were hospitalized during their initial COVID-19 cases were more likely to experience these health problems, the team found. But those with milder initial infections were still at higher risk for about one-third of the medical issues that the scientists analyzed, compared with people who didn&#39;t test positive. As most COVID-19 cases are milder, this group represents a greater burden to the health care system, says Ziyad Al-Aly, a clinical epidemiologist at the Veterans Affairs Saint Louis Health Care System.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The most common problems align with common long COVID symptoms identified in other studies, such as fatigue, memory problems, loss of smell, blood clots, metabolic issues and gastrointestinal problems. For example, initially hospitalized patients were about 1.88 times as likely to experience acute gastritis, or stomach inflammation as those with no record of COVID-19 at two years after infection; non-hospitalized patients had a risk factor of 1.44 times.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “Long COVID represents a significant burden of disease and disability,” says Al-Aly, who is also affiliated with Washington University in Saint Louis. A coronavirus infection can “result in heart disease, result in brain problems,” and many other long-term risks which scientists are just beginning to understand.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> While the patients in the study were predominantly male and older, the findings align with Upinder Singh&#39;s experience seeing patients at Stanford University&#39;s long COVID clinic. “This is an important set of data,” she says.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The findings also match patients&#39; experiences with persistent symptoms, says Lisa McCorkell, a long COVID patient and researcher at the Patient-Led Research Collaborative. In particular, she noted that autonomic nervous system issues, which can lead to symptoms like pain and fatigue, persisted for both groups of patients in the study and even increased over time for the non-hospitalized group. Many people with long COVID have also been diagnosed with this condition.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Al-Aly and colleagues examined 77 medical problems that may arise after an acute COVID-19 case. Two years after infection, COVID-19 patients who hadn&#39;t been hospitalized for severe symptoms early on – about 120,000 of those in the study — remained at higher risk for 24 of the 77 issues, compared with people who hadn&#39;t tested positive. Those who had been hospitalized were at higher risk for 50 of the 77 issues, suggesting that worse symptoms in the acute phase can contribute to a greater chance of long COVID.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Initially hospitalized patients also had higher risks of going to the hospital again or dying in the two years following their COVID-19 infections, the researchers found. These risks tapered off for people who had milder cases early on, as did some specific health risks, including low blood oxygen levels and memory problems.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Overall, Al-Aly and colleagues found that for every 1,000 people infected with the coronavirus, a cumulative 150 years of healthy life is lost due to these patient&#39;s struggles with persistent symptoms. This finding demonstrates “how destructive long COVID can be,” McCorkell says. Other studies, such as the <a href="https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/covid19/pulse/long-covid.htm" target="_blank" rel="noopener">US Census&#39; Household Pulse Survey</a> , similarly found that long COVID can severely restrict day-to-day life for many patients.<s></s></p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The study does have limitations. Because it used <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/researchers-fill-the-gaps-long-covid-data">electronic health records</a> , only information available to the medical system can be analyzed ( <em>SN: 11/28/22</em> ). The researchers couldn&#39;t assess some common long COVID symptoms that are not typically captured by doctor&#39;s visits, such as post-exertional malaise (PEM). “When it comes to a symptom clinicians have never heard of before, like PEM, [health records don&#39;t capture] the full picture,” says Jaime Seltzer, an expert on myalgic encephalomyelitis/chronic fatigue syndrome who heads scientific and medical outreach with the advocacy group #MEAction. This chronic condition shares many symptoms with long COVID.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Seltzer also notes that the study may be skewed by its veteran population. About 90 percent of veteran records included were from men, while long COVID and other similar chronic conditions are more common among women. Some health issues that are more common for women with long COVID, such as long-term neurological and endocrine symptoms, may be underrepresented, she says.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The study also didn&#39;t include people who may have been infected by SARS-CoV-2 but failed to get a positive test result in early 2020, when tests were not widely available. In fact, many of the people included as controls could have “actually had COVID-19,” Singh says.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Despite the caveats, <a>with</a> <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/expect-coronavirus-fall-endemic-variants">COVID-19 transmission rising again</a> in recent weeks, the study offers a reminder that “it&#39;s still worth it to protect yourself,” Al-Aly says ( <em>SN: 8/21/23</em> ). Even a mild infection could lead to health problems in the months or years that follow.</p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/082123_bl_long-covid_feat-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="241074" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/082123_bl_long-covid_feat-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title> This extreme star might have huge tidal waves</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/extreme-star-tidal-waves-astronomy<dc:creator><![CDATA[Liz Kruesi]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Mon, 21 Aug 2023 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Astronomy]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3130471 </guid><description><![CDATA[Gravitational forces between two orbiting stars might be creating huge waves of plasma on one of the stars that break and crash to the surface.]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<p>Like ocean surf smashing on a sandy beach, enormous waves of plasma may crash onto the surface of one massive star.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The star is part of a pair, stretched and pulled by its companion&#39;s gravity. That gravitational tug-of-war causes the star&#39;s brightness to change drastically and rhythmically. Now, a computer simulation suggests that this steady heartbeat of starlight <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41550-023-02036-3" target="_blank" rel="noopener">is caused by giant tidal waves undulating and breaking on the star&#39;s surface</a> , researchers report August 10 in <em>Nature Astronomy</em> . The height of the waves could be up to three times the diameter of the sun.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “It&#39;s quite rare to see these really kind of dramatic but transformative moments in action,” says astrophysicist Morgan MacLeod of the Harvard-Smithsonian Center for Astrophysics in Cambridge, Mass.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The star system, dubbed MACHO 80.7443.1718, sits about 160,000 light-years away from Earth in the Large Magellanic Cloud. It hosts one visible star that is 35 times the mass of the sun and another unseen star of at least 10 solar masses. About once a month, as they orbit each other, they pass near enough that gravitational forces raise tides on both stars&#39; surfaces, scientists suspect, much the way <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/matter-gravity-0">the moon tugs on Earth&#39;s oceans</a> ( <em>SN: 4/5/11</em> ).</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> On the stars, though, that tug would be substantially more extreme. “Instead of being a few meters tall, [the tide] can be 10 percent of the diameter of the star” that&#39;s visible, says astrophysicist Jim Fuller of Caltech, who was not part of the study. On a star as big as that visible star — about 24 times as wide as the sun — that corresponds to a tidal wave roughly 3.3 million kilometers tall.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The new study, Fuller says, “shows how complicated and interesting the dynamics get when you have an extreme system like this.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Astronomers can&#39;t see the shapes of these stars through a telescope, but they can track how the brighter star&#39;s light changes over time. While the brightness of most known “heartbeat stars” changes by about a tenth of a percent, the brightness of this system changes by 20 percent.</p><div class="wp-block-sciencenews-content-sidebar" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Stellar dance</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Roughly once a month, two stars about 160,000 light-years away from Earth pass close enough to one another that gravitational forces should raise tides in the plasma on both stars&#39; surfaces. A computer simulation (shown) suggests that the gravitational tug-of-war raises enormous tides in the plasma on the larger star&#39;s surface. </p><figure class="wp-block-image "><picture class="sn-responsive-image"><source srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/081723_lk_star_tidal_waves_inline_desktop-648x450.jpg 648w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/081723_lk_star_tidal_waves_inline_desktop-552x383.jpg 552w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/081723_lk_star_tidal_waves_inline_desktop-268x186.jpg 268w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/081723_lk_star_tidal_waves_inline_desktop.jpg 680w" width="648" height="450" media="(min-width: 600px)" sizes="(max-width: 1023px) 100vw, 680px"></source><source srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/081723_lk_star_tidal_waves_inline_mobile-648x450.jpg 648w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/081723_lk_star_tidal_waves_inline_mobile-552x383.jpg 552w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/081723_lk_star_tidal_waves_inline_mobile-268x186.jpg 268w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/081723_lk_star_tidal_waves_inline_mobile.jpg 680w" width="648" height="450"></source><img src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/081723_lk_star_tidal_waves_inline_mobile-648x450.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large" alt="An image of 4 illustrations put together. The first shows the two stars orbiting each other on zero days, the next at 15.1 days, the third at 17.4 days and the last at 22 days." decoding="async" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/081723_lk_star_tidal_waves_inline_mobile-648x450.jpg 648w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/081723_lk_star_tidal_waves_inline_mobile-552x383.jpg 552w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/081723_lk_star_tidal_waves_inline_mobile-268x186.jpg 268w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/081723_lk_star_tidal_waves_inline_mobile.jpg 680w" sizes="(max-width: 1023px) 100vw, 680px" data-attachment-id="3130475" data-permalink="https://www.sciencenews.org/081723_lk_star_tidal_waves_inline_mobile" data-orig-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/081723_lk_star_tidal_waves_inline_mobile.jpg" data-orig-size="680,472" data-comments-opened="0" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="081723_lk_star_tidal_waves_inline_mobile" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/081723_lk_star_tidal_waves_inline_mobile-552x383.jpg" data-large-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/081723_lk_star_tidal_waves_inline_mobile-648x450.jpg" /></picture><figcaption> <span class="credit mobile-credit wp-credit-3130475">M. MacLeod and A. Loeb/ <em>Nature Astronomy</em> 2023</span> <span class="credit desktop-credit wp-credit-3130476">M. MacLeod and A. Loeb/ <em>Nature Astronomy</em> 2023</span></figcaption></figure></div><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> MacLeod wanted to know how the dynamics of this star system lead to those visible changes. So he and Harvard astronomer Avi Loeb simulated how plasma moves on and between these stars as they orbit one another.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The waves can get big enough that they actually break and crash across the brighter star&#39;s surface, the study suggests. When an ocean wave is far from shore, it&#39;s a rolling, undulating wave. But as it comes closer to shore, it rises and collapses on itself. “Something kind of parallel is happening here,” MacLeod says. The top of the wave steepens, “gets out of phase with the bottom, and it folds over on itself, and it crashes.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> After it crashes on the stellar surface, he says, “debris that&#39;s thrown off is fed into this atmosphere around the star,” like the foamy surf left behind on a beach. As the waves crash, energy is lost. That crashing, the study suggests, causes the stars&#39; orbits to shrink, meaning eventually these stars could collide and possibly merge.</p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/081723_lk_star_tidal_waves_feat-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="151204" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/081723_lk_star_tidal_waves_feat-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title> What should we expect from the coronavirus this fall?</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/expect-coronavirus-fall-endemic-variants<dc:creator><![CDATA[Erin Garcia de Jesús]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Mon, 21 Aug 2023 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Health & Medicine]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3130457 </guid><description><![CDATA[The virus may be reaching a phase of baseline circulation, says epidemiologist Aubree Gordon. But it’s unclear what will happen in the next few months.]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<p>Across the United States, thousands of people with COVID-19 are being hospitalized each week and the number is steadily trending up — a sure sign that overall cases have also been on the rise.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Levels of detectable coronavirus in wastewater samples and the proportion of tests that come back positive have certainly been ticking up since June, data from the US Centers for Disease Control and Prevention show. Both metrics indicate rising cases at the national level, albeit indirectly. It&#39;s hard to get a good grasp of the start of new surges or know what&#39;s happening within communities, in part because states are no longer required to report new cases, a result of <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/covid-public-health-emergency-ending-tests-vaccines-drugs-research">the US public health emergency ending in May</a> ( <em>SN: 5/4/23</em> ).</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> We do know the worst of the pandemic is largely behind us. While the virus can, and does, still spread far and wide, its transmission isn&#39;t the overwhelming crush that characterized the pandemic&#39;s first years.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Amid a backdrop of ever-evolving variants — including a new version of omicron designated BA.2.86 that is <a href="https://www.reuters.com/world/us/us-cdc-tracks-new-lineage-virus-that-causes-covid-2023-08-18/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">under close watch</a> from global and US health agencies — most infections are now less deadly than the pandemic&#39;s early days. Data from blood banks show that as of September 2022, <a href="https://www.cdc.gov/mmwr/volumes/72/wr/mm7222a3.htm" target="_blank" rel="noopener">around 96 percent of people in the United States had been vaccinated</a> , infected with the virus or both, which can help reduce the severity of future infections. And, a new booster shot — designed to target relatives of <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/covid-xbb15-kraken-omicron-variant-virus">a viral lineage dubbed XBB</a> — should be available at the end of September ( <em>SN: 1/13/23</em> ).</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Even with those rays of hope, our future with SARS-CoV-2, the virus that causes COVID, is unclear. The virus is not going anywhere; new variants will continue to appear with varying degrees of infectiousness and severity. How many people might fall ill or die on average each year? אנחנו לא יודעים.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Answering that question requires the virus to have entered its endemic phase — when it regularly circulates at some baseline amount. Even then, endemic does not mean benign. In that phase, people will still get sick with COVID, some severely so. But far fewer will land in the hospital or die in a “normal” year than during the pandemic years.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> To see if this fall — our fourth with COVID and the first without a public health emergency in place — could possibly be the start of the coronavirus&#39; endemic phase, <em>Science News</em> spoke with epidemiologist Aubree Gordon of the University of Michigan in Ann Arbor. This conversation has been edited for length and clarity.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <strong><em>SN:</em></strong> <strong>How are things different this fall than in previous years?</strong></p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <strong>Gordon:</strong> One of the big differences … is that at this point pretty much everybody … has some sort of immunity against SARS-CoV-2.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> A majority of people have hybrid immunity, meaning that most people in the United States, or a good chunk of them, have been not only vaccinated but had an infection. For a majority of people that did not choose to get vaccinated, most of those individuals have been infected a few times. And some of the people who were vaccinated have been infected a few times.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> What that means is that we have a higher level of immunity against the virus. Obviously, that&#39;s not preventing people from getting infected or reinfected. But it&#39;s certainly helping to reduce the severity of those infections when they happen.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <strong><em>SN:</em></strong> <strong>What have we learned about what reinfections tend to look like?</strong></p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <strong>Gordon:</strong> They tend to be a lot milder than a first infection. But severe reinfections still do occur. And when you talk about severe, you&#39;re not only thinking about fatal infections, which are of course the most severe, but also infections that cause hospitalization or may cause long-term symptoms.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <strong><em>SN:</em></strong> <strong>A new booster this fall will replace the omicron variant with a new one. Is it important to get this booster?</strong></p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <strong>Gordon:</strong> I think booster shots are definitely advised, particularly for individuals who are more likely to have severe disease.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> I had really hoped that we would have arrived at a point where SARS-CoV-2 was looking like a seasonal coronavirus, one that causes symptoms of the common cold, and was therefore less severe than influenza. What we&#39;re still seeing for SARS-CoV-2 is that it is more severe than flu. It&#39;s still causing a lot more deaths on an annual basis than flu is causing. I&#39;d say it&#39;s not clear if we&#39;ve gotten to the fully endemic level yet [when transmission falls into an average range from year to year].</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <strong><em>SN:</em></strong> <strong>Where do you think we are on the spectrum between pandemic and endemic?</strong></p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <strong>Gordon:</strong> I think we&#39;re getting pretty close to what endemic will look like. I don&#39;t know if we&#39;ll be fully at that level for this next season, or if it might take another season or two for us to get there.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> I will say that I&#39;m kind of hoping we&#39;re not at the endemic level yet. At least based on last year, because there were a substantial number of deaths in the United States — 244,000 was the CDC estimate. It&#39;s four or five times higher than a severe seasonal influenza season in the United States.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> But [COVID disease severity] has been trending downward over the last many months. The hope would be that we continue to see that downward trend in the number of severe and fatal cases. If [COVID] had hit its endemic level, we would expect some season-to-season fluctuations, but it&#39;d be fluctuating around that number rather than continuing a downward trend of being less and less severe.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <strong><em>SN:</em></strong> <strong>Have researchers learned anything over the past year about what endemic might look like?</strong></p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <strong>Gordon:</strong> I think we&#39;re zeroing in on what endemic will look like. It&#39;s, I think, become fairly clear that this is going to be a regular infection that people may get more often than flu. Maybe the virus will start changing less. For adults [who are more likely than kids to get severely ill], it is probably looking like it&#39;s going to [be as dangerous as] influenza if not [more dangerous]. We will see for sure.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> I had thought that everybody would need maybe a vaccination and then one or two infections to get at whatever the endemic level would be. It&#39;s possible that you need a little bit broader immunity [to protect against more variants of the virus] and more exposures to hit that endemic level.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <strong><em>SN:</em></strong> <strong>What do you think experts might learn this fall?</strong></p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <strong>Gordon:</strong> One thing that we&#39;ll look at this fall is how different it is from last fall. Because if we&#39;re still seeing a downward trajectory, then maybe we haven&#39;t yet hit the endemic level. Or we may see something that looks quite similar to last fall, which would tell us that perhaps we&#39;ve arrived at that endemic level.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> There is season-to-season variability, there are differences in variants, and we have new variants arising, which will all contribute on a yearly basis to how severe the SARS-CoV-2 season is. We have that for flu. CDC estimates for recent flu seasons, excluding the pandemic ones, were anywhere from 12,000 to 52,000 deaths a year. That&#39;s quite a bit of variability.</p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/081723_eg_covid-fall_feat-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="189049" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/081723_eg_covid-fall_feat-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title> JWST&#39;s hunt for distant galaxies keeps turning up surprises</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/jwst-distant-galaxies-surprises-space<dc:creator><![CDATA[Lisa Grossman]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Sun, 20 Aug 2023 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Astronomy]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3130017 </guid><description><![CDATA[In its first year, the James Webb Space Telescope has found many galaxies from the early universe that are bigger, brighter and more mature than expected. ]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<p class="has-drop-cap">When Brant Robertson saw a new measurement of the distance to a familiar galaxy, he laughed out loud.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> For more than a decade, the galaxy had been a contender for the most distant ever observed. In 2012, Robertson and colleagues used data from the Hubble Space Telescope to show that the galaxy&#39;s light had shone across the universe from about 13.3 billion years ago — less than 400 million years into the universe&#39;s existence.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Not everyone believed it. “We got a lot of flak,” recalls Robertson, an astrophysicist at the University of California, Santa Cruz. “It seemed too implausible that it was at such a great distance.” It felt like he was going around claiming to have seen the Loch Ness monster.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> But in September, the James Webb Space Telescope, JWST for short, aimed its massive mirror and sensitive spectrograph at the same galaxy and showed that Robertson and his colleagues were right. The galaxy&#39;s light is indeed incredibly old, dating to just 390 million years after the Big Bang. It was like someone had drained the lake, and the monster was sitting there at the bottom.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> And this galactic Nessie is not alone. So far, in its first year of observations, JWST has turned up thousands of distant galaxies dating to the early universe, many more than astronomers had expected. Some of those galaxies are brighter, more massive or more mature than astronomers would have thought. They are now scratching their heads trying to explain how the galaxies could have grown up so fast. </p><div class="wp-block-image  has-alignleft" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><figure class="alignleft size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="450" height="450" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/081223_galaxies_inline1-450x450.jpg" alt="A James Webb Space Telescope image of Maisie's Galaxy, which appears as a series of red pixels surrounded by clumps of blue, green and brown pixels." class="wp-image-3130154" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/081223_galaxies_inline1-450x450.jpg 450w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/081223_galaxies_inline1-383x383.jpg 383w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/081223_galaxies_inline1-186x186.jpg 186w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/081223_galaxies_inline1-580x580.jpg 580w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/081223_galaxies_inline1-214x214.jpg 214w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/081223_galaxies_inline1.jpg 680w" sizes="(max-width: 450px) 100vw, 450px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3130154">Studying Maisie&#39;s Galaxy, which dates to about 400 million years after the Big Bang, helped astronomers gain confidence in distance estimates derived from initial JWST data.</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3130154">S. FINKELSTEIN <em>et al</em> /arXiv.org 2022 ( <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">CC BY 4.0</a> )</span></figcaption></figure></div><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> A lot of the extreme distances still need to be confirmed, but initial evidence suggests there&#39;s reason to believe that many, if not most, of the galaxies really are that far away.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “I was expecting to find some galaxies at this [distance]. Some people were pessimistic; I wasn&#39;t,” says Steven Finkelstein, an astrophysicist at the University of Texas at Austin. “But I was not this optimistic. I thought, &#39;Yeah, yeah, we know what we&#39;re going to see.&#39; And I was wrong.”</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The Hubble Space Telescope&#39;s distant galaxies</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> For longtime galaxy hunters, JWST&#39;s bounty may feel like déjà vu. In the 1990s, Hubble took a long, deep look at an apparently blank patch of sky, just to see what was there. The result was thousands of galaxies, some captured as they looked when the universe was only a billion years old.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Those galaxies looked mature, like they had already been through multiple rounds of supernova explosions and star formation. Thus, they were not the first to form in the universe, astronomers realized. The first galaxies must date even further back.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The hunt for those original galaxies was part of the motivation for building JWST, says astrophysicist Erica Nelson of the University of Colorado Boulder. “The reason we have JWST is, they launched Hubble and saw that the things in the early universe were very evolved,” she says. “They were like, &#39;Wow! There are galaxies way earlier than we thought&#39; ” — even further back in time than Hubble can see.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Hubble wasn&#39;t designed to see all the way back to the universe&#39;s beginning. The telescope is sensitive to ultraviolet, visible and near-infrared wavelengths of light. But by the time light from the universe&#39;s early days reaches us, it has stretched all the way into infrared wavelengths that are longer than Hubble&#39;s (or human) eyes can see. That&#39;s because the universe is expanding; everything in it is moving away from everything else. And as light sources move away from us, their light stretches — the wavelengths of light grow longer, or redder.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The amount of stretching of that light, known as the redshift, is astronomers&#39; proxy for cosmic distance and age. The present-day universe is at redshift zero. A redshift of 1 corresponds to about 6 billion years after the Big Bang. A redshift of 4 is about 1.5 billion years after the Big Bang, and so on.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> In 1995, redshift 4 was the furthest back that Hubble could detect. Over the next 20 years, upgrades to the telescope and new observing techniques pushed the frontier back to redshift 7, which corresponds to 800 million years after the Big Bang. In 2012, the galaxy that Robertson studied appeared at a possible, though at the time unconfirmed, redshift of 11.9. Later, a galaxy called GN-z11 clocked in at a redshift of 11.1, or 400 million years after the Big Bang.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> These tantalizing discoveries set off a search for even more distant galaxies. “This has kind of become a game in extragalactic astronomy, where everyone wants to find the highest redshift, most distant galaxy,” astrophysicist Jeyhan Kartaltepe of the Rochester Institute of Technology in New York said in April in Minneapolis at an American Physical Society meeting. “Become the new record holder, right? It&#39;s fun.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> By 2016, when GN-z11 was discovered, the hunt had stalled. Astronomers had wrung everything they could out of existing technology.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “It really requires JWST to push to even earlier times,” Kartaltepe said, “which we need to understand the very beginnings of galaxy formation.” </p><figure class="wp-block-image alignwide size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1030" height="580" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/081223_galaxies_inline2_1030.jpg" alt="A JWST Advanced Deep Extragalactic Survey image showing hundreds of galaxies that appear to date to within 650 million years of the Big Bang on two black rectangles with a white overall background." class="wp-image-3130155" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/081223_galaxies_inline2_1030.jpg 1030w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/081223_galaxies_inline2_1030-680x383.jpg 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/081223_galaxies_inline2_1030-800x450.jpg 800w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/081223_galaxies_inline2_1030-330x186.jpg 330w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/081223_galaxies_inline2_1030-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1030px) 100vw, 1030px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3130155">The JWST Advanced Deep Extragalactic Survey, or JADES, scanned a swath of sky (shown) that has turned up hundreds of galaxies that appear to date to within 650 million years of the Big Bang (reddish dots are the most distant galaxies).</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3130155">NASA, ESA, CSA, M. Zamani/ESA and Webb</span></figcaption></figure><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Why astronomers want to find early galaxies</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The quest to find the earliest galaxies is about more than just bragging rights. These galaxies could shed light on a key event in the universe&#39;s infancy called reionization.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> In the beginning, there was the Big Bang. After that initial cataclysm, the universe continued to expand and cool. After about 372,000 years, it had cooled enough for electrons, protons and neutrons to combine into hydrogen atoms. That hydrogen gas was diffuse and opaque, plunging the universe into what astronomers call the cosmic dark ages.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Sometime during these dark ages, the first stars formed and began to clump together into galaxies with the help of an invisible and still mysterious material known as dark matter. But because of the opacity of that neutral hydrogen, all astronomers can really observe is that the universe became transparent again at about 200 million years after the Big Bang, as hydrogen atoms lost their electrons.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “We know there was a transition where the hydrogen was reionized somehow,” Robertson says. Thanks to observations with Hubble and other telescopes, “we think galaxies are very likely the agents of that process,” he says. Light from the youngest, most massive stars in those early galaxies might have knocked electrons off atoms in the hydrogen gas between galaxies. “But how that process unfolds, we have relatively little information on,” Robertson says.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> JWST can help fill in those details. Taking a census of the galaxies that were around during the era of reionization could help illuminate how it got started.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> And so, astronomers were giddy with excitement when JWST launched on Christmas Day in 2021 and started collecting data about six months later. <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/james-webb-space-telescope-first-image-nasa">The first images</a> were unveiled with great fanfare on July 12, 2022 ( <em>SN: 8/13/22, p. 30</em> ). But astronomers had to wait until the next day to download the rest of the data the telescope had acquired while getting up and running.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “We knew, somewhere, on some computer, our photons were sitting there, waiting for us to see them,” Kartaltepe said. “As soon as the data were released in July, we jumped on it and started analyzing.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Astronomers sifted through the images like a cosmic Where&#39;s Waldo, picking the reddest-looking candidate galaxies out of the pack.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Extremely distant candidates popped out quickly. In several different regions of the sky, JWST found little red dots corresponding to galaxies that appeared to be at astonishing redshifts: 10, 13, even 17. Some of the galaxies seemed small and dim, as expected. But others looked big and bright, suggesting they were heftier than astronomers would expect for such early galaxies.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “These galaxies, they&#39;re just at phenomenal distances. It&#39;s a little hard to swallow,” Robertson said in June in Cambridge, Mass., at the JWST First Light Conference. “But it&#39;s really important to actually confirm the distances to these very, very distant galaxies, and then learn about their properties.”</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The most distant galaxy ever confirmed</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Most of the cosmic distances reported for JWST galaxies so far have been preliminary estimates based on data from the telescope&#39;s cameras. The cameras scan broad areas of sky and use filters to let in certain wavelengths of light. These filters allow astronomers to estimate “photometric” redshifts.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> But to know for sure how far away a galaxy really is, astronomers need to use JWST&#39;s spectrograph. A redshift calculated from a galaxy&#39;s full spectrum of light uses 1,000 data points compared with a photometric redshift&#39;s seven data points.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “Until we have spectra, nothing is ironclad,” Nelson says.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> As part of a project called the JWST Advanced Deep Extragalactic Survey, or JADES, Robertson and colleagues collected spectra for four galaxies with photometric redshifts higher than 10 — likely close to the beginning of the era of reionization. One of the galaxies was the one Robertson studied in 2012. The distance of that galaxy, now known as JADES-GS-z11-0, was downgraded a bit, from a redshift of 11.9 to 11.58. But with one of the other galaxies, the team claimed a new record for most distant galaxy ever confirmed, with a redshift of 13.2, just 325 million years after the Big Bang.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The spectra the team analyzed were detailed enough to reveal some <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41550-023-01921-1" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">properties of the galaxies</a> , Robertson and colleagues reported in April in <em>Nature Astronomy</em> . They&#39;re all about a hundredth the size and mass of the Milky Way, but they are forming stars at a comparable rate — a lot of stars for galaxies this small. All those newborn stars produce a lot of ionizing radiation, meaning it&#39;s possible these galaxies could be some of the earliest agents of reionization, Robertson says.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> JADES has since reported <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.02468" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">about 700 more galaxies</a> whose photometric redshifts place them at redshift 8 or greater, or less than 650 million years after the Big Bang, Robertson said at the June First Light meeting. Those galaxies&#39; distances still need to be confirmed, but the sheer numbers are amazing. “We&#39;re really in a remarkable age,” Robertson said.</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Trusting JWST&#39;s measurements</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The huge galaxy haul raises another question: How many of them are likely to be at such great distances?</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> A potential record-breaking galaxy called CEERS-93316 is a cautionary tale. The galaxy was identified in JWST images taken for the Cosmic Evolution Early Release Science, or CEERS, survey. Those images put the galaxy at a photometric redshift of 16.4, or just 240 million years after the Big Bang.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “That was higher redshift than we expected to see with CEERS,” says Finkelstein, the survey&#39;s lead researcher. CEERS was designed to practice using JWST in its different observing modes and give astronomers some data to play with, not necessarily to set new records.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> In its first chunk of data, CEERS contained a surprising number of apparently high-redshift galaxies. So Finkelstein and colleagues asked the director of the Space Telescope Science Institute in Baltimore, which operates JWST, for some extra telescope time to chase down the spectra of CEERS-93316, as well as a galaxy that Finkelstein had found with a photometric redshift of about 12. He named that galaxy Maisie&#39;s Galaxy in honor of his daughter, because he found it on her ninth birthday. (Maisie didn&#39;t mind that her dad had to work that day — “I got other birthday presents,” she says, though she did wish her galaxy was the potential record holder.)</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> When the spectral data came through, Finkelstein&#39;s colleague Pablo Arrabal Haro, an astrophysicist at the National Science Foundation&#39;s NOIRLab, based in Tucson, worked through the weekend to write up results before anyone else.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> CEERS-93316&#39;s 16.4 redshift turned out to be wrong. The galaxy was actually at a redshift of 4.9, putting it 1.2 billion years after the Big Bang — practically modern compared with some of JWST&#39;s other finds.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The galaxy&#39;s photometric redshift was so high because of a weird coincidence. Light streaming from hydrogen in the galaxy was redshifted such that it looked like it jumped in brightness at a wavelength suggestive of the huge distance. But when the full spectrum came in, that single jump was revealed to be several separate peaks, suggesting a smaller redshift.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Maisie&#39;s Galaxy, however, is <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.15431" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">almost as distant as the photometric redshift implied</a> , Arrabal Haro and colleagues reported in a paper posted in March to arXiv.org. And in an April paper posted to arXiv.org, the team reported <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.05378" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">spectra for more than 30 other galaxies</a> with redshifts of roughly between 8 and 10. So photometric redshift estimates are generally reliable, Finkelstein says.</p><div class="wp-block-sciencenews-content-sidebar alignwide" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><h3 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Timeline of early galaxies</h3><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> JWST has detected many galaxies from the early universe (a few are shown on this timeline). These galaxies could shed light on reionization, the process that ended the cosmic dark ages, when the universe was shrouded in darkness. Some of these galaxies, the “universe breakers,” appear to be more massive than theory can explain. </p><figure class="wp-block-image "><picture class="sn-responsive-image"><source srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/081223_galaxies_inline3_desktop_1030-800x197.jpg 800w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/081223_galaxies_inline3_desktop_1030-680x167.jpg 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/081223_galaxies_inline3_desktop_1030-330x81.jpg 330w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/081223_galaxies_inline3_desktop_1030-768x189.jpg 768w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/081223_galaxies_inline3_desktop_1030.jpg 1030w" width="800" height="197" media="(min-width: 600px)" sizes="(max-width: 1023px) 100vw, 680px"></source><source srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/081223_galaxies_inline3_mobile.jpg 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/081223_galaxies_inline3_mobile-591x383.jpg 591w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/081223_galaxies_inline3_mobile-287x186.jpg 287w" width="680" height="441"></source><img src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/081223_galaxies_inline3_mobile.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large" alt="A timeline showing how far back in time the James Webb Space Telescope can see." decoding="async" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/081223_galaxies_inline3_mobile.jpg 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/081223_galaxies_inline3_mobile-591x383.jpg 591w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/081223_galaxies_inline3_mobile-287x186.jpg 287w" sizes="(max-width: 1023px) 100vw, 680px" data-attachment-id="3130157" data-permalink="https://www.sciencenews.org/081223_galaxies_inline3_mobile" data-orig-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/081223_galaxies_inline3_mobile.jpg" data-orig-size="680,441" data-comments-opened="0" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="081223_galaxies_inline3_mobile" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/081223_galaxies_inline3_mobile-591x383.jpg" data-large-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/081223_galaxies_inline3_mobile.jpg" /></picture><figcaption> <span class="credit mobile-credit wp-credit-3130157">JWST: ESA; Background: NASA, ESA, P. Oesch and B. Robertson/Univ. of California, Santa Cruz, A. Feild/STScI, adapted by C. Chang</span> <span class="credit desktop-credit wp-credit-3130156">JWST: ESA; Background: NASA, ESA, P. Oesch and B. Robertson/Univ. of California, Santa Cruz, A. Feild/STScI, adapted by C. Chang</span></figcaption></figure></div><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “Although we have this notable failure case, that&#39;s a pathological case,” he says. It&#39;s “not devastating.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> That&#39;s good news for JWST&#39;s observing schedule: Astronomers won&#39;t have to follow up with the full spectrum for every distant galaxy. They can believe that most of the redshifts are legit and save the extra effort of taking the full spectrum for the really interesting ones. “It is exciting that the photometric redshifts tend to hold up,” Robertson says. “It gives us some hope that some of these really distant things could be real.”</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Distant galaxies too bright to explain</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Another outcome of JWST analyses so far is that there are more bright galaxies around redshift 10 than expected. Galaxy brightness is an indicator of galaxy mass, and thus star abundance. The brighter the galaxy, the more stars it must have to produce all that light.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Galaxies are born in halos of dark matter, whose gravity pulls in and concentrates ordinary matter. Cosmologists know from simulations and theory how many dark matter halos the universe would have had when the first galaxies formed. They also have a decent idea of how massive those halos were in the universe&#39;s first 500 million years and how much of that mass ended up in the form of hydrogen and helium, the raw material for making stars. Theoretically, if all that gas turned into stars, the largest a galaxy could get would be about 10 billion times the mass of the sun.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> In reality, researchers expect early galaxies to be much less massive, because modern galaxies never convert all their gas into stars.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> JWST has not turned up any galaxy near the theoretical upper limit. But it has found many more hefty early galaxies than predicted. The confirmed JADES galaxies weigh in at about 100 million solar masses, just 330 million years after the Big Bang. Some of the CEERS galaxies seem to have over a billion suns&#39; worth of stars as early as 450 million years after the Big Bang. Two galaxies discovered in another JWST survey, called COSMOS-Web, appear to be about 5 billion solar masses as early as 350 million years after the Big Bang, astronomer Caitlin Casey of the University of Texas at Austin said at the June First Light meeting.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “With these massive beacons, you can test the limits of how fast you can assemble that much matter in the short time between the Big Bang and the time that we&#39;re observing them in,” she says.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> What astronomers find from these galaxies could point to where our existing understanding of galaxy formation is wrong. Or researchers might discover that some of the galaxies&#39; light doesn&#39;t come directly from stars but instead from the ionized gas in between stars that are actively forming, Casey says. That would mean the galaxies aren&#39;t actually as massive as they look.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Finding out how early galaxies were put together is the first step to understanding our own galaxy, Robertson says. “That&#39;s ultimately what drives a lot of galaxy formation research, is trying to understand how our home, the thing that&#39;s important to us, the place that we live, came to be,” he says. “We&#39;re never going to complete that full story without looking at how galaxies at redshift 10 were put together…. That&#39;s the starting place for how we got here.”</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Breaking the universe … or not</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> One set of galaxies has sparked debate over not just galaxy formation, but the theoretical foundations of the universe itself.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> In February, Nelson and colleagues reported six galaxies spotted with CEERS that seem to have <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/james-webb-telescope-six-galaxies-old">grown so big, so fast</a> that they directly challenge the standard theory of how structure forms in the universe ( <em>SN: 3/25/23, p. 14</em> ). These galaxies have photometric redshifts between about 7 and 9, meaning they grew up in the first 800 million years of the universe. But their stellar masses appear to rival or exceed that of the Milky Way, about 60 billion solar masses.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Nelson affectionately calls them the “universe breakers.” Nothing that massive should have been able to form that fast, she says. “As soon as we saw it, we were like, this is bananas.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Barely enough ordinary matter is even believed to have existed back then to create the universe breakers, says astrophysicist Mike Boylan-Kolchin of the University of Texas at Austin. Regions where budding galaxies formed would have had to turn all their atoms into stars. </p><figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="680" height="455" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/081223_galaxies_inline4.jpg" alt="Six distant galaxies (red dots, above) spotted by the Cosmic Evolution Early Release Science, or CEERS." class="wp-image-3130158" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/081223_galaxies_inline4.jpg 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/081223_galaxies_inline4-572x383.jpg 572w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/081223_galaxies_inline4-673x450.jpg 673w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/081223_galaxies_inline4-278x186.jpg 278w" sizes="(max-width: 680px) 100vw, 680px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3130158">Six distant galaxies (red dots, above) spotted by the Cosmic Evolution Early Release Science, or CEERS, survey appear to be too massive for standard cosmological theories to explain, though one of these “universe breakers” (top row, middle image) is not as distant as originally thought.</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3130158">NASA, ESA, CSA, I. LABBÉ/SWINBURNE UNIV. OF TECHNOLOGY; IMAGE PROCESSING: G. BRAMMER/COSMIC DAWN CENTER/NIELS BOHR INSTITUTE/UNIV. OF COPENHAGEN</span></figcaption></figure><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “We have this reservoir of atoms,” he says. “Almost every single one of them has to be in stars or in galaxies” if the universe breakers are for real. “If these observations and their interpretation is correct … it&#39;s very hard to accommodate them in our current models,” he says.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Over the last few months, theorists have come up with several ways to explain the universe breakers. One of the most dramatic options would be to add some extra dark energy, the mysterious substance that drives the universe to expand faster and faster, to the early universe, which would speed up all sorts of cosmic processes.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “That would go in the right direction here, in the sense that there&#39;d be bigger reservoirs [of atoms] and maybe more of them at earlier times,” Boylan-Kolchin says. “These early dark energy models do predict faster evolution of structure at early times.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> More mundane options include super-compact early galaxies that could have converted all their gas into stars before the oldest stars had a chance to go supernova and blow it away. <em>S</em> uch efficient star formation <a href="https://academic.oup.com/mnras/article-abstract/523/3/3201/7179993?redirectedFrom=fulltext" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">could explain the universe breakers without breaking the universe</a> , physicist Avishai Dekel of the Hebrew University in Jerusalem and colleagues suggested in a paper published May 25 in the <em>Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society.</em></p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> And there&#39;s still the question of whether the universe breakers&#39; masses and distances will hold up. A spectrum of one of them has already revealed it to be a galaxy at redshift 5.6 with an actively feeding black hole creating extra light — so not a universe breaker after all.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> JWST&#39;s second observing cycle began in July, and Nelson will take spectra of the rest of the universe breakers to find out if they are truly abounding with stars, filled with black holes or something else.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Meanwhile, another group of astronomers will test JWST&#39;s limits, hunting for galaxies at redshift 15 or greater. So by the telescope&#39;s second birthday next summer, there may be new distance records.</p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/081223_galaxies_feat-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="120576" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/081223_galaxies_feat-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item></channel></rss>