<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/" xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/" xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"><channel><title> חדשות המדע </title><atom:link href="https://www.sciencenews.org/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org<description> עיתונאות עצמאית מאז 1921</description><lastbuilddate> שישי, 21 ביולי 2023 21:10:08 +0000</lastbuilddate><language> en-US</language><sy:updateperiod> מדי שעה</sy:updateperiod><sy:updatefrequency> 1</sy:updatefrequency><generator> https://wordpress.org/?v=6.2.2</generator><item><title> ייתכן שהטלסקופ של ג&#39;יימס ווב הבחין בכוכבים המופעלים על ידי חומר אפל</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/james-webb-telescope-stars-dark-matter<dc:creator><![CDATA[Skyler Ware]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Mon, 24 Jul 2023 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Space]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3129789 </guid><description><![CDATA[Three objects in the distant universe bear signs of hypothesized “dark stars,” researchers claim, though others say more definitive data are needed. ]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<p>טלסקופ החלל ג&#39;יימס ווב זיהה עצמים ביקום המוקדם שעשויים להיות סוג חדש של כוכב - כזה המופעל על ידי חומר אפל.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> &quot;הכוכבים האפלים&quot; הללו הם עדיין היפותטיים. הזיהוי שלהם בתמונות JWST רחוק מלהיות בטוח. אבל אם מישהו משלושת <a href="https://www.pnas.org/doi/epdf/10.1073/pnas.2305762120" target="_blank" rel="noopener">המועמדים</a> - שדווח ב-25 ביולי <em>של האקדמיה הלאומית למדעים</em> - יתברר כסוג חדש זה של כוכבים, הם יכולים להציע הצצה להיווצרות כוכבים ביקום המוקדם, לרמוז על טבעו של החומר האפל ואולי להסביר את מקורותיהם של חורים שחורים סופר-מסיביים.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> הוצע לראשונה בשנת 2007 על ידי הקוסמולוגית קתרין פריזה ועמיתיה, <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/twinkle-twinkle-dark-matter-may-have-lit-first-stars">כוכבים אפלים עשויים להיות חלק מסוגי הכוכבים הראשונים</a> שנוצרו ביקום ( <em>SN: 1/1/08</em> ). אף על פי שטרם נצפו כוכבים אפלים, חושבים שהם מופעלים על ידי חום מאינטראקציות של חומר אפל ולא על ידי תגובות היתוך גרעיני כמו בשמש.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> כוכבים אפלים &quot;יהיו מאוד מוזרים למראה&quot;, אומר פריז, מאוניברסיטת טקסס באוסטין. הכוכבים ההיפותטיים היו נוצרים מענני מימן והליום ששאבו פנימה חומר אפל בשפע מקומי כשהם התלכדו. אף על פי שהטבע האמיתי של <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/dark-matter-lz-experiment-physics">החומר האפל</a> אינו ידוע - נוכחותו מוסקת בעיקר באמצעות השפעתו על האופן שבו כוכבים נעים בתוך גלקסיות - ייתכן שחלקיקי החומר האפל יכולים לקיים אינטראקציה עם עצמם, להשמיד זה את זה כאשר הם מתנגשים ומייצרים כמויות אדירות של אור וחום ( <em>SN: 7/7/22</em> ). החום הזה ימנע מענן המימן וההליום להתעבות לגרעין צפוף וחם כמו הכוכבים הקיימים היום.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> מכיוון שהחום מהשמדת החומר האפל ימנע מענן הגז להתעבות, כוכבים אפלים יכולים לגדול לגודל ענק. תיאורטית, כוכבים אפלים יכולים להיות רחבים פי 10 ממסלול כדור הארץ סביב השמש. הם יכולים גם להיות מסיביים פי מיליוני כמו השמש ולזהוח בהירים פי מיליארדי - בהירים מספיק, פוטנציאליים, כדי להיות מזוהים על ידי JWST.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> כדי לראות אם כוכבים אפלים כלשהם אורבים בנתונים ממצפה הכוכבים הסובב, Freese ועמיתיו בדקו תמונות מסקר JWST של גלקסיות מוקדמות. בתמונות כאלה, JWST גילה עד כה למעלה מ-700 עצמים שמקורם אולי <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/james-webb-space-telescope-time-galaxy">בכמה מאות מיליוני השנים הראשונות של היקום</a> - התקופה שבה כוכבים אפלים היו מופיעים ( <em>SN: 12/16/22</em> ). האור מעצמים מרוחקים אלה נמתח, או מוסט לאדום, כשהיקום מתפשט. אז Freese ועמיתיו התעניינו בארבעה אובייקטים שכבר אישרו כי הם הועברו מאוד לאדום, מה שהפך אותם לחלק מהאובייקטים העתיקים ביותר שנראו עד כה.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> אובייקטים אלה נחשבים כיום לגלקסיות קטנות מינקותו היחסית של היקום. אבל בגלל שהם כל כך רחוקים, JWST לא יכול לפתור אותם מספיק טוב כדי לקבוע אם הם בעצם גלקסיות או כוכבים גדולים ואולטרה-בהירים, אומרים החוקרים. </p><figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" width="680" height="551" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071823_sw_dark-stars_inline.jpg" alt="תמונה מטלסקופ החלל ג&#39;יימס ווב עם חץ המצביע על JADES-GS-z13-0." class="wp-image-3129792" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071823_sw_dark-stars_inline.jpg 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071823_sw_dark-stars_inline-473x383.jpg 473w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071823_sw_dark-stars_inline-555x450.jpg 555w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071823_sw_dark-stars_inline-230x186.jpg 230w" sizes="(max-width: 680px) 100vw, 680px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3129792">שלושה מועמדים לכוכבים אפלים זוהו מנתונים שנאספו על ידי JWST Advanced Deep Extragalactic Survey. אחד המועמדים, JADES-GS-z13-0, מוצג כאן (חץ).</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3129792">NASA, ESA, CSA, JADES שיתוף פעולה</span></figcaption></figure><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> הצוות הפעיל הדמיות מחשב של כמה אור עשוי כוכב כהה היפותטי להפיק באורכי גל שונים. הם השוו את הספקטרים ​​הללו לאור מתמונות שנאספו על ידי JWST באורכי גל שונים עבור כל אחד מארבעת העצמים. נתוני JWST משלושה מהאובייקטים הללו תואמים לדפוסי הכוכבים האפלים המדומים, מדווחים Freese ועמיתיו.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> חלק מהמדענים סקפטיים. סוגים ידועים של כוכבים יכולים גם ליצור את האור הנצפה משלושת המועמדים, אומר סנדרו טצ&#39;לה, אסטרופיזיקאי מאוניברסיטת קיימברידג&#39;. וזיהוי כל אחד מהעצמים ככוכב אפל ידרוש שהדפוסים המדומים יתאימו היטב לספקטרום מפורט יותר, אומר ברנט רוברטסון, אסטרופיזיקאי תיאורטי מאוניברסיטת קליפורניה, סנטה קרוז.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> אם היו מוצאים כוכבים אפלים, &quot;זה יהיה מהפכני&quot;, אומרת מחברת המחקר קוסמין אילי, אסטרופיזיקאית מאוניברסיטת קולגייט בהמילטון, ניו יורק.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> זיהוי כוכבים אפלים <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/dark-matter-lz-experiment-physics">יאשר את קיומו של חלקיק חומר אפל</a> ורמז כיצד הוא פועל ( <em>SN: 7/7/22</em> ). &quot;רק לקבל את המידע ש[חומר אפל] הוא משהו שיכול להשמיד יהיה ממש ממש חזק&quot;, אומרת טרייסי סלטייר, פיזיקאית תיאורטית ב-MIT שלא הייתה מעורבת במחקר. ידע זה יכול לעזור למדענים לחפש חומר אפל במקומות אחרים ביקום, היא אומרת.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> כוכבים אפלים יכולים גם לעזור להסביר <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/astronomers-cant-figure-out-why-some-black-holes-got-so-big-so-fast">את היווצרותם של חורים שחורים סופר מסיביים</a> ( <em>SN: 3/16/18</em> ). ברגע שהחומר האפל שבתוך הכוכב ישמיד את עצמו, המימן וההליום שנותרו - פי מיליוני ממסת השמש בחלל קומפקטי יחסית - יקרסו פנימה ויוצרים חור שחור. החורים השחורים האלה יכולים להתמזג עם הזמן לחורים שחורים כמו אלה שבמרכזי רוב הגלקסיות, מסיביות פי מיליוני או מיליארדי כמו השמש.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> ניסויים עתידיים, כמו חיפוש אחר אור בהיר יותר או עמום יותר באורכי גל מסוימים, יכולים לעזור לאשר אם אחד משלושת העצמים הוא כוכבים כהים. Freese גם מצפה למצוא עוד מועמדים לכוכבים אפלים בנתוני JWST עתידיים, היא אומרת. אבל לעת עתה, האם באמת קיימים כוכבים אפלים נותרה בגדר תעלומה.</p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071823_sw_dark-stars_feat-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="175323" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071823_sw_dark-stars_feat-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title> העתקים של עוברים אנושיים נעשו מורכבים יותר. הנה מה שאתה צריך לדעת</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/human-embryo-replica-complex-advanced<dc:creator><![CDATA[Tina Hesman Saey]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Mon, 24 Jul 2023 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Humans]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3129908 </guid><description><![CDATA[Lab-engineered human embryo models created from stem cells provide a look at development beyond the first week. But they raise ethical questions. ]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<p>כמה גושים שדווחו לאחרונה של תאים הגדלים בכלי מעבדה הועלו כדברים הקרובים ביותר לעוברים אנושיים שמדענים הכינו אי פעם במעבדה.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> הישויות הללו הן מודלים של עוברים אנושיים - המוני תאים שנוצרו מתאי גזע המחקים כמה תכונות של שלבים מסוימים של התפתחות העובר. ההישג נותן לחוקרים הזדמנות להסתכל על התפתחות האדם מעבר לשבוע הראשון לערך, כאשר עובר צריך להשתיל ברחם כדי להתפתח עוד יותר. השלב שלאחר ההשתלה לא נוצר מחדש בכלי מעבדה - עד עכשיו.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> שישה מחקרים שדווחו ביוני ויולי מתארים את דגמי העוברים, שיצרו התרגשות ודאגה באותה מידה.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> עבור חוקרים העובדים על מודלים אלה של עוברים, העוברים המזויפים הם כלים חדשים להשיג תובנה לגבי &quot;הקופסה השחורה&quot; של התפתחות האדם, לאחר השתלת עוברים ברחם. הם שימושיים מכיוון שעוברים אנושיים שנתרמו הם במחסור, ויש מגבלות על סוגי הניסויים שחוקרים יכולים לבצע בהם.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> כ-60% מההריונות נכשלים ממש לפני, במהלך או זמן קצר לאחר ההשתלה, אמרה ביולוגית ההתפתחות ותאי הגזע מגדלנה ז&#39;רניקה-גוץ מאוניברסיטת קיימברידג&#39; ו-Caltech ב-27 ביוני במהלך תדרוך חדשות שדן במודל עוברים שנעשה במעבדתה. תובנות שנאספו מדגמי העובר עשויות לתת הבנה חדשה מדוע הריונות רבים אינם מצליחים לתפוס אחיזה ולהוביל לטיפולי פוריות טובים יותר, אמרה ז&#39;רניקה-גוץ.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> אבל אחרים חוששים שהמודלים - יחד עם ביציות וזרע העשויים מתאי גזע - מעלים את רוח הרפאים של חוקרים המשתמשים בחיקויים כדי ליצור תינוקות. מדענים המפתחים את המודלים אומרים שהתרבות אינה המטרה או הכוונה שלהם, וכי השתלה ברחם היא בלתי אפשרית עם מודלים אלה של עוברים.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> ובכל זאת, המחקר מעלה סוגיות של איך - והאם - לווסת את מה שמדענים יכולים לעשות עם ישויות דמויות עוברים העשויות מתאי גזע. שאלות סובבות האם ניתן או צריך לגדל מודלים של עוברים מעבר ל-14 ימים של התפתחות אנושית נורמלית לאחר ההפריה. ומבקרים מזהירים שהפרזת מה שהמודלים הם או יכולים לעשות עלולה לגרום לפגיעה באמון במדע.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <em>Science News</em> שוחח עם מדענים ואנשי אתיקה כדי ללמוד עוד על מודלים אלה של עוברים אנושיים.</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> מהם מודלים של עוברים אנושיים?</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> לפני שנענה על השאלה הזו, אמנדר קלארק, נשיא האגודה הבינלאומית לחקר תאי גזע, אומר שעלינו להבין תחילה שעובר אנושי הוא תוצר של הפריה של ביצית וזרע.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> מודלים של עוברים, לעומת זאת, מרכיבים את עצמם מתאי גזע פלוריפוטנטיים - כאלה שיש להם את הכוח ליצור כמעט כל סוג של תא בגוף. &quot;לכן, מודלים של עוברים אינם עונים להגדרה הקלינית, הרפואית או המדעית של עובר מכיוון שהם אינם מקורם בתוצר של הפריה על ידי שני גמטות&quot;, אומר קלארק, מדען תאי גזע, ביולוג התפתחותי וגנטיקאי ב-UCLA.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> במשך שנים, מדענים חקרו את השבוע הראשון בערך של התפתחות האדם באמצעות עוברים אנושיים או <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/blastoid-stem-cells-fertility-research">מודלים של עוברים</a> שנתרמו ( <em>SN: 1/5/22</em> ). מהם למדו החוקרים הרבה על היווצרות כדור התאים המכונה בלסטוציסט. בלסטוציסטים יש שכבה חיצונית של תאים שיהוו את השליה ומערכות תמיכה אחרות לעובר המתפתח, ומקבץ פנימי של תאים שיוליד את הגוף.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> אבל בשבועות הקרובים של החיים מתרחשת הפעולה האמיתית, אומר הביולוג והאמבריולוג של תאי גזע יעקב חנה ממכון ויצמן למדע ברחובות, ישראל. בין היום השביעי ליום ה-35 בערך לאחר ההפריה, הוא כאשר העובר בונה את כל איבריו. &quot;זה עובר מכדור של תאים למבנה שכל אחד ברחוב... היה אומר לך, &#39;זה עובר&#39;.&quot; ואז שאר שמונת החודשים האחרים הם רק גידול של העובר&quot;, הוא אומר.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> חוקרים הרכיבו מודלים של עוברים המכילים חלק, אך לא את כולם, מסוגי התאים הדרושים להתפתחות תקינה. דגמי העוברים החדשים שדווחו מחקים מבנים שיימצאו בעובר שהושתל ברחם, למרות שלמחקים אין מה להשתיל לתוכו. המודלים מדמים חלון מאוד ספציפי של התפתחות העובר: &quot;האירועים המתרחשים כשתלי עובר, איך העובר מתאסף בעצמו&quot;, אומר קלארק. &quot;אז בעצם הם קורסים.&quot;</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> אף אחת מהדוגמניות לא מעתיקה לחלוטין עובר אמיתי, היא אומרת. למשל, אף אחד מהם לא מייצר טרופקטודרם טוב מאוד, שכבת התאים שמולידה את השליה בשלב מאוחר יותר בהתפתחות. שכבה זו חשובה לעובר להשתיל ברחם, והיא גם שולחת אותות שעוזרים לשאר העובר להתפתח כראוי.</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> איך התחיל הבאז האחרון על דגמי עוברים?</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> מודלים של עוברים לאחר השרשה משכו תשומת לב תקשורתית כאשר ז&#39;רניקה-גוץ הציגה ממצאים ראשוניים ברגעי הסיום של הרצאה שנשאה ב-13 ביוני בבוסטון בפגישה של האגודה הבינלאומית לחקר תאי גזע. העיתון <em>&quot;גרדיאן&quot;</em> שיבח את העבודה כפריצת דרך שיצרה עוברים אנושיים סינתטיים. </p><figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="680" height="680" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071323_ths_human-embryo_inline.jpg" alt="דגם עובר אנושי הדומה לטבעות של תאים בצבעים משתנים, עם ירוק עז באמצע וכתום (עם מגנטה מדי פעם) בטבעות החיצוניות" class="wp-image-3129911" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071323_ths_human-embryo_inline.jpg 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071323_ths_human-embryo_inline-383x383.jpg 383w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071323_ths_human-embryo_inline-450x450.jpg 450w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071323_ths_human-embryo_inline-186x186.jpg 186w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071323_ths_human-embryo_inline-580x580.jpg 580w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071323_ths_human-embryo_inline-214x214.jpg 214w" sizes="(max-width: 680px) 100vw, 680px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3129911">המעבדה של מגדלנה ז&#39;רניקה-גוץ יצרה מודל עוברים עם שכבות של תאים (ירוקים), שלדברי החוקרים דומה לחלק של עובר שייצור את הגוף, מוקף בשכבה (כתומה) המחקה תאים יוצרי שק חלמון, וכמה תאים (סגולים) דומים לאלה שמולידים את השליה. חוקרים אחרים ספקנים לגבי הטענה.</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3129911">אוניברסיטת קמברידג</span></figcaption></figure><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> האפיון הזה מגזים בהישג, אומר אלפונסו מרטינז אריאס, ביולוג התפתחותי באוניברסיטת פומפאו פברה בברצלונה. העבודה היא לא פריצת דרך, אלא התקדמות מצטברת, והיא רחוקה מליצור מחדש עובר, הוא אומר.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> ז&#39;רניקה-גוץ ועמיתיו הנדסו גנטית תאי גזע אנושיים כדי להידמות לשלושה סוגים של תאים הנחוצים להתפתחות העובר: תאים המחקים את הטרופקטודרם החשוב ליצירת השליה, תאים שדומים לאלה שיצרו את שק החלמון שמזין את העובר עד שהשליה משתלטת על התא בפנים, ואלה שיוצרים את העובר לגוף. כדורי התאים שנוצרו <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-023-06368-y" target="_blank" rel="noopener">דומים להיבטים מסוימים של עוברים אנושיים</a> , כך דיווח הצוות ב-27 ביוני ב- <em>Nature</em> .</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> לדוגמה, שכבת הטרופקטודרם נוצרת בצד החיצוני של המבנה דמוי העובר כפי שהיא עושה בעוברים. אבל זה לא הופך חלבונים לאופייניים לשכבה הזו כשהם מורכבים במבנה תלת-ממדי, כך שהוא לא באמת מבשר שליה, אמרה מחברת-השותף ביילי וות&#39;רבי מאוניברסיטת קיימברידג&#39; במהלך תדרוך החדשות. אבל השכבה נחוצה להרכבת שאר מודל העובר, מה שמרמז שהיא מבצעת חלק מהפונקציות של הטרופקטודרם, אמרה.</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> כיצד נוצרו דגמי עוברים אחרים?</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> כמו הצוות של ז&#39;רניקה-גוץ, כל קבוצות המחקר התחילו עם תאי גזע אנושיים. שליטה קפדנית של תנאי הגידול ומספר סוגים מסוימים של תאים שנוספו לתערובת אפשרו לתאי הגזע לגדול למבנים דמויי עובר. המודלים שונים במספר סוגי התאים שהם מכילים ובתכונות של עוברים אמיתיים שהם מסוגלים לחקות.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> קבוצה אחת של חוקרים שידלה <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-023-06354-4" target="_blank" rel="noopener">תאי גזע ליצירת מבנים דמויי עובר</a> עם שתי שכבות רקמה. העבודה הזו, שתוארה גם ב-27 ביוני ב- <em>Nature</em> , לא השתמשה במניפולציה גנטית או בכימיקלים כדי לגרום לתאי הגזע ליצור מבנים דמויי עובר. במקום זאת, החוקרים הסתמכו על יכולתם של תאי גזע להתארגן בעצמם, אומרת הביולוגית ההתפתחותית ברנה סוזן מבית הספר לרפואה של ייל.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> המודל המתקבל חסר את הטרופקטודרם. כשהחוקרים הבינו שהרקמה חסרה, הם חשבו שהיעדרה עשוי לומר להם משהו על חשיבותה, היא אומרת. &quot;בהיעדר הרקמות האלה אתה יכול לראות מה יקרה, מה לא יקרה, ואז אתה [מקבל] תובנות מדעיות חזקות מאוד [על] מדוע אתה צריך את הרקמה הזו.&quot;</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> מאמץ נוסף של חוקרים בסין ובמישיגן, המתואר ב-preprint שעדיין לא זכה לביקורת עמיתים שפורסם ב-16 ביוני באינטרנט ב-bioRxiv.org, <a href="https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2023.06.15.545180v1" target="_blank" rel="noopener">מרשים מבחינה טכנית</a> , אומר מרטינז אריאס. אבל עדיין חסרה לו שכבת מקדימה שליה.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> לאחרונה, צוות בראשות יוני וו מהמרכז הרפואי UT Southwestern בדאלאס שיכנע תאי גזע ליצור <a href="https://www.cell.com/cell/fulltext/S0092-8674(23)00794-8" target="_blank" rel="noopener">ישויות דמויות עוברים</a> המשתרעות על פני אירוע הסידור מחדש שנקרא גסטרולציה, כך מדווחים החוקרים ב-20 ביולי ב- <em>Cell</em> . במהלך הקיבה עוברים עוברים מכדורים חלולים של תאים למבנים רב-שכבתיים שיולידו איברים ורקמות היוצרים את הגוף.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> מודלים &quot;פרי-גסטרואידים&quot; אלה יצרו רקמות מסוימות הדומות לאלו שבמערכת העצבים המוקדמת ועשויים לסייע לאשר את מקורות התאים שיולידו ביציות וזרע. הדגמים האלה מכילים גם שק חלמון, אבל &quot;הדגם שלנו אינו דגם שלם&quot;, אומר וו. &quot;אין לנו את רקמת השליה.&quot; </p><figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="680" height="501" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/072023_ths_human-embryo_inline2.jpg" alt="מבנה דמוי עובר, מוצג כגוש תאים בצורת אליפסה. המבנים החיצוניים הם בעיקר כתומים. במרכז החצי התחתון נמצאים בעיקר תאים ירוקים, ובמרכז הישיר יש יותר תאים סגולים" class="wp-image-3129909" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/072023_ths_human-embryo_inline2.jpg 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/072023_ths_human-embryo_inline2-520x383.jpg 520w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/072023_ths_human-embryo_inline2-611x450.jpg 611w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/072023_ths_human-embryo_inline2-252x186.jpg 252w" sizes="(max-width: 680px) 100vw, 680px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3129909">מבנה דמוי עובר הנקרא פרי-גסטרולואיד מהמעבדה של ג&#39;ון וו במרכז הרפואי UT Southwestern בדאלאס מחקה כמה שלבים התפתחותיים מוקדמים, כולל היווצרות שק החלמון (כתום) והפס הפרימיטיבי (סגול) - חריץ המופיע כ-14 ימים לאחר ההפריה ומאותת כי הרקמה המרובה עוברת בעצמה. תאים הדומים לאפיבלסט (ירוק) מתחילים ליצור מספר שכבות של רקמות כמו אלו שייצרו את הגוף בעובר.</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3129909">L. Lui <em>et al</em> / <em>Cell</em> 2023</span></figcaption></figure><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> מכיוון שלמודלים חסר הטרופקטודרם, החוקרים נאלצו להוסיף חלבונים לעיגון ולתמוך בגסטרואידים כדי שיוכלו להתפתח כראוי.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> צוות חוקרים בסין דיווח על תוצאות ראשוניות של <a href="https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2023.06.28.546720v1" target="_blank" rel="noopener">גסטרואידים דומים עם שקי חלמון</a> ב-28 ביוני ב-bioRxiv.org. צוות זה מצא שהכימיקל תלידומיד משנה את היווצרות שכבות הרקמה ומפריע להתפתחות.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> בעתיד, חוקרים עשויים להשתמש במודלים כאלה כדי להבין כיצד כימיקלים מהסביבה יכולים להשפיע על עוברים מתפתחים, אומר וו.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> מרטינז אריאס ואחרים יצרו בעבר גסטרולואידים שיכולים לדגמן התפתחות עד יום 19 לאחר ההפריה, אך לדגמים הקודמים הללו לא היו שקי חלמון.</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> האם כל אחד מדגמי העובר הוא התקדמות משמעותית?</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> מתוך &quot;בהלת הזהב&quot; הזו של דגמי עוברים, רק שניים הם התקדמות אמיתית, אומר מרטינז אריאס: הגסטרואידים ודגמי <a href="https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2023.06.14.544922v1" target="_blank" rel="noopener">העוברים</a> של וו שנעשו על ידי הקבוצה של האנה.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> למודלים של האנה המתוארים ב-15 ביוני שפורסם ב-bioRxiv.org, יש פקסימיליה סבירה הן של שק חלמון והן של מבשר השליה, אומר מרטינז אריאס, והם יוצרים מבנים בעלי דמיון &quot;מדהים&quot; לאלו של עוברים ב-14 ימי התפתחות.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> התהליך להשגת מודל עובר כל כך דומה לדבר האמיתי היה ארוך, אומרת האנה. הצוות שלו חשב לראשונה כיצד לגדל עוברי עכברים מעבר לשלב ההתפתחותי הזה במנות מעבדה. תוך שימוש בעוברי עכבר כ&quot;מצפן הניסוי&quot; שלהם, החוקרים גילו כיצד להרכיב מודל של עוברי עכבר מתאי גזע. משם, הצוות השתמש בתחבולות שלמדו כדי לגדל תאי גזע אנושיים בתנאים ששידלו אותם להרכיב את עצמם למבנים המתקרבים לעוברים לאחר ההשתלה.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> ההרכבה העצמית עקפה את שלב הבלסטוציסט ועברה ישירות למשהו הדומה לעובר לאחר השרשה, כך מצא הצוות שלו. &quot;אולי העובר [מודלים] חסרים כי אנחנו לא עוברים דרך הבלסטוציסט [שלב]. אני לא חושב כך. אבל אני לא יכולה לשלול את זה כרגע&quot;, אומרת חנה.</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> האם מודלים אלה של עוברים יכולים לגרום לתינוקות?</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> לא, אבל השאלה הזו תמיד עולה.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> מדענים מתעניינים בהתקדמות טכנית וביולוגית שהמודלים החדשים של העוברים מביאים. אבל עבור רוב האנשים, &quot;זו באמת האפשרות שהם יכולים לשמש לרבייה שמושכת את תשומת הלב&quot;, אומרת קייטי חסון, מנהלת שותפה של המרכז לגנטיקה וחברה, ארגון צדק חברתי ללא מטרות רווח שבסיסו בברקלי, קליפורניה.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> לא ניתן להשתמש במודלים אלה של עוברים להתרבות, אומרים מדענים. &quot;לא רק שזה לא חוקי לשים את השלבים המאוחרים האלה [דגמי עוברים] בתוך הרחם, אלא שלמעשה אם אני רוצה, או מישהו רוצה, המבנים האלה לעולם לא יוכלו להשתיל&quot;, אומרת האנה. ההשתלה מתרחשת רק כאשר העוברים מורכבים מאחד עד 64 תאים. המודלים שלאחר ההשתלה עברו מעבר לשלב זה. מבחינה ביולוגית, הוא אומר, &quot;זה לעולם לא יצליח&quot;.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> וו מסכים. &quot;המודלים האלה אינם עוברים אנושיים בכלל&quot;, הוא אומר. &quot;הם לא מסוגלים לייצר שום סוג של חיים. הם בעצם רק מקבץ של תאים.&quot;</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> ישנם חסמים חוקיים לגידול עוברים במעבדה מעבר לשלב מסוים גם כן. בבריטניה, החוק אוסר על גידול עוברים לאחר 14 ימי התפתחות, הנקודה שבה העובר מפעיל את תוכנית בניית הגוף שלו. הגבול הזה הוטל זמן קצר לאחר שהתאפשרה הפריה חוץ גופית.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> אבל כמה מדגמי העוברים האלה כבר דומים לעוברים בשלב ההתפתחות של 14 יום. מכיוון שהמודלים אינם נוצרים באמצעות הפריה ולעולם לא יכלו להוליד אדם, חלק מהחוקרים טוענים שהם לא צריכים להיות כפופים לכלל 14 הימים.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> בארצות הברית, אין חוק האוסר על גידול עוברים ב-14 הימים האחרונים, אך תיקון דיקי-וויקר משנת 1995 אוסר על המכון הלאומי לבריאות בארה&quot;ב לממן מחקר על עוברים או תאים דמויי עוברים בעלי &quot;פוטנציאל אורגניזמי&quot;, אומר קלארק. מכיוון שלמודלים אלה חסרים חלקים קריטיים, אין להם פוטנציאל ליצור אורגניזם - כך שניתן לממן מחקר עם מודלים של עוברים.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> החברה הבינלאומית לתאי גזע עדכנה לאחרונה את ההנחיות שלה, והציעה שאם מדענים רוצים לטפח עוברים שנוצרו על ידי הפריה במשך יותר מ-14 ימים, עליהם לבקש אישור ציבורי בתחום השיפוט שלהם. מכיוון שהדגמים אינם עוברים, ההנחיות של החברה מציעות שניתן לתרבת אותם עד להופעת מבנה שנקרא הפס הפרימיטיבי, המעיד על כך שהעובר מתחיל לבנות את הגוף.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> המטרה של רוב המדענים בתחום היא להבין את התהליך שבו תאים מרכיבים עובר ואז יוצרים את כל האיברים והרקמות של הגוף, אומר מרטינז אריאס. זה לא הכרחי ולא רצוי, ואולי אפילו לא אפשרי, לבנות העתק מושלם של עובר. &quot;אני בהחלט לא חושב שזה משהו שאנחנו רוצים לעשות, או שאנחנו צריכים לעשות או צריכים להגיד&quot;, הוא אומר. &quot;וזה לא משהו שנמצא באופק.&quot;</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> למרות זאת, מדענים צריכים ללחוץ על כפתור ההשהיה כדי להעריך ביסודיות את המבנים דמויי העובר ולקבוע כיצד הם יכולים לסייע בהבנת ההתפתחות האנושית, אומר מרטינז אריאס. &quot;אני מקווה שעכשיו כולנו יכולים לפתח את המערכות האלה בצורה שימושית למחקר, במקום לנסות לראות כמה רחוק אנחנו [יכולים] ללכת לחלל, מבלי לחשוב [על] איך נחזור&quot;.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> שיחות עם הציבור על מה שדגמי העובר מייצגים מבחינה מדעית, פילוסופית ומשפטית, ועל איך להשתמש בהם מבחינה אתית, צריך להתחיל עכשיו, אומר חסון. &quot;אנחנו צריכים לחשוב עליהם עכשיו כי זה לא המקרה, וזה לא צריך להיות המקרה, שהגבולות הטכניים של מה שמדענים יכולים לעשות עם המודלים האלה צריכים להגדיר את הדיון האתי ומה הגבולות האתיים צריכים להיות.&quot;</p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071323_ths_human-embryo_feat-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="146386" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071323_ths_human-embryo_feat-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title> איך התלקחות סולארית עתיקה האירה את תחילתו של עידן הוויקינגים</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/viking-age-ancient-solar-flare-trade-archaeology<dc:creator><![CDATA[Martin J. Kernan]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Sun, 23 Jul 2023 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Archaeology]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3129837 </guid><description><![CDATA[Improved radiocarbon dating aided by a solar flare in the year 775 sheds light on the early days of Vikings and global trading in medieval times. ]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<p class="has-drop-cap">פורענות אחר פורענות פקדה את אירופה בתחילת מה שנקרא ימי האפל. האימפריה הרומית קרסה בסוף המאה החמישית. התפרצויות געשיות באמצע המאה השישית חסמו את השמש, וגרמו לכישלון יבול ולרעב ברחבי חצי הכדור הצפוני. בינתיים, מגפת יוסטיניאן הגיעה, והרגה, לפי הערכות מסוימות, כמעט מחצית מכולם בקונסטנטינופול, בירת האימפריה הביזנטית, ועשרות אנשים אחרים במקומות אחרים.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> ואז, ב-8 ביוני 793, קבוצת שודדים תקפה אי קטן מול החוף הצפון-מזרחי של בריטניה הגדולה. כפי שציינו נזירים נוצרים ב- <em>Anglo-Saxon Chronicle</em> , &quot;אנשים גויים הרסו את כנסיית האל באי לינדיספארן על ידי שוד וטבח קשים&quot;.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> עם התיאור הזה, הוויקינגים נכנסו אל דברי ימי ההיסטוריה של ימי הביניים כשודדים חסרי רחמים, לאחר שהרגו גם פקיד מקומי בדרום בריטניה הגדולה בשנת 789. מנקודת המבט של היום, יורדי הים הנורדים הללו פרצו לקיום לכאורה משום מקום.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> מתי בדיוק ומדוע הוויקינגים הפנו את סירותיהם לראשונה מהחוף כדי להפליג דרומה מעל האופק ואל הלא נודע, יש ויכוח חריף. על פי כמה היסטוריונים, התפתחות נוספת בסוף המאה השמינית מציעה רמז: מטבעות כסף הידועים בשם דירהם עשו דרכם לאירופה מהעולם האסלאמי במזרח התיכון. בערך בזמן הזה, גברים ויקינגים במה שהיא כיום נורבגיה ושוודיה הפכו אובססיביים לכסף כאמצעי לרכישת כלות שנגרמו כתוצאה מרצח תינוקות, או כך לפחות גורסת תיאוריה פופולרית. צורך נואש בכסף, כך חשבו, הניע את מסעותיהם הראשוניים של הוויקינגים על פני הים הצפוני והבלטי ואיכשהו זירז את הפשיטות הידועות לשמצה שלהם.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> היסטוריונים אחרים, לעומת זאת, חושדים שהגיחות הראשונות של הוויקינגים לעולם החיצון קדמו זמן רב לפשיטות האלימות שלהם ולא היה להם שום קשר למסע אחר כסף.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> &quot;ההבנה שלנו לגבי הכרונולוגיה של תקופת הוויקינגים המוקדמת היא ממש פגומה מכיוון שהתיאורים הטובים ביותר שלנו נכתבים לפעמים 100 שנים מאוחר יותר&quot;, אומר מתיו דלוו, היסטוריון מימי הביניים באוניברסיטת פרינסטון. זה כולל את התיאור של פשיטת לינדיספארן <em>בכרוניקה האנגלו-סכסית</em> .</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> למרבה המזל, חוקרים מימי הביניים מצאו לאחרונה עזר נוסף לפנות אליו: סופת שמש.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> הארכיאולוג סורן סינדבק ועמיתיו מאוניברסיטת ארהוס בדנמרק שחזרו את העיתוי של מסעותיהם המוקדמים של הוויקינגים על ידי רתימת הכוח של מה שהיה ככל הנראה התלקחות סולארית סופר-מסיבית שפרצה בשנת 775. ההתלקחות סייעה לצוות לשפר תיארוך פחמן רדיואקטיבי ובכך ליתר דיוק לתארך חפצים מוקדמים של דנמרק, חפירה באתר המסחר המוקדם של דנמרק.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> הכרונולוגיה של האירועים בריבה חושפת התחלה פחות אלימה למסעות הויקינגים, לפחות 50 שנה לפני הפשיטה של ​​לינדיספארן. סוד ההצלחה הוויקינגית, מאמין סינדבק, מוסבר בצורה הטובה ביותר על ידי מסחר מיומן, לא פשיטה מפחידה.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> תיארוך פחמן מדויק יותר יש לו פוטנציאל לחשוף היבטים אחרים של העולם של ימי הביניים שפעם חשבו שאבודים להיסטוריה.</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> ארכיאולוגיה של תקופת הוויקינגים בריבה</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> מאז שנות ה-70, ארכיאולוגים חיפשו בריבה, על הים הצפוני, חפצים שיכולים לעזור להסביר את אחת התעלומות העמוקות ביותר בהיסטוריה של ימי הביניים: כיצד, בטווח של עשורים בלבד, חקלאים קשוחים תקועים בין ים מסוכן ויערות בלתי חדירים הפכו לוויקינגים ששלטו בתקופה הקרובה באירופה כ-300 שנים.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> בשלב מסוים, כמה יורדי ים בעלי מוטיבציה גבוהה מחצי האי הסקנדינבי עברו את מיצר סקגראק הבוגדני בן 100 הקילומטרים לריבה. שם, בין מקבץ של בתים חד-קומתיים עם קש על מחשוף חולי המתנשא מעל לביצת גאות, השאירו הוויקינגים רמזים למה הם הגיעו.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> סינדבק מדמיין איך ריבה, שכבר הייתה שוק להתנחלויות בדרום, הייתה נראית בעיני הוויקינגים המוקדמים האלה. &quot;מה שירשים אותך ממבט ראשון יהיו כל התורנים האלה&quot;, הוא אומר. &quot;יהיו יותר ספינות ממה שאי פעם ראית בחייך.&quot;</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> ריבה, העיר העתיקה ביותר בדנמרק, קישרה בסופו של דבר נתיבי מסחר שחצו את צפון אירופה. החפצים שנחפרו לאורך רחובותיו הצרים חושפים מתי הגיעו הוויקינגים המוקדמים לראשונה ולאן הם התפשטו, מה שמרחיב את השפעתם ברחבי האזור.</p><div class="wp-block-sciencenews-content-sidebar" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><h3 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> נתיבי סחר מימי הביניים המוקדמים בצפון אירופה</h3><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> בתקופת ימי הביניים המוקדמת, ריבה הייתה מוקד של סחר בינלאומי, עם נתיבי מסחר שהביאו סחורות מרחבי צפון אירופה והמזרח התיכון. קווים מקווקוים מראים מסלולים שבהם סחורות כנראה עברו דרך מתווכים לפני שהלכו לריבה. </p><div class="image-desktop" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="680" height="670" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_vikings_inline-1_desktop.jpg" alt="מפה של נתיבי סחר ישירים ועקיפים ברחבי ריבה" class="wp-image-3129843" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_vikings_inline-1_desktop.jpg 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_vikings_inline-1_desktop-389x383.jpg 389w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_vikings_inline-1_desktop-457x450.jpg 457w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_vikings_inline-1_desktop-189x186.jpg 189w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_vikings_inline-1_desktop-589x580.jpg 589w" sizes="(max-width: 680px) 100vw, 680px" /><figcaption> <span class="credit wp-credit-3129843">T. TIBBITTS, מותאם מ-B. PHILIPPSEN <em>ET AL</em> / <em>NATURE</em> 2022</span> </figcaption></figure></div><div class="image-mobile" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="680" height="670" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_vikings_inline-1_mobile.jpg" alt="מפה של נתיבי סחר ישירים ועקיפים ברחבי ריבה" class="wp-image-3129842" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_vikings_inline-1_mobile.jpg 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_vikings_inline-1_mobile-389x383.jpg 389w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_vikings_inline-1_mobile-457x450.jpg 457w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_vikings_inline-1_mobile-189x186.jpg 189w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_vikings_inline-1_mobile-589x580.jpg 589w" sizes="(max-width: 680px) 100vw, 680px" /><figcaption> <span class="credit wp-credit-3129842">T. TIBBITTS, מותאם מ-B. PHILIPPSEN <em>ET AL</em> / <em>NATURE</em> 2022</span></figcaption></figure></div></div><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> החל מיוני 2017 במשך 15 חודשים רצופים, חשפה הקבוצה של סינדבק <a href="https://projects.au.dk/northernemporium/about" target="_blank" rel="noopener">עדויות נרחבות למסחר בריבה</a> , החל משנת 700. ברצפות חרס של בתים שתפקדו כבית מגורים ובתי מלאכה, צוות ארהוס מצא חרוזי זכוכית, כולל מערך קליידוסקופי של חומרי הכנה ססגוניים מעבודות מתכת, מחרוזות וחרוזים ממזרח תיכוניים. גילוף עצמות. כל אלה היו שרידים מובהקים של עיירת מסחר מתקופת הוויקינגים, שבה נפגשו מגוון אנשים, התערבבו וסרו את מרכולתם.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> והם עשו זאת בשלווה. אין למעשה עדות ארכיאולוגית לסכסוך אלים בריבה, בניגוד למיתוס הפופולרי של ויקינגים כברברים צמאי דם.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> &quot;מההתחלה נראה שריבה הייתה מעין מקלט בטוח. אתה יכול לנחות כאן, אתה תהיה בטוח. אנחנו לא הולכים לבזוז אותך. ננסה להערים עליך&quot;, אומר סינדבק.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> בסך הכל, הוא ועמיתיו חשפו יותר מ-100,000 חפצים - כלים, אביזרים וחפצי נוי שיבואו להגדיר את התרבות של תקופת הוויקינגים. במקרים רבים, חפצים אלו נעשו מחומרים שמקורם בחצי האי הסקנדינבי בו גרו הוויקינגים המוקדמים. כמה יפהפיות בולטות. תליון מרהיב בגרזן קרב ענבר מרמז על אתוס הלוחמים של הוויקינגים. מסרקים מגולפים מקרני איילים מציגים עיצובים מורכבים. חיות מפחידות מעטרות סיכות אובליות. פניו של האל הוויקינגי אודין מפארים מטבעות. לממצאים היה ערך מעבר לתועלת או ליופי הטמון בהם. בחזרה הביתה בחצי האי הסקנדינבי, פריטי היוקרה הללו העניקו מעמד חברתי למי שמסר או קיבל אותם.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> &quot;אתה יכול להראות את היכולת שלך להשתתף ברשתות הבין-אזוריות האלה באותו אופן שבו אנו עשויים להשוויץ ביכולת שלנו לרכוש מכונית זרה&quot;, אומר Delvaux.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> חפירה לאורך מאות שנים, היו דורות רבים של בתי מלאכה. עשרים קומות חנויות זרועות חפצים. מאתיים שנה של פעילות ייצור מתמשכת דחוסה ל-2½ מטרים אנכיים.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> ריצ&#39;רד הודג&#39;ס, ארכיאולוג ונשיא לשעבר של האוניברסיטה האמריקנית ברומא, ביקר באתר ב-2018. זוהי &quot;עוגת שכבות של סדנאות מונחות זו על גבי זו&quot;, הוא אומר. &quot;חלק נשרפו. חלק מהם פשוט נהרסו. כל אחד מהם ייצר כמויות אדירות של תרבות חומרית&quot;.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> כשהשכבות מדממות לעתים קרובות יחד, צוות ארהוס היה צריך לתארך פחמן רדיו לכל אחת מהן כדי לשים את החפצים בסדר כרונולוגי ברור ולחשוף את התזמון של האירועים שהביאו אותם. </p><figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="680" height="510" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_vikings_inline-3.jpg" alt="תמונה של סורן סינדבק כורע בתעלה שנחפרה ומחזיק שולחן מדידה כדי להראות את מלוא גובהה של התעלה" class="wp-image-3129846" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_vikings_inline-3.jpg 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_vikings_inline-3-511x383.jpg 511w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_vikings_inline-3-600x450.jpg 600w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_vikings_inline-3-248x186.jpg 248w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_vikings_inline-3-263x197.jpg 263w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_vikings_inline-3-560x420.jpg 560w" sizes="(max-width: 680px) 100vw, 680px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3129846">הארכיאולוג סורן סינדבק כורע בתעלת חפירה שחושפת את השכבות הארכיאולוגיות הרבות בריבה.</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3129846">מוזיאון דרום מערב יוטלנד</span></figcaption></figure><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> המגבלות של תיארוך פחמן רדיו</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> במשך עשרות שנים, תיארוך פחמן רדיואקטיבי היה טכניקת בחירה עבור ארכיאולוגים. הוא מנצל את העובדה שכאשר אורגניזמים חיים לוקחים פחמן ומשלבים אותו ברקמותיהם, חלק מסוים מהפחמן הוא גרסה רדיואקטיבית של היסוד. לוקח 5,730 שנים עד שמחצית מפחמן הרדיו הזה מתפרק לצורה של חנקן. הידיעה שזמן מחצית חיים וכמות הפחמן הרדיואקטיבי בעצם או חתיכת פחם, למשל, עוזרת למדענים לחשב את גילו של החומר האורגני הזה.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> אבל כמות הפחמן הרדיואקטיבי באטמוספירה - וכך נספגת על ידי הצמחים במהלך הפוטוסינתזה ולאחר מכן על ידי בעלי החיים שאוכלים אותם - משתנה עם הזמן, ולכן מדענים חייבים לכייל את המדידות שלהם כדי להעריך תאריך לוח שנה אמיתי. טבעות עצים שימושיות למטרה זו; כל אחד מהם מתעד את תכולת הפחמן הרדיו-אטמוספרי בשנה בה נוצר. מומחים השתמשו בעצים בגילאים ידועים מרחבי העולם כדי להרכיב עקומה בשם IntCal20 המתווה תנודות בפחמן רדיו במהלך 55,000 השנים האחרונות כדי לעזור לחוקרים לכייל תאריכים של פחמן רדיו.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> אבל נתוני טבעות העצים השנתיים של IntCal20 דלים בחלקים של המאות השמינית והתשיעית. אז ארכיאולוגים לא הצליחו לתארך ממצאים מתקופת הוויקינגים בצורה מדויקת מספיק כדי להסביר את הופעתם של הוויקינגים על הבמה העולמית.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> כדי למלא את החסר, הפיזיקאית בנטה פיליפסן, חברה בצוות ארהוס, ביצעה כיול משלה באמצעות דגימות עץ אלון מהמוזיאון הלאומי של דנמרק - אחת מהן, כיאה לה, הייתה חלק מגשר שנבנה על ידי המלך הוויקינגי האראלד בלוטות&#39; (המאחד הגדול של אנשים בדנמרק ובנורווגיה במאה ה-10, שעל שמו נקראת טכנולוגיית הקישור למכשירים בעלי שם). </p><div class="wp-block-image  has-alignright" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><figure class="alignright size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="680" height="907" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_vikings_inline-4.jpg" alt="תמונה של בנטה פיליפסן בשטח חפירה מוקף בדליים של חומר" class="wp-image-3129845" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_vikings_inline-4.jpg 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_vikings_inline-4-287x383.jpg 287w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_vikings_inline-4-337x450.jpg 337w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_vikings_inline-4-139x186.jpg 139w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_vikings_inline-4-435x580.jpg 435w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_vikings_inline-4-582x776.jpg 582w" sizes="(max-width: 680px) 100vw, 680px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3129845">הפיזיקאי בנטה פיליפסן הוביל תיארוך פחמן רדיו בריבה.</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3129845">מוזיאון דרום מערב יוטלנד</span></figcaption></figure></div><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> אבל אפילו עם הכיול הנוסף, פיליפסן לא הצליח לצמצם את טווח הגילאים האפשרי של שכבה נתונה מספיק כדי לדעת בדיוק מתי הוויקינגים הגיעו לראשונה או מתי רשתות מסחר למרחקים ארוכים הגיעו לעיירה.</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> התלקחות סולארית עתיקה מגבירה את הדיוק של פחמן רדיואקטיבי</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> To zero in on the timing of these events, the Aarhus team looked to see if signs of an ancient solar flare were recorded at the site. In 775, a few literate observers in western Europe reported seeing the impact of a solar storm. Celestial phenomena streaking across the sky were described in various ways: a red cross, inflamed shields, fire from heaven. Some people saw “snakes” slither with the same movements as the aurora borealis.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> At the atomic level, solar particles streaming into Earth&#39;s atmosphere kicked off nuclear reactions that transformed some nitrogen atoms into an unstable variant of carbon with six protons and eight neutrons: the isotope carbon-14, or radiocarbon.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Typically, 99 percent of atmospheric carbon is carbon-12, which has six protons and six neutrons. Only one in a trillion atoms of the remaining 1 percent is carbon-14; the rest is carbon-13. But these ratios vary ever-so-slightly over time due to carbon-14&#39;s unstable nature. In 775, the solar storm created 1.2 percent more carbon-14 than usual. That ratio of carbon isotopes became imprinted on any organisms alive at the time.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Physicist Fusa Miyake of Nagoya University in Japan and colleagues first <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/nature11123" target="_blank" rel="noopener">discovered this 775 spike in radiocarbon</a> about a decade ago, in the rings of Japanese cedar trees. Counting the annual rings, she was able to pinpoint the year of the solar storm. It turns out that the sun has on several occasions, about once every millennium and a half or so it appears, sent flares in our direction with enough energy to make measurably more carbon-14.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> So while the Aarhus team peeled back layer upon layer of wet clay and sand along one of Ribe&#39;s ancient streets, Philippsen set out to see if any of those layers might date to 775. Up to her elbows in mud and clay at the site, she searched for the right bits of organic material to date.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “I&#39;ve been trained in all the [excavation] methods, so it&#39;s safe for them to let me be in the trench and work, and you get a really good understanding of the samples,” Philippsen says.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Of all the startling finds in Ribe, the site&#39;s trash held the most potential to shed light on the origins of Viking Age trade. Twigs, rye, barley, oats, nutshells and other refuse still lying around more than 1,000 years later possibly bore the time stamp of the supermassive flare.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Philippsen shuttled between her lab at Aarhus and the dig at Ribe with 140 samples plucked from different workshop layers. Trading her trowel for a scalpel, she diced up her bits of ancient oak and ran them along with samples from the site through the lab&#39;s accelerator mass spectrometer, which counts carbon-12 and carbon-14 atoms by sorting them according to mass.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Two pieces of charcoal and a hazelnut shell from a combmaker&#39;s workshop turned out to have the same ratio of carbon-12 to carbon-14 as the oak tree rings dated to 775.</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Ribe is a time capsule of early medieval trade</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Once Philippsen identified a workshop layer dated to 775, every other workshop and its artifacts above and below fell into a decade-by-decade chronological order. And with that sequence, Sindbæk and colleagues <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-021-04240-5" target="_blank" rel="noopener">pieced together the evolution of trade at Ribe</a> , reporting the findings in 2022 in <em>Nature</em> .</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Around the year 700, ceramics and repurposed Roman glass appear at Ribe, indicating trade with the Franks of the Rhine Valley in what&#39;s now Germany. By the 740s, early Vikings were arriving in ships large enough to carry blocks of Swedish and Norwegian stone. In the 750s, reindeer antler appears from a species not found outside of Norway&#39;s hinterlands — more signs of a Viking presence. Craftspeople in town turned those bulk items into sought-after combs and sharpening stones. In exchange, vendors probably offered the early Vikings beads and brooches that would become the ubiquitous hallmarks of the Viking Age. These items also show up later in other Viking trading towns, such as Birka in Sweden. Finally, around 790, a cache of beautiful beads arrived in Ribe, likely via Russia, indicating new Middle Eastern trade connections. </p><div class="wp-block-image  has-alignleft" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><figure class="alignleft size-full" data-component="lightbox"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1500" height="2071" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_vikings_inline-2.jpg" alt="image of glass beads from Ribe in chronological order" class="wp-image-3129847" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_vikings_inline-2.jpg 1500w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_vikings_inline-2-277x383.jpg 277w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_vikings_inline-2-326x450.jpg 326w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_vikings_inline-2-135x186.jpg 135w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_vikings_inline-2-768x1060.jpg 768w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_vikings_inline-2-1113x1536.jpg 1113w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_vikings_inline-2-1483x2048.jpg 1483w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_vikings_inline-2-420x580.jpg 420w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_vikings_inline-2-562x776.jpg 562w" sizes="(max-width: 1500px) 100vw, 1500px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3129847">These glass beads found at Ribe are in chronological order, from the newest, dating to around 900 (top), to the oldest, from around 700 (bottom). Segmented beads from the Middle East appear after 790 (middle rows and above). After the introduction of those beads, black-and-yellow-striped beads made in Ribe disappear. <em>Click to enlarge</em> .</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3129847">Museum of Southwest Jutland</span></figcaption></figure></div><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> This scenario strongly suggests, if not proves, that Viking explorations began as regional trading expeditions, not as a desperate bid for Middle Eastern silver, Sindbæk&#39;s team argues.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Given the similar timing, the possibility that the raids somehow relate to Middle Eastern trade goods just then finding their way into northern Europe raises important questions.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “We&#39;re seeing this intensification of [Middle] Eastern trade on the Scandinavian periphery of the North Sea, and that precedes the intensification of Viking raiding in the British Isles,” Delvaux says. “Did this trade stimulate the raids? Were they raiding so they would pick up things to engage in Eastern trade? Did the raids start because people wanted to compete with Eastern trade? I could trade with the Muslims for silver or else I can raid the English for it, right?” Delvaux asks rhetorically.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Regardless, the solar flare clearly demarcates a moment of first contact between emerging civilizations. Sindbæk can imagine how it happened.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The Middle Eastern beads, he says, probably traveled north from the Mesopotamian heartland in several-pound bags before being handed over to a merchant in present-day Turkey, who probably followed nomadic trails north to the forest steppe somewhere in northern Ukraine. There, the merchant may have met Vikings who had come east across the Baltic Sea and exchanged the beads for furs or enslaved people. The beads dispersed through Scandinavian markets, ultimately arriving in Ribe.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Ribe is awash in these imported beads after 790, while the locally made black-and-yellow-striped “wasp beads” individually crafted exclusively in Ribe disappear from the archaeological record. The reason, the Aarhus team concludes, is competition.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Craftspeople living several thousand kilometers away mass-produced beads by dicing up long rods of glass. People now had to ask themselves: “Do I want the beads that are made by Sven on the corner, or do I want the beads Olaf is bringing in from God-knows-where, but he could give me 30 of them for the same price that Sven can make me one?” Delvaux says.</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Future questions to address</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The solar flare in 775 and a slightly weaker one in 993 with a distinct carbon spike have revealed how Vikings were trying to touch every corner of the globe. Using that 993 solar flare, another group of archaeologists finally confirmed when Vikings lived in North America. Wooden objects at the L&#39;Anse aux Meadows site in Newfoundland, Canada, hold the signature of the 993 flare. Counting tree rings <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-021-03972-8" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">revealed when the timbers to make those objects had been cut</a> — in the year 1021, the team reported in 2022 in <em>Nature</em> . </p><figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="800" height="450" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_vikings_inline-5-800x450.jpg" alt="photo of a reconstructed settlement at L’Anse aux Meadows" class="wp-image-3129844" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_vikings_inline-5-800x450.jpg 800w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_vikings_inline-5-680x383.jpg 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_vikings_inline-5-330x186.jpg 330w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_vikings_inline-5-768x432.jpg 768w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_vikings_inline-5.jpg 1030w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3129844">The Vikings briefly lived in Newfoundland, Canada, at L&#39;Anse aux Meadows (reconstructed settlement shown). Recent dating suggests the Vikings arrived there by 1021.</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3129844">Dylan Kereluk/Wikimedia Commons ( <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">CC BY 2.0</a> )</span></figcaption></figure><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Vikings weren&#39;t the only ones reaching beyond their horizons at the time. A diverse set of trader-explorers in Afro-Eurasia also survived perilous sea crossings and found each other in towns akin to Ribe. Solar flare–aided radiocarbon dating could bring their stories to light as well.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “We can put different cultures and regions on the same timeline, no matter whether they had a tradition of history writing or not,” Philippsen says. “This makes it much easier to study contacts and the causes and effects of developments in different parts of the world. Environmental and climate records are also dated by radiocarbon … we can also check how societies responded to climate change, and how cultural developments are connected with changes in the environment.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Archaeologist Mark Horton of the Royal Agricultural University in Cirencester, England, agrees that solar flares “enable us to create a much more precise timetable for history.” But in trading towns around the Indian Ocean where he works, for example, dead trees decay out of existence very quickly, leaving huge gaps in the radiocarbon calibration curve for the Southern Hemisphere, SHCal20, making it more difficult to fill them in as Philippsen did.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Next up for Philippsen is helping Aarhus archaeologist Sarah Croix radiocarbon-date early Christian graves to test King Harald Bluetooth&#39;s claim that he converted Denmark to Christianity. If the graves predate his rule, then Bluetooth would&#39;ve been, let&#39;s say, exaggerating.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “Radiocarbon dating now approaches the precision of traditional historical sources, so it becomes relevant for studying &#39;recent&#39; history, not only prehistory,” Philippsen says. “We can thus study the lives of individuals who are not mentioned in historical sources, ie, &#39;normal people,&#39; with the same chronological precision as those of the rulers, the literate, or whoever wrote or was written about.” </p><style>.image-mobile {

    display: none;

  }

  @media (max-width: 400px) {

    .image-mobile {

      display: block;

    }

    .image-desktop {

      display: none;

    }

  }

</style>]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_vikings_feat-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="273531" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_vikings_feat-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title> NASA&#39;s DART mission lofted a swarm of boulders into space</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/nasa-dart-mission-boulder-asteroid-space<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sid Perkins]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Fri, 21 Jul 2023 21:10:06 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Planetary Science]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3129916 </guid><description><![CDATA[Hubble telescope images of the asteroid Dimorphos reveal a halo of 37 dim, newfound objects — most likely boulders shaken loose from the surface.]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<p>When a probe smashed into a small asteroid last year, the collision did more than change the asteroid&#39;s orbit — it blasted a few dozen hefty boulders into space too.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Last September, NASA steered<a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/dart-mission-deflected-asteroid-for-planetary-defense">the DART spacecraft into Dimorphos</a> , a moonlet of the larger asteroid Didymos, to test a strategy for knocking any future Earth-bound asteroids off course ( <em>SN: 10/11/22</em> ). About three months after the impact, the Hubble Space Telescope spied <a href="https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/2041-8213/ace1ec" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a halo of 37 previously unseen objects</a> accompanying the space rock duo in their orbit around the sun, researchers report in the July 21 <em>Astrophysical Journal Letters.</em></p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The boulders probably aren&#39;t bits that were pulverized from larger rocks during the impact. Instead, simulations suggest they were likely intact when they were blasted off Dimorphos and could have been launched off the moonlet&#39;s rubble-covered surface by the energy of either the collision or the seismic waves bouncing around inside it in the wake of the impact.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Still, “there&#39;s a lot of uncertainty in such simulations,” planetary astronomer David Jewitt of the University of California, Los Angeles. </p><figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="680" height="687" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/072123_sp_dimorphos-boulders_inline.jpg" alt="image of the surface of the asteroid Dimorphos" class="wp-image-3129918" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/072123_sp_dimorphos-boulders_inline.jpg 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/072123_sp_dimorphos-boulders_inline-379x383.jpg 379w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/072123_sp_dimorphos-boulders_inline-445x450.jpg 445w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/072123_sp_dimorphos-boulders_inline-184x186.jpg 184w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/072123_sp_dimorphos-boulders_inline-574x580.jpg 574w" sizes="(max-width: 680px) 100vw, 680px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3129918">The last complete image from NASA&#39;s DART spacecraft shows Dimorphos&#39; rubble-strewn surface just two seconds before the probe smashed into the asteroid.</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3129918">NASA, APL</span></figcaption></figure><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Based on the brightness of the new objects, some of the dimmest ever spied by Hubble in our solar system, Jewitt and colleagues estimate that these boulders may be as wide as 7 meters. At least 15 are larger than 4 meters across. Together, the researchers calculate, the boulders probably weigh just over 5 million kilograms — roughly the weight of 300 dump truck loads of gravel.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Repeated observations by Hubble reveal that, on average, the boulders are drifting away from Dimorphos and Didymos at about 1 kilometer per hour — a little faster than the escape velocity for the double asteroid system. So, Jewitt says, the boulders, as well as a presumed multitude of rocks too small and dim for Hubble to see, will eventually break away from the asteroid system&#39;s orbit and circle the sun on their own.</p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/072123_sp_dimorphos-boulders_feat-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="147358" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/072123_sp_dimorphos-boulders_feat-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title> With a new body mapping technique, mouse innards glow with exquisite detail</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/new-body-mapping-technique-mouse-organ<dc:creator><![CDATA[Erin Garcia de Jesús]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Fri, 21 Jul 2023 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Health & Medicine]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3129783 </guid><description><![CDATA[Removing cholesterol from mouse bodies lets fluorescently labeled proteins infiltrate every tissue, helping researchers to map entire body systems. ]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<p>A mouse&#39;s entire nervous system lights up in psychedelic hues. Clumps of immune cells attacking tumors give off a ghostly glow. The vessels that make up the body&#39;s sewer system flare brightly.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> These and other images are shining a new light on the inner workings of mice, thanks to a new technique <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41587-023-01846-0" target="_blank" rel="noopener">that makes whole body imaging cheaper and faster</a> , researchers report July 10 in <em>Nature Biotechnology</em> .</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> See-through mice <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/blog/scicurious/clearing-anatomy-see-through-mouse">are nothing new</a> ( <em>SN: 8/14/14</em> ). But existing techniques to image their insides can be expensive, time-consuming or don&#39;t hit the right target. Now, a study shows that chemically removing cholesterol — an essential component of cell membranes — from dead mice creates spongelike holes in tissues without destroying them. That means tailored antibodies can move through the holes to infiltrate every corner of the body and bind to proteins of interest to make entire anatomical features visible under fluorescent light.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The technique, dubbed wildDISCO, gives scientists an extraordinarily thorough peek under mouse skin to create body-wide anatomical atlases. It&#39;s a bit like Google Maps, says Ali Ertürk, a neuroscientist at Helmholtz Munich. But in place of cars driving around to record every street, antibodies act as streetlamps to illuminate scientific landmarks.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Such maps could help researchers train artificial intelligence programs to simulate bodily processes in mice. The algorithms would aim, for example, to simulate how a drug travels through blood vessels, or predict the path of <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/cancer-genetically-engineered-immune-cells-car-t-therapy-remission">genetically engineered immune cells</a> for cancer therapy, Ertürk says ( <em>SN: 2/2/22</em> ). Computational simulations of biology may help researchers move away from doing animal experiments, he says. </p><figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="680" height="291" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071723_EGJ_nervous-system_inline-1.jpg" alt="An image of a mouse's lymphatic system. Blue indicates lymphatic vessels and organs that are closest to the camera, while yellow marks ones that are deeper inside the body." class="wp-image-3129785" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071723_EGJ_nervous-system_inline-1.jpg 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071723_EGJ_nervous-system_inline-1-330x141.jpg 330w" sizes="(max-width: 680px) 100vw, 680px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3129785">The wildDISCO imaging technique turns a mouse&#39;s lymphatic system into a kaleidoscope of blues and yellows. Blue indicates lymphatic vessels and organs that are closest to the camera, while yellow marks ones that are deeper inside the body.</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3129785">H. Mai <em>et al</em> / <em>Nature Biotechnology</em> 2023</span></figcaption></figure><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> To make the mice glow, Ertürk and colleagues pumped cholesterol-removing chemicals along with antibodies tagged with fluorescent molecular markers into the dead animals via the heart and blood vessels, a proven tactic that allows liquids to traverse the entire body. Then the team made all the tissues transparent, and the mice were ready for their close-ups.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> One of the resulting maps depicts a comprehensive view of the network of nerves that runs beneath the skin and around organs. Another shows off the lymphatic system, an open network of organs and lymphatic vessels that helps fight off pathogens and transport cellular waste for removal.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> These blueprints yielded some scientific nuggets.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Images taken of the nervous systems, for instance, showed that mice with no microbes in their bodies had underdeveloped nerve networks in their guts compared with normal mice, suggesting that the gut microbiome plays an important role in helping nerves develop.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> And in mice with cancer, the team documented clumps of immune cells inside and near the tumors. The role that these clusters play in controlling cancer is unclear, Ertürk says. But wildDISCO offers scientists a way to investigate.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> wildDISCO might also help with studies that focus on animals other than mice, says Yijun Su, an imaging specialist at Howard Hughes Medical Institute&#39;s Janelia Research Campus in Ashburn, Va., who was not involved in the work. Scientists working with fruit flies, frogs or zebra fish might use a similar “recipe,” he says, to take clearer snapshots of their anatomy. </p><figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="680" height="282" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071723_EGJ_nervous-system_inline-2.jpg" alt="An image of a mouse with immune cells (pink) clustered inside and near a mouse’s cancer tumors (olive)." class="wp-image-3129786" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071723_EGJ_nervous-system_inline-2.jpg 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071723_EGJ_nervous-system_inline-2-330x137.jpg 330w" sizes="(max-width: 680px) 100vw, 680px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3129786">Immune cells (pink) cluster inside and near a mouse&#39;s cancer tumors (olive). How the cells might affect cancer progression is unclear, but wildDISCO could help researchers investigate.</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3129786">H. Mai <em>et al</em> / <em>Nature Biotechnology</em> 2023</span></figcaption></figure> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071723_EGJ_nervous-system_feat-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="1208874" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071723_EGJ_nervous-system_feat-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title> &#39;The Next Supercontinent&#39; predicts a future collision of North America and Asia</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/next-supercontinent-book-north-america-asia-collision<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alka Tripathy-Lang]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Fri, 21 Jul 2023 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Earth]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3129252 </guid><description><![CDATA[In his new book, Ross Mitchell traces the dance of the continents through time to predict what Amasia, the next supercontinent, might look like.]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[



<div class="wp-block-image  has-alignleft"><figure class="alignleft size-medium is-resized"><a href="https://bookshop.org/a/21798/9780226824918" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/062223_ATL_supercontinent_inline-270x383.jpg" alt="The Next Supercontinent book cover" class="wp-image-3129254" width="203" height="287" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/062223_ATL_supercontinent_inline-270x383.jpg 270w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/062223_ATL_supercontinent_inline-317x450.jpg 317w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/062223_ATL_supercontinent_inline-131x186.jpg 131w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/062223_ATL_supercontinent_inline.jpg 680w" sizes="(max-width: 203px) 100vw, 203px" /></a></figure></div><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <a href="https://bookshop.org/a/21798/9780226824918" target="_blank" rel="noopener">The Next Supercontinent</a><br> <em>Ross Mitchell</em><br> <em>Univ. of Chicago, $30</em></p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Today, there are seven continents. Some 200 million years from now, there will be just one. In <em>The Next Supercontinent</em> , geophysicist Ross Mitchell previews what the world might look like when Earth&#39;s continents amalgamate into a single landmass.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Although Mitchell&#39;s destination is the distant future, don&#39;t be fooled. His book is as much a romp through the past as it is a look ahead, complete with references unique to the present (like Dwayne “The Rock” Johnson helming a speedboat as it crests a highly improbable tsunami that ravages the Golden Gate Bridge in the movie <em>San Andreas</em> ).</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> On the journey back in time, Mitchell visits how the continents came together in the past to form the previous supercontinents. He begins about 300 million to 200 million years ago with lush, dinosaur-laden Pangaea, which was centered on present-day Africa. He then goes back to a billion years ago to barren Rodinia, whose center consisted of much of today&#39;s North America plus Greenland. Two billion years ago, there was what some scientists call Columbia — the Siberia-centric first supercontinent.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Tracking the paths of today&#39;s continents through history takes some serious scientific sleuthing. This often begins with fieldwork to collect samples that constrain when a rock formed and its latitude at that time. To give readers a taste of such (mis)adventures, Mitchell shares how he lost half his right thumb in the Australian Outback while unearthing some of Rodinia&#39;s mysteries, and when he and a colleague were nearly stranded with their samples on a frigid lake in Canada&#39;s Northwest Territories.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Clues as to why supercontinents form in the first place and what causes their repeated rending also reside in an entirely different field of study — one in which scientists simulate how the “solid but pliable” mantle might have behaved to coax continents along. The mantle regulates the relationship between the crust and Earth&#39;s core, which stores primordial heat. The supercontinent cycle, Mitchell argues, is linked to mantle movement that transfers Earth&#39;s interior heat upward so the crust can release it.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> As heat rises, scientists suspect, continents drift toward regions where the mantle is cold. These cold spots exist where oceanic plates subduct, or sink below more buoyant tectonic plates, into the mantle. Inch by inch, subducting ocean will disappear and bring continents closer together, resulting in a collision that will eventually culminate in a new supercontinent. Mantle simulations suggest that after the supersized landmass has formed, the incessant inward pull ceases as new subduction zones initiate at the coastlines of the supercontinent. Somewhere in the interior of the supercontinent, hot mantle rises, eventually causing the supercontinent to tear, forming new oceans and beginning another cycle.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Using the past to predict the future and understanding the mechanics of the mantle, Mitchell presents his vision of <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/evidence-falls-place-once-and-future-supercontinents">Amasia — the next supercontinent</a> ( <em>SN: 1/21/17, p. 18</em> ). Some researchers have suggested it will form from either the closing of the Pacific or Atlantic oceans. But he posits Amasia will form via the disappearance of the Arctic Ocean as the Americas and Eurasia meet near the North Pole, dragging the other continents along for the ride.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Throughout the book, Mitchell&#39;s clear explanations and carefully chosen images help make sense of even the most complicated concepts (take it from a trained geologist who always had trouble with the particulars of the study of Earth&#39;s past magnetic field — paleomagnetism — which often drive supercontinent reconstructions).</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> But whether Mitchell&#39;s predictions are correct is something no reader will live long enough to find out, though maybe our descendants will. That will require humankind to survive far longer than any other known mammal. But given all our achievements as a species, Mitchell is hopeful we can beat the odds. “While such longevity may seem far-fetched,” he writes, “doesn&#39;t it also sound a lot like us?”</p><hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" /><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <em>Buy</em> <a href="https://bookshop.org/a/21798/9780226824918" target="_blank" rel="noopener">The Next Supercontinent</a> <em>from Bookshop.org.</em> Science News <em>is a Bookshop.org affiliate and will earn a commission on purchases made from links in this article.</em></p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/062223_ATL_supercontinent_feat-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="253204" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/062223_ATL_supercontinent_feat-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title> Time in nature or exercise is touted for happiness. But evidence is lacking</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/nature-exercise-happiness-psychology<dc:creator><![CDATA[Luis Melecio-Zambrano]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Thu, 20 Jul 2023 15:00:07 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Psychology]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3129869 </guid><description><![CDATA[A review of hundreds of studies finds limited strong scientific evidence to support many common recommendations for leading a happier life.]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<p>Go on a run, hike through nature and meditate, and you&#39;re basically guaranteed a happier life. At least, that&#39;s what scores of listicles might lead you to believe. But a new review of hundreds of studies on happiness questions just how strong the evidence is for some of these happiness hacks.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The finding comes in the wake of the “replication crisis” in psychology, where the results of dozens of key psychological studies <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/psychology-results-evaporate-upon-further-review">haven&#39;t been able to be repeated</a> ( <em>SN: 8/27/15</em> ). In response, scientists have reassessed reams of old studies and <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/blog/science-the-public/replication-crisis-psychology-science-studies-statistics">doubled down on the best practices</a> for ensuring that new studies will hold up under scrutiny ( <em>SN: 8/27/18</em> ).</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> To find studies of happiness that applied these best practices, psychologists Dunigan Folk and Elizabeth Dunn of the University of British Columbia in Vancouver combed through hundreds of papers. The team focused on research that studied a large sample of people, which helps tease out real effects, and studies that were pre-registered, meaning that researchers outlined how they were going to conduct a study before starting it. That way, they can&#39;t tweak it midway; it&#39;s the scientific equivalent of calling your shot in pool.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Although studies of happiness were plentiful, studies that met these high standards were relatively scarce. And the evidence they offered, <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41562-023-01651-4" target="_blank" rel="noopener">especially for exercise, meditation and time in nature</a> , was weaker than one might expect, the researchers report July 20 in <em>Nature Human Behaviour</em> .</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <em>Science News</em> spoke with Dunn to discuss happiness, how we can get better at studying it and what science says works — and doesn&#39;t — to build a happier life. This interview has been edited for length and clarity.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <strong><em>SN:</em></strong> <strong>Why study happiness?</strong></p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <strong>Dunn:</strong> Science has given us our most essential human advances. It&#39;s because of science that we got to the moon, that we have substantially increased longevity, that we have COVID vaccines. The scientific method is what solves our greatest challenges, and so I want to apply that method toward understanding happiness.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> I think of happiness as being kind of the ultimate outcome measure. You know, whatever else we might be interested in, what ultimately matters is: “Are people leading happy lives?”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> For me, understanding happiness is one of the fundamental mysteries and challenges of human existence.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <strong><em>SN:</em> What gave you the idea to look into these past studies of happiness?</strong></p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <strong>Dunn:</strong> This research actually started with a question from a journalist who asked, &#39;&#39;These things we hear about in the media as being really important for happiness, like meditation and nature, how rigorous is the research behind those kinds of claims?”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> I realized I didn&#39;t know. We were inspired to go look at the scientific literature, really comb through it to understand how good the evidence is underlying commonly recommended strategies. We didn&#39;t go in with an agenda, but rather just an open curiosity.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <strong><em>SN:</em></strong> <strong>So where did you start?</strong></p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <strong>Dunn:</strong> First, we wanted to identify what strategies were most recommended to the public. So we googled phrases like “how to be happy” and identified media stories providing recommendations. Then we said, OK, these five strategies [practicing gratitude, meditating and being mindful, spending time in nature, being social and exercising] are really commonly recommended to the public as ways to be happier.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> And then we combed through the literature and found every experiment that we could testing the effectiveness of these strategies for happiness. We wanted to look for studies that hold up to modern standards of what constitutes good evidence. We found over 500 studies examining these strategies, but fewer than 60 of them actually met contemporary standards for rigor.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <strong><em>SN:</em></strong> <strong>What did you find?</strong></p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <strong>Dunn:</strong> The key takeaway here is that some of the strategies that have been widely recommended to the public as ways of improving happiness are not actually supported by very rigorous evidence.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> What&#39;s shocking to me is when we reviewed the literature on meditation, exercise and nature, of the hundreds of studies that we looked at, 95 percent of them didn&#39;t include enough people that we would trust these studies by contemporary standards.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> [Take exercise. Dunn and Folk found no study that both had a sufficiently large sample size and was pre-registered. They did find a dozen studies that included enough people to have meaningful conclusions. Five of those studies “found evidence that people feel happier after a single bout of exercise, but only in comparison with rather boring activities, such as sitting in silence or watching a documentary on bookbinding,” the researchers write in the paper. Similarly, the researchers found only four experiments that supported the happiness benefit of spending time in nature and had large enough sample sizes, though none were pre-registered either.]</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Importantly, we&#39;re certainly not saying that this is all snake oil. There are good reasons why these strategies should work. It&#39;s just that there isn&#39;t all that much rigorous evidence to show that they actually do work.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> If something works for you, great. I&#39;m not saying you should stop. It&#39;s important to emphasize that if you&#39;re, for example, dealing with an anxiety disorder and your therapist is recommending meditation, you know, we&#39;re not saying ignore this advice. All we&#39;re saying is that, for the average person trying to get a little bit happier, the evidence is maybe not there yet.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> This is really a call to action to say, hey, we as researchers and as a society need to better understand these topics because they have been so widely embraced by the public and so widely disseminated by the media. We built our castles in the sky; you really need to get some foundations under them.</p><div class="wp-block-sciencenews-content-sidebar" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><h3 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Assessing happiness studies</h3><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Of the hundreds of studies that experimentally tested common recommendations for happiness, only a handful met the gold standard for rigor (larger samples and pre-registered, in blue). Some have one or the other, and the majority didn&#39;t have large sample sizes and weren&#39;t pre-registered.</p><h5 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Common happiness hacks aren&#39;t rigorously tested </h5><figure class="wp-block-image "><picture class="sn-responsive-image"><source srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071923_lmz_happiness_inline_desktop-659x450.png 659w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071923_lmz_happiness_inline_desktop-561x383.png 561w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071923_lmz_happiness_inline_desktop-273x186.png 273w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071923_lmz_happiness_inline_desktop.png 680w" width="659" height="450" media="(min-width: 600px)" sizes="(max-width: 1023px) 100vw, 680px"></source><source srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071923_lmz_happiness_inline_mobile-408x450.png 408w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071923_lmz_happiness_inline_mobile-347x383.png 347w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071923_lmz_happiness_inline_mobile-169x186.png 169w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071923_lmz_happiness_inline_mobile-526x580.png 526w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071923_lmz_happiness_inline_mobile.png 680w" width="408" height="450"></source><img src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071923_lmz_happiness_inline_mobile-408x450.png" class="attachment-large size-large" alt="A bar graph showing the number of happiness experiments on the horizontal axis, the action studied on the vertical and color-coded by how many met the gold standard for rigor." decoding="async" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071923_lmz_happiness_inline_mobile-408x450.png 408w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071923_lmz_happiness_inline_mobile-347x383.png 347w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071923_lmz_happiness_inline_mobile-169x186.png 169w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071923_lmz_happiness_inline_mobile-526x580.png 526w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071923_lmz_happiness_inline_mobile.png 680w" sizes="(max-width: 1023px) 100vw, 680px" data-attachment-id="3129874" data-permalink="https://www.sciencenews.org/071923_lmz_happiness_inline_mobile" data-orig-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071923_lmz_happiness_inline_mobile.png" data-orig-size="680,750" data-comments-opened="0" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="071923_lmz_happiness_inline_mobile" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071923_lmz_happiness_inline_mobile-347x383.png" data-large-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071923_lmz_happiness_inline_mobile-408x450.png" /></picture><figcaption> <span class="credit mobile-credit wp-credit-3129874">D. Folk and E. Dunn/ <em>Nature Human Behaviour</em> 2023</span> <span class="credit desktop-credit wp-credit-3129873">D. Folk and E. Dunn/ <em>Nature Human Behaviour</em> 2023</span></figcaption></figure></div><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <strong><em>SN:</em></strong> <strong>Even if there&#39;s limited evidence, what&#39;s the harm in, say, going for a walk in nature?</strong></p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <strong>Dunn:</strong> Most of these behaviors, like going for a nature walk or meditating, require time and effort. And as somebody who has a child and job, I can tell you time and effort are not in super strong supply.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Particularly for people who are working multiple jobs and have a lot of family responsibilities, finding even 20 minutes on a typical Tuesday where they can do something purely for themselves that they think will make them happy [can be hard]. How they use that 20 minutes really matters.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> And they should be getting the best scientific guidance you can possibly give them about how to make the most of that scarce resource of time and of energy.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> There&#39;s also a potential danger that people could [needlessly] feel like they failed. If they are like, “Well, nature and meditation make everybody happier, and they don&#39;t work for me. I guess there&#39;s nothing that&#39;s gonna make me happier.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> It&#39;s important that we not overstate the strength of the evidence behind these things.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <strong><em>SN:</em></strong> <strong>Did any strategies seem to work in making people happier?</strong></p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <strong>Dunn:</strong> Gratitude comes out looking pretty good, and also chatting with strangers and acting more extroverted. I would always like for the evidence to be even stronger, but those are the strategies I would probably feel the best about recommending from our current review.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> [There is “consistent evidence that people in diverse cultural contexts benefit from making gratitude lists,” Dunn and Folk write in the review paper. The researchers also found two studies that had large enough sample sizes and were pre-registered that found talking to strangers boosts mood. Another study that included enough people but wasn&#39;t pre-registered had a similar finding.]</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> We have another paper in process where we looked at the best studies on happiness, meeting the modern gold standard. From that, there&#39;s also pretty good evidence that spending money on others promotes happiness. And there&#39;s good evidence that giving money to poor people makes them happier.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> It&#39;s not that [psychologists] know nothing about happiness. We do. It&#39;s just that some of the strategies that have been so widely touted and disseminated are not actually among the sort of best and brightest to emerge from our field.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <strong><em>SN:</em></strong> <strong>Do you have personal practices that help you be happier?</strong></p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <strong>Dunn:</strong> [My past research has shown a link between] generosity and happiness. One thing that I&#39;ve done with a group of friends was privately sponsor a family of Syrian refugees. Without really intending it this way, it was the perfect application of all of my research, and was probably the most rewarding experience I&#39;ve ever had.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> I also work out every day. It does put me in a really good mood. But this research has given me perhaps some humility in recognizing that that was the case for me. It&#39;s not like other people would experience necessarily the same benefit as I do from that experience.</p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071923_lmz_happiness_feat-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="204560" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071923_lmz_happiness_feat-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title> Centuries on, Newton&#39;s gravitational constant still can&#39;t be pinned down</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/newton-gravitational-constant-physics<dc:creator><![CDATA[James R. Riordon]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Thu, 20 Jul 2023 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Physics]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3129676 </guid><description><![CDATA[A new experiment could finally answer the question 'What is the strength of gravity?' But it's a hard test to do. ]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<p class="has-drop-cap">There was a secret inside the envelope in the hands of Stephan Schlamminger, one of the world&#39;s leading experts in experimental tests of gravity. He appeared to be on the verge of opening the envelope during a presentation at the April 2022 meeting of the American Physical Society, to read a number that would reveal whether his latest efforts in a lifelong passion had been a success.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Schlamminger, of the National Institute of Standards and Technology in Gaithersburg, Md., sought to <a href="https://meetings.aps.org/Meeting/APR22/Session/S16.2" target="_blank" rel="noopener">measure Newton&#39;s gravitational constant</a> . The secret number in the envelope was a kind of code — an intentional and specific error inserted into his NIST experiment to obscure the measurement as it progressed. Only one person knew the number. And that person was not Schlamminger. </p><div class="wp-block-image  has-alignleft" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><figure class="alignleft size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="394" height="450" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_gravity_inline2-394x450.jpg" alt="A photo of Stephan Schlamminger." class="wp-image-3129747" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_gravity_inline2-394x450.jpg 394w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_gravity_inline2-336x383.jpg 336w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_gravity_inline2-163x186.jpg 163w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_gravity_inline2-508x580.jpg 508w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_gravity_inline2.jpg 680w" sizes="(max-width: 394px) 100vw, 394px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3129747">Stephan Schlamminger of the National Institute of Standards and Technology in Maryland is leading an effort to measure Newton&#39;s gravitational constant, or G, using an experiment that previously tested the value in Sèvres, France. Schlamminger wants to settle discrepancies in recent measurements from labs around the globe.</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3129747">JENNIFER LAUREN LEE/NIST</span></figcaption></figure></div><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Without access to it, he couldn&#39;t know what the experiment had found. Schlamminger had imposed the secrecy on himself to protect against bias in the experiment, including the unconscious bias that can beset even the best experimentalists. It was extra precaution to ensure the integrity of an experiment that could help untangle mysterious discrepancies in measurements of the constant, known as G, that have crept up over the last few decades.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> G, often called “big G” (to distinguish it from “g,” which depends on G and is the special case of the acceleration of gravity near the surface of the Earth), reflects the strength of gravity between any things with mass. It determines the orbits of planets and galaxies, and describes the force that pulls you to the ground. Nobody knows how to predict from theory what the actual value of G should be, says Clive Speake, a physicist at the University of Birmingham in England who developed the instrument that Schlamminger is using at NIST.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> It&#39;s also very difficult to measure. After two centuries of improved precision, recent measurements of G are troubling. A handful of labs around the world have <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/explanation-gs-imprecision-stumbles">turned up values that disagree</a> ( <em>SN Online: 4/30/15</em> ). The scattered values could be a sign of trouble with the measurement techniques among various groups, or there might be a more intriguing aspect.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “There&#39;s this haunting elephant in the room which suggests that maybe there&#39;s something going on that we don&#39;t understand,” Speake says. “If the measurements are right, then it could be the greatest discovery since Newton.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Like so many science presentations in the time of COVID-19, Schlamminger&#39;s reveal was set to be virtual. Presumably other physicists and science reporters around the world were, like me, hunched over screens waiting to see what the secret number would tell us about G.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The time had come to tear open the envelope. But the video feed stopped. The big reveal had been canceled. Puzzling discrepancies in the measurements meant the numbers could not be trusted. The envelope would remain sealed for at least another year as Schlamminger went back to the lab to take another shot at one of the most challenging measurements in physics.</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> What is Newton&#39;s gravitational constant?</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Newton&#39;s gravitational constant is a misnomer. Though Isaac Newton developed his theory of gravity in the 17th century, he didn&#39;t think in terms of G. He was primarily interested in how the force moved objects. Apples falling, planets in orbit and the surprisingly squashed shape of the Earth are just a few of the countless phenomena that Newton&#39;s theory explained, all without explicitly mentioning G. The constant, named for Newton two centuries later, was instead wrapped into the masses involved.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> We now know that Newton&#39;s theory is only an approximation of Einstein&#39;s more encompassing version of gravity, the general theory of relativity. It took Einstein&#39;s theory to explain the intense gravity of black holes and the warping of space and time. Still, back here on Earth, it&#39;s Newton&#39;s theory of gravity that concerns Schlamminger and others wanting to measure G.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The force of gravity depends on three factors: the masses involved, the distances between the masses and G. While the masses and distances differ depending on whether you&#39;re considering the forces between you and the Earth, for example, or a planet orbiting the sun, G is always the same. Along with the masses of elementary particles, the charge on an electron and the speed of light, G is one of <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/units-measure-are-getting-fundamental-upgrade">dozens of constants crucial to science today</a> ( <em>SN: 11/12/16, p. 24</em> ).</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> G, though, stands out from the rest. It&#39;s one of the oldest recorded constants — only the speed of light was measured earlier. Yet despite hundreds of elegant experiments since British physicist Henry Cavendish first measured it 225 years ago, G remains among the least precisely known of the fundamental constants.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> And in a way, our understanding of G has only worsened in recent decades as new, incompatible measurements have come in.</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Recent measurements of big G don&#39;t agree</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> When Cavendish performed his first measurements of the force of gravity in a lab, he relied on a set of lead spheres. Two of them were hanging at either end of a rod 6 feet (about 2 meters) long, and the whole contraption was dangled from a wire. He then placed larger lead balls nearby and measured the forces between the spheres by tracking how the hanging rod twisted on the wire. Although Cavendish was primarily interested in figuring out the Earth&#39;s density, a little manipulation of his results shows that he effectively measured G for the first time. He got a value about 1 percent higher than today&#39;s generally accepted value.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Many of the modern-day G experiments are refined versions of Cavendish&#39;s setup. That includes the one Schlamminger uses. Instead of lead spheres, Schlamminger&#39;s system has precisely machined copper cylinders. Four 1.2-kilogram cylinders, known as test masses, rest on a disk that hangs from a metallic ribbon. The gravitational attraction between the suspended cylinders and four larger, roughly 11-kilogram copper cylinders nearby causes the disk to rotate on the ribbon. Schlamminger calls the heavy cylinders source masses. He&#39;s also done the experiment with a set of source masses made of sapphire crystal to see if G depends on the materials involved (it shouldn&#39;t). Where Cavendish used a large wooden box to protect his apparatus from stray breezes, Schlamminger relies on a vacuum chamber to eliminate the air almost entirely.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Conceptually, the experiment running at NIST is the same as the one Cavendish used. But modern experiments offer much higher precision.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Cavendish&#39;s experiments returned a value of 6.74 x 10 <sup>-11</sup> cubic meters per kilogram-second squared. The number is correct to about one part in 100. These days, the accepted value is 6.67430 x 10 <sup>-11</sup> with an uncertainty of about a part in 50,000, which means an error of plus or minus 0.00002 x 10 <sup>-11</sup> . Some experiments have reached similar precision by relying on pendulums swinging near heavy masses instead of twisting wires.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> But as precision increased, a new problem came along. Measurements over the last 20 years from various groups don&#39;t agree. It&#39;s as if G is slightly different in different places and at different times in a way that experimental error can&#39;t account for. Schlamminger&#39;s apparatus is on loan to NIST from the International Bureau of Weights and Measures, or BIPM, in Sèvres, France, where researchers came up with a value of 6.67554 x 10 <sup>-11</sup> , a <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/notorious-big-g-gets-little-larger">clear deviance from the accepted value</a> ( <em>SN Online: 9/12/13</em> ).</p><div class="wp-block-sciencenews-content-sidebar" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><h3 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The original G test</h3><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Many modern tests of G are based on Henry Cavendish&#39;s original torsion balance design (shown), developed more than two centuries ago. Cavendish hung two small lead spheres at either end of a long rod that was also hanging from a wire. He placed larger lead spheres nearby (inset). How the hanging rod twisted on its wire revealed the force of attraction between the smaller and larger lead spheres. Instead of lead spheres, an ongoing experiment at NIST uses copper cylinders. </p><figure class="wp-block-image "><picture class="sn-responsive-image"><source srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_gravity_inline3_desktop-800x388.jpg 800w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_gravity_inline3_desktop-680x330.jpg 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_gravity_inline3_desktop-330x160.jpg 330w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_gravity_inline3_desktop-768x373.jpg 768w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_gravity_inline3_desktop.jpg 1030w" width="800" height="388" media="(min-width: 600px)" sizes="(max-width: 1023px) 100vw, 680px"></source><source srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_gravity_inline3_mobile-383x450.jpg 383w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_gravity_inline3_mobile-326x383.jpg 326w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_gravity_inline3_mobile-158x186.jpg 158w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_gravity_inline3_mobile-493x580.jpg 493w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_gravity_inline3_mobile-660x776.jpg 660w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_gravity_inline3_mobile.jpg 680w" width="383" height="450"></source><img src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_gravity_inline3_mobile-383x450.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large" alt="" decoding="async" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_gravity_inline3_mobile-383x450.jpg 383w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_gravity_inline3_mobile-326x383.jpg 326w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_gravity_inline3_mobile-158x186.jpg 158w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_gravity_inline3_mobile-493x580.jpg 493w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_gravity_inline3_mobile-660x776.jpg 660w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_gravity_inline3_mobile.jpg 680w" sizes="(max-width: 1023px) 100vw, 680px" data-attachment-id="3129749" data-permalink="https://www.sciencenews.org/071523_gravity_inline3_mobile" data-orig-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_gravity_inline3_mobile.jpg" data-orig-size="680,800" data-comments-opened="0" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="071523_gravity_inline3_mobile" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_gravity_inline3_mobile-326x383.jpg" data-large-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_gravity_inline3_mobile-383x450.jpg" /></picture></figure></div><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The most likely reason for the discrepancies is that there&#39;s something about each experimental system that&#39;s unique. Researchers are keen to track down these sorts of systematic errors. But measuring gravity is tough, both because it&#39;s the weakest of the fundamental forces (gravity is so weak that some modern experiments use tons of material to home in on G) and because everything with mass has gravity. There&#39;s no way to shield the experiments from other sources of gravity, so researchers must attempt to account for the outside influences.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Alternatively, the discrepancies in G could have something to do with where the experiments are taking place. Perhaps the value of G in Sèvres really is 0.04 percent higher than the value of G recently measured in Boulder, Colo., for example. None of the experts contacted for this story think that&#39;s a likely scenario. But in borrowing the BIPM gravity experiment and moving it to NIST&#39;s campus in Maryland, Schlamminger&#39;s efforts should help confirm that G doesn&#39;t vary from place to place. That&#39;s assuming he can work out whatever threw a wrench in his April 2022 reveal.</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Why do we care about the precision of big G?</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Why do scientists need to measure G to perpetually higher precision anyway?</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> According to some experts, they don&#39;t. “From a practical point of view, there isn&#39;t a huge benefit to be derived from knowing G better,” says physicist Clifford Will of the University of Florida in Gainesville. Other constants, like the charge on an electron and the speed of light, “play a huge role in all kinds of important technology, whereas G doesn&#39;t, because gravity is so darn weak,” Will says. “By the time gravity matters, on scales ranging from planets to the universe, what matters is G times mass.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Physicist Claudia de Rham of Imperial College London has a different view. “G governs the strength of the gravitational force. In Newtonian gravity, it tells us how two massive bodies are gravitationally attracted to one another, but in Einstein&#39;s theory of general relativity, this constant communicates how anything in our universe curves the fabric of spacetime.” Getting a better handle on G, she says, might help explain why gravity is so much weaker than electromagnetic forces or the strong nuclear force, which holds the parts of atoms together.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Although general relativity has proved to be one of the <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/century/wild-universe-einstein-general-relativity-spacetime">most successful and revolutionary theories in history</a> , de Rham points out that its description of gravity may not be complete ( <em>SN: 2/13/21, p. 16</em> ). “Testing G to higher precision allows us to understand how constant and universal G really is and if there couldn&#39;t be something else beyond Einstein&#39;s theory of general relativity,” de Rham says.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Some researchers speculate that precise measures of G might one day help uncover the solution to one of the deepest mysteries in science: Why doesn&#39;t gravity fit in with quantum physics? The standard model of particle physics is a quantum theory that describes just about everything in the universe, except gravity. Understanding G better, de Rham says, might lead to a quantum version of gravity, which is necessary to blend gravity into the standard model. Such a “theory of everything” has been a dream of physicists since at least Einstein.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> For Schlamminger, the motivation is multifaceted. “It&#39;s mostly pure curiosity. And right now, there&#39;s salt in the wounds that the agreement [between experimental groups] is so bad.” The thrill of pushing an extraordinarily difficult experiment just a bit further drives him too. “Why do people climb Mount Everest?” Schlamminger says. “Because it&#39;s there.”</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Other approaches to measuring big G</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> One perennial challenge with Cavendish-style experiments is the wires. To interpret what&#39;s going on with G, researchers have to know how the suspending wires respond to twisting or swaying, and how they change as they age.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Some researchers choose to do away with the pesky wires altogether, instead dropping or tossing things to see how they respond to the pull of nearby masses. The most precise versions of those experiments so far toss supercooled clouds of atoms up in a tower and then allow them to fall back down again. By doing the tossing with various configurations of heavy objects nearby, researchers can see how the gravitational force exerted by those objects affects the atoms&#39; trajectories. So far, the experiments have come up short of the most precise suspended-mass experiments by a factor of around 10, achieving a precision of one part in 5,000.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> A recent experiment designed with other purposes in mind also dispensed with wires. The Laser Interferometer Space Antenna, or LISA, Pathfinder mission was a proof-of-principle test for a different type of gravity experiment. It was designed to show that it&#39;s possible to precisely measure the distance between objects in space — key to building a <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/blog/science-ticker/lisa-pathfinder-pave-way-gravitational-wave-detection">space-based gravitational wave detector</a> ( <em>SN Online 12/3/15</em> ).</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> LISA Pathfinder managed to measure the distance between objects well enough to find G to within about one part in 15. That&#39;s crude compared with Cavendish&#39;s precision of one in 100, and much worse than other modern measurements. But it shows that an experiment in space, free of the complication of wires and nearby massive objects like the Earth, has potential to measure G in an entirely new way. </p><figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="800" height="450" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_gravity_inline4-800x450.jpg" alt="An illustration of the spacecraft being used in the LISA Pathfinder mission." class="wp-image-3129750" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_gravity_inline4-800x450.jpg 800w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_gravity_inline4-680x383.jpg 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_gravity_inline4-330x186.jpg 330w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_gravity_inline4-768x432.jpg 768w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_gravity_inline4.jpg 1030w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3129750">Though designed and launched for other purposes, the LISA Pathfinder mission measured the distance between two objects in free fall in a spacecraft (illustrated) well enough to find G to within about one part in 15. This proof of concept suggests G can be measured without the interference of Earth&#39;s gravity.</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3129750">ESA</span></figcaption></figure><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Another shortcoming of Cavendish-like experiments is that they measure forces between objects that are either moving slowly or standing completely still. These experiments can&#39;t say much about whether G stays constant when things are moving quickly.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> In experiments deep inside a mountain in Switzerland, mechanical engineering researcher Jürg Dual of ETH Zurich is replacing static masses with <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/gravity-strength-big-g-newton-gravitational-constant">vibrating beams or rods rotating</a> like helicopter blades ( <em>SN Online: 7/11/22</em> ). The motions result in changes in distance between the moving parts and a beam that acts as a detector, which in turn changes the gravitational forces the detector beam feels. The detector beam vibrates like a tuning fork, and the size of those vibrations offers a measure of G.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Unlike conventional experiments, this one could detect whether G depends on motion, which “might be something quite spectacular actually,” Dual says. As for how likely that is, “I&#39;m completely open,” he says.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> For now, though, Schlamminger and others using hanging masses much as Cavendish did 225 years ago are still providing the most precise measurements.</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> There&#39;s no clear answer yet</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Schlamminger&#39;s lab on the NIST campus is well below his office. “It&#39;s about four stories underground,” he says. “There is less vibration, it&#39;s easier to stabilize the temperature and the lab floor does not tilt as much. Usually buildings tilt with varying wind load. That is not a problem underground.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> On my visit to NIST a month after the canceled reveal, we head down several flights of stairs and take a walk through a vacant hall before entering a room that has a sticky mat just inside. It&#39;s there to clean dust from your shoes as you go in. Even so, Schlamminger switches to a dedicated pair of shoes he stashes in the lab and gives me covers to slip over the soles of my shoes. Then we pass through another, airtight door to see the gravity experiment on loan to NIST. Things must be tidy when you&#39;re trying to do something as difficult as measuring G.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Dust interfering with the tips of measurement probes could throw off readings of the positions of the cylinders. “A second concern, albeit smaller,” Schlamminger says, “is that dust settling on the source masses will change their mass.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The G experiment is smaller than Cavendish&#39;s pioneering design. You could fit it on a modest dining table. Here, it sits on a massive slab that minimizes the vibrations that manage to make it down to the lab. The vacuum chamber hides some of the moving parts of the apparatus from view.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Schlamminger is between runs at the moment, but four copper source masses, each about the diameter of a 2-liter soda bottle, are at the ready for the next G measurement. The source masses ride on a carousel outside the vacuum chamber, while the test masses sit on the disk suspended inside the chamber. </p><figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1030" height="636" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_gravity_inline1.jpg" alt="A photo of lab equipment from the National Institute of Standards and Technology to study the gravitational constant." class="wp-image-3129746" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_gravity_inline1.jpg 1030w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_gravity_inline1-620x383.jpg 620w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_gravity_inline1-729x450.jpg 729w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_gravity_inline1-301x186.jpg 301w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_gravity_inline1-768x474.jpg 768w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_gravity_inline1-939x580.jpg 939w" sizes="(max-width: 1030px) 100vw, 1030px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3129746">In a lab at the National Institute of Standards and Technology, scientists are using an updated version (shown) of a centuries-old experiment to try to determine the precise value of Newton&#39;s gravitational constant.</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3129746">JENNIFER LAUREN LEE/NIST</span></figcaption></figure><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> In the experimental mode that most closely mimics Cavendish&#39;s experiment, tracking the rotation of the disk as it twists on the suspending ribbon offers a measure of the force between the source and test masses, revealing G. In another mode, Schlamminger determines G by finding the force it takes to prevent the disk from rotating.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> A set of sapphire crystal source masses that are the same size as the copper ones are in a case nearby. They can take the place of the copper ones on the carousel to confirm that G is a true constant that doesn&#39;t depend on the materials involved. At roughly twice the mass of the sapphire cylinders, the copper versions provide a better measure of G. Precisely how much each of the source masses weigh, though, Schlamminger doesn&#39;t know. That&#39;s because of the secret number tucked away in the sealed envelope.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “The big M, which is the masses of my big copper masses,” he says, “I have basically asked this mass group at NIST who has measured them to add a random factor.” Any studies he makes of G will be slightly off due to the random factor added to the true masses. Just how far off the measurement is won&#39;t be clear until he opens the envelope. So why didn&#39;t he open it in April 2022?</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “I measured big G for like three months solid,” Schlamminger says, before popping open the vacuum chamber to check the placement of the cylinders. “Then I did another big G run, and the number was different. And that&#39;s why I did not open the envelope, because I figured there&#39;s something that I don&#39;t understand.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> It turns out he had prerecorded his talk and expected to reveal the answer in real time at the meeting. He changed his mind before the presentation streamed, which is why the audience was left wondering.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> There are hints that changes in the quality of the vacuum that come with opening and closing the experimental chamber are related to the measurement shifts. It&#39;s another factor that Schlamminger says researchers will have to keep in mind if they&#39;re to understand the discrepancies in measurements of Newton&#39;s gravitational constant.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> These days, Schlamminger is back at it with <a href="https://meetings.aps.org/Meeting/APR23/Session/B14.6" target="_blank" rel="noopener">another experimental run</a> . But one year on, at the 2023 American Physical Society meeting in Minneapolis, he still wasn&#39;t ready to open the envelope. “I&#39;m very, very careful with it because you can&#39;t unopen the envelope.”</p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_gravity_feat-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="143780" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_gravity_feat-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title> What&#39;s causing this summer&#39;s extreme heat waves?</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/summer-extreme-heat-waves-jet-stream<dc:creator><![CDATA[Nikk Ogasa]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Wed, 19 Jul 2023 14:55:05 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Climate]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3129809 </guid><description><![CDATA[Climate change and meandering jet streams are fomenting this summer’s extreme waves of heat.]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<p>The dog days of summer are upon us. Brutal heat waves are roasting regions around the globe, smashing records with unrelenting severity.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> In the southwest United States and northern Mexico, devastating heat has been scorching the region for weeks. For 19 straight days and counting, temperatures in Phoenix have reached above 43.3° Celsius (110° Fahrenheit), surpassing a record streak from 1974. The Texas city of El Paso has endured an unprecedented 33 consecutive days of temperatures reaching over 37.8° C (100° F), and that streak is only expected to continue. And just after midnight on July 17, Death Valley, Calif., may have sweltered under the highest temperature ever recorded anywhere for that time: 48.9° C (120° F).</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> China has also been enduring extreme heat for weeks. On July 16, the township of Sanbao broke not only the national record with a temperature of 52.2° C (126° F), but also the record for highest temperature above 40˚ N latitude. Meanwhile, southern Europe is in its second heat wave in a week, with Rome recording a new all-time high of 42.9° C (109.2° F) on July 18 while a town in Catalonia, Spain set a new record for the region, 45.3° C (113.5° F).</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> What&#39;s concocting these bouts of extreme heat? It&#39;s partly because the world has been <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/heat-record-june-july-water-climate">exceptionally warm</a> this year, thanks to the compounding of human-caused climate change with a natural climate phenomenon called El Niño, whose influence is known to temporarily warm our planet ( <em>SN: 7/13/23</em> ).</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> But it&#39;s not just that Earth&#39;s a hotter stovetop; the cooks have been busy. The jet streams, powerful ribbons of wind that control much of the planet&#39;s weather, have been meandering and getting stuck, holding bulges of hot air over many parts of the Earth. While that&#39;s not unusual, some scientists have suggested that climate change may be altering the dynamics of the consequential winds.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Here&#39;s what we know about how climate change is impacting extreme heat and how these potentially dangerous events occur.</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Extreme heat waves are becoming more likely</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Let&#39;s start with that hot stovetop. Humans have been warming the planet for decades by emitting climate-warming greenhouse gases into the atmosphere. That&#39;s made extreme heat waves more common, many researchers say.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Since 2004, scientists have conducted <a href="https://www.carbonbrief.org/mapped-how-climate-change-affects-extreme-weather-around-the-world/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">attribution studies</a> to estimate how much climate change may have influenced the probability and severity of a specific bout of extreme weather. These studies essentially simulate the world with and without climate change to compare how often certain types of extreme weather events occur.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The work of the <a href="https://www.worldweatherattribution.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">World Weather Attribution initiative</a> has repeatedly indicated that climate change has made <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/climate-change-storms-deadly-africa-early-2022">extreme weather</a> events like <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/human-driven-climate-change-pacific-northwest-heat-wave-temperatures">heat waves</a> more likely and more severe ( <em>SN: 4/11/22</em> ; <em>SN: 7/7/21</em> ).</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> A May report concluded that an <a href="https://www.worldweatherattribution.org/extreme-humid-heat-in-south-asia-in-april-2023-largely-driven-by-climate-change-detrimental-to-vulnerable-and-disadvantaged-communities/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">April heat wave in South Asia</a> — during which locations in Thailand and Laos set new national temperature records of 45.4° C and 42.9° C, respectively — was made at least 30 times more likely due to climate change.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Another study suggested that a different heat wave in northern Africa and southwestern Europe, which subjected some areas to temperatures <a href="https://www.worldweatherattribution.org/extreme-april-heat-in-spain-portugal-morocco-algeria-almost-impossible-without-climate-change/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">20 degrees C higher than is normal</a> in April, was at least 100 times more likely due to climate change.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Climate change is pushing heat waves in general to have higher temperatures, but it&#39;s having a particularly strong impact on the frequency of the most extreme events, says atmospheric scientist Noboru Nakamura of the University of Chicago.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “What used to be once every 1,000 years might now occur every 20 years,” he says. “It&#39;s still a rare event, but … you can actually feel that in our daily lives.”</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> How heat waves form</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> What&#39;s actually whipping up these summer scorchers, and why are only certain regions getting roasted?</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The answer lies roughly 8 to 14 kilometers high in the sky. There, the jet streams flow at about 177 kilometers per hour on average, though they can reach speeds of more than 400 kilometers per hour — faster than a Shinkansen bullet train.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> These powerful winds control much of Earth&#39;s weather by transporting high- and low-pressure systems around the world.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Jet streams develop where large masses of air with different temperatures meet, flowing faster where the temperature contrast is stronger. When jet streams are blowing strong, they tend to orient themselves more parallel to the equator, says atmospheric scientist Jennifer Francis of the Woodwell Climate Research Center in Falmouth, Mass. “But when those winds get weaker … then we tend to see the jet stream take these bigger meanders.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> When the jet stream meanders, it forms broad waves, with crests and troughs that reach north and south for hundreds of kilometers. Jet streams in the northern and southern hemispheres typically undulate more during their respective summers. Due to Earth&#39;s axial tilt, polar regions receive more warming sunlight during their summers, weakening their temperature contrast with the tropics. As the waves become amplified, high- and low-pressure systems in the crests and troughs encroach farther north and south. Sometimes these pressure systems become stuck over one spot for days to weeks, causing weather to persist over a region.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> When a high-pressure system gets stuck over an area, it pushes air down toward the surface, compressing and warming the air. The high pressure also pushes clouds away, clearing the sky for the hot sun to beat down unabated. These factors compound to produce a heat dome, a phenomenon that scorches and often dries landscapes. </p><figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1030" height="715" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071823_no_jet-stream-heat-waves_inline_1030.jpg" alt="An image of jet streams which are mostly high-velocity wind currents (shown in red and purple)." class="wp-image-3129814" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071823_no_jet-stream-heat-waves_inline_1030.jpg 1030w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071823_no_jet-stream-heat-waves_inline_1030-552x383.jpg 552w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071823_no_jet-stream-heat-waves_inline_1030-648x450.jpg 648w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071823_no_jet-stream-heat-waves_inline_1030-268x186.jpg 268w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071823_no_jet-stream-heat-waves_inline_1030-768x533.jpg 768w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071823_no_jet-stream-heat-waves_inline_1030-836x580.jpg 836w" sizes="(max-width: 1030px) 100vw, 1030px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3129814">Jet streams are mostly high-velocity wind currents (shown in red and purple) that often flow at the altitudes passenger planes frequent. When the currents form broad crests and troughs (one shown over the eastern United States), the winds can weaken (slow winds are shown in green). Swirling high-pressure systems (one shown over the US Southwest and northern Mexico) can get stuck over areas, generating persistent heat. The city of Phoenix is indicated by the green dot. This graphic shows jet stream activity on July 18.</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3129814">N. Ogasa, C. Beccario/ <a href="https://earth.nullschool.net/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">earth.nullschool.net</a> Source: GFS/NCEP/NOAA</span></figcaption></figure><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> An exception is when heat domes form by coastlines — such as the one that has formed by the US Gulf Coast. Since warmer air can carry more moisture, heat domes near the ocean can make for weather that is both hot and humid, a <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/heat-humans-stress-extreme-climate-change-physiology">potentially lethal combination</a> for humans ( <em>SN: 7/27/22</em> ).</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> It&#39;s a bit of a mystery why pressure systems become stuck, Nakamura says, making the phenomenon difficult to predict. It may occur when jet streams become especially wavy, he and a colleague reported in 2018 in <em>Science</em> . The waves may get stuck like cars in a <a href="https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.aat0721" target="_blank" rel="noopener">traffic jam</a> , causing weather to idle in place.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> But this explanation is a theoretical one, and more evidence is needed to validate it, Nakamura says. Until then, he says, the underlying mechanics of those jams will remain elusive.</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The jet streams&#39; uncertain future</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> A related, but similarly unresolved, problem is how climate change may affect the dance of the jet streams in the future. In 2012, Francis and a colleague proposed climate change could <a href="https://agupubs.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1029/2012GL051000" target="_blank" rel="noopener">make the powerful winds more wobbly</a> .</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “The Arctic is warming about four times faster than the globe as a whole,” Francis says. “That means that the north-south temperature difference has been getting weaker and weaker.” As a result, jet streams may be becoming more unstable, she says, and more prone to meandering.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> But that&#39;s still “a very hotly contested hypothesis,” Nakamura says, pointing out that some climate simulations have suggested that in the Northern Hemisphere, the jet stream may actually become less wavy. “There is not a widely accepted consensus on this,” Nakamura says.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Even if the fate of the jet streams remains up in the air, one thing seems clear: Extreme heat waves aren&#39;t going anywhere.</p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071823_no_jet-stream-heat-waves_feat-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="367361" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071823_no_jet-stream-heat-waves_feat-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title> Granite likely lurks beneath the moon&#39;s surface</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/granite-moon-surface-volcanism<dc:creator><![CDATA[Katherine Kornei]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Wed, 19 Jul 2023 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Planetary Science]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3129613 </guid><description><![CDATA[Without plate tectonics or water, granite is hard to make. But a 50-kilometer-wide hunk sits beneath the moon’s surface, lunar orbiter data suggest.]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<p>Watch out Yosemite — the moon has its own impressive rock display.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> An <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-023-06183-5" target="_blank" rel="noopener">enormous chunk of granite</a> , measuring roughly 50 kilometers wide, may be buried beneath the lunar surface, researchers reported July 5 in <em>Nature</em> . Finding such a behemoth, by far the largest granite structure spotted beyond Earth, is a surprise given that forming this type of rock typically requires plate tectonics or abundant water.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> When Apollo astronauts landed on the moon in the 1960s and 1970s, they encountered vistas dominated by basalt. The igneous rock is run-of-the-mill stuff on both the moon and our planet, says Matthew Siegler, a planetary scientist at the Planetary Science Institute in Tucson. “Everything starts as basalt.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> But over time, with enough heat and pressure, basalt can melt and morph into more durable granite. Plate tectonics and water, both <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/century/earth-history-plate-tectonics-volcanoes-earthquakes">mainstays on Earth</a> , often help facilitate that transformation: Tectonic forces can help drag rocks down deep, where it&#39;s hotter, and water, acting like a salt, helps rocks melt at lower temperatures ( <em>SN: 1/13/21</em> ).</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Because the moon has no plate tectonics and very little water, finding copious amounts of granite there would be unexpected, Siegler says. Indeed, out of the <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/nasa-apollo-anniversary-moon-rocks-preservation">roughly 380 kilograms of moon rocks</a> (about the heft of a large bear) brought back to Earth by Apollo astronauts, just a handful of millimeter-sized pieces are granite ( <em>SN: 7/15/19</em> ). “That&#39;s our whole inventory,” Siegler says.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> But Siegler and his colleagues now have strong evidence that a massive piece of granite might be lurking under the moon&#39;s surface. The team analyzed microwave data collected from the farside of the moon by China&#39;s Chang&#39;e-1 and Chang&#39;e-2 lunar orbiters and discovered a geothermal hotspot roughly 9 degrees Celsius warmer than expected. Elevated temperatures are often an indicator of granite, Siegler says, because uranium and thorium — radioactive elements that decay over time and release heat — tend to aggregate within the rock.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> To estimate how large a piece of granite could be lying beneath the region, known as the Compton-Belkovich Volcanic Complex, the researchers ran computer simulations of different sizes of granite buried at different depths. The team concluded that an ellipsoidal hunk of granite roughly 50 kilometers wide and 25 kilometers tall capped by a smaller ellipsoid of granite, all buried four kilometers below the lunar surface, best explained the Chang&#39;e-1 and Chang&#39;e-2 observations.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The big question is how such an edifice formed. One idea that Siegler and his colleagues propose is that a mantle plume — a column of molten rock — once persisted under the Compton-Belkovich Volcanic Complex. That plume would have turned some of the region&#39;s basalt into granite.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> On Earth, mantle plumes famously combine with tectonic plate movement <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/pacific-volcanoes-share-split-personality">to create island chains like Hawaii</a> , Siegler says ( <em>SN: 9/19/11</em> ). But on the moon, where there is no plate tectonics, a mantle plume would just continuously heat one region, he says. “You get a single spot of the crust that keeps getting roasted.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> This is an intriguing discovery that should be followed up with a lunar mission, says Brad Jolliff, a planetary scientist at Washington University in St. Louis who was not involved with the new study. “It&#39;s ripe for a robotic mission that has a small rover that can test some of these properties up close.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> In the next few years, scientists plan to do just that. NASA&#39;s Lunar Vulkan Imaging and Spectroscopy Explorer mission, or Lunar-VISE, which is slated to launch by 2027, will land on the summit of one of the <a href="https://moon.nasa.gov/resources/482/a-lunar-mystery-the-gruithuisen-domes/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Gruithuisen domes</a> . Located on the moon&#39;s nearside, these volcanic features are believed to also contain granite. Lunar-VISE will be able to take a closeup look at the region&#39;s chemical composition, says the mission&#39;s principal investigator Kerri Donaldson Hanna, a planetary geologist at the University of Central Florida in Orlando.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> That&#39;s important because it&#39;s often difficult to capture small details from orbit. Landers like Lunar-VISE can shed light on the moon&#39;s geology, says Donaldson Hanna. “We need new observations.”</p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071123_KK_Compton-Belkovich-Volcanic-Complex_feat-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="315623" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071123_KK_Compton-Belkovich-Volcanic-Complex_feat-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title> &#39;Milking&#39; umbilical cords may help some sickly newborns</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/milking-umbilical-cord-help-sick-newborns<dc:creator><![CDATA[Luis Melecio-Zambrano]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Wed, 19 Jul 2023 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Health & Medicine]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3129539 </guid><description><![CDATA[Taking a few seconds to push umbilical cord blood into a baby’s belly could provide extra essential nutrients. But questions about the practice remain. ]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<p>Giving birth to a child who is unresponsive or struggling to breathe is a harrowing experience. The medical team must quickly cut the umbilical cord and then rush the baby to aid. But taking a few seconds to squeeze blood from the cord into an infant&#39;s abdomen before cutting the cord could help with the infant&#39;s recovery, two recent studies suggest.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The practice, known as umbilical cord milking, is relatively unknown and not without some controversy. But if its promise holds up, it may help protect some of the most at-risk newborns, researchers say.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> During fetal development, <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/blog/growth-curve/public-private-cord-blood-banks-caveats">the umbilical cord</a> brings nutrients from the placenta, which also serves as a reservoir for blood, iron and stem cells ( <em>SN: 4/4/18</em> ). At birth, the infant is still connected to this reservoir, and the <a href="https://www.acog.org/clinical/clinical-guidance/committee-opinion/articles/2020/12/delayed-umbilical-cord-clamping-after-birth" target="_blank" rel="noopener">standard recommendation</a> is to wait at least 30 seconds to a minute before clipping that connection, allowing the baby to take in more of those essential nutrients.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Some studies suggest that for healthy babies, delayed cord clamping can improve some aspects of health, such as iron levels or fine motor skills, <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC6544813/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">for months</a> or <a href="https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamapediatrics/fullarticle/2296145" target="_blank" rel="noopener">even years</a> .</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> For babies born with urgent health problems, however, there&#39;s no time to wait. In these cases, quickly milking the cord might provide similar benefits as delayed cord clamping. But the jury is still out on if or when to use the technique. The American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists, for example, said that there is “insufficient evidence to support or refute umbilical cord milking” in its 2020 <a href="https://www.acog.org/clinical/clinical-guidance/committee-opinion/articles/2020/12/delayed-umbilical-cord-clamping-after-birth" target="_blank" rel="noopener">guidelines</a> , which the group reaffirmed earlier this year.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> In one of the new studies, researchers randomly assigned 10 medical centers in three countries to one of two groups. If an infant was born limp, with difficulty breathing or bluish skin, the cord was immediately clamped and cut in one group. In the other, the umbilical cord was milked four times before being cut. The hospitals then switched practices halfway through the study.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> After <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0002937822006494" target="_blank" rel="noopener">analyzing outcomes for over 1,700 infants</a> , researchers found that babies who had had their umbilical cords milked were less likely to need extra oxygen or other breathing assistance. The newborns were also less likely to suffer from a brain injury called hypoxic encephalopathy that&#39;s caused by a lack of oxygen to the brain before or shortly after birth, the team reported in the February <em>American Journal of Obstetrics and Gynecology</em> .</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> In a follow-up analysis of <a href="https://www.jpeds.com/article/S0022-3476(23)00179-8/fulltext" target="_blank" rel="noopener">blood flow in over 200 of the infants</a> , published in the June <em>Journal of Pediatrics</em> , the researchers found that these improved outcomes were probably due in part to increased blood volume and blood flow to the heart, lungs and brain in the infants who received the cord milking. These newborns also had slightly higher levels of hemoglobin, the protein which carries oxygen in human blood, than babies whose cords were quickly cut.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “We saw dramatic differences in the babies that have this extra blood,” says Anup Katheria, a neonatologist at Sharp Mary Birch Hospital for Women &amp; Newborns in San Diego.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The new research adds key evidence in favor of umbilical cord milking, says Heike Rabe, a neonatologist at Brighton and Sussex Medical School in England who has collaborated with Katheria but wasn&#39;t involved in the two studies. The findings offer important assurance to obstetricians who might be hesitant to adopt the practice, she says. “It should really be getting into standard of care.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The intervention is quick, simple and does not require equipment, meaning it might be readily adopted in places with limited medical resources.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> But the practice could harm some infants&#39; health. Another study lead by Katheria ended early in 2019 after it found that umbilical cord milking increased the <a href="https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jama/fullarticle/2755614" target="_blank" rel="noopener">likelihood of brain bleeding</a> in very preterm infants, those born at less than 32 weeks of pregnancy.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Based on the recent studies, umbilical cord milking “shows promise” in infants born in poor health at or near term, says Sarah McDonald, a maternal-fetal medicine specialist at McMaster University in Hamilton, Canada, who wasn&#39;t involved in the studies. But more research is needed before the practice is recommended for use, even in emergency situations. And for most infants, she and Katheria agree, delayed cord clamping will likely remain the best course of action.</p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071023_LM_umbilical-cord-milking_feat-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="127872" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071023_LM_umbilical-cord-milking_feat-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item></channel></rss>