<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/" xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/" xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"><channel><title> חדשות המדע </title><atom:link href="https://www.sciencenews.org/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org<description> עיתונאות עצמאית מאז 1921</description><lastbuilddate> שני, 06 בנובמבר 2023 22:57:16 +0000</lastbuilddate><language> en-US</language><sy:updateperiod> מדי שעה</sy:updateperiod><sy:updatefrequency> 1</sy:updatefrequency><generator> https://wordpress.org/?v=6.2.3</generator><item><title> מדוע מדענים מרחיבים את ההגדרה של בדידות</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/expanding-definition-loneliness-belonging<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sujata Gupta]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Tue, 07 Nov 2023 14:00:00 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Psychology]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3132811 </guid><description><![CDATA[Feeling detached from animals, places and routines can cause loneliness, researchers are learning, which may expand the list of interventions. ]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<p class="has-drop-cap">במשך מאות שנים, פסטורליסטים של טורקנה מצפון קניה עקבו אחר המים. משפחות עברו פעם כ-15 פעמים בשנה בחיפוש אחר בורות מים לפרות, חמורים, גמלים, עיזים וכבשים.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> אבל אורח החיים העונתי של בני הטורקנה הפך למעורער בעשורים האחרונים. עם הבצורת והלחימה המתמשכת ברחבי האזור, נשים וילדים רבים נשארים במקום בזמן שגברים מסתובבים בנוף - לעתים קרובות על סכנתם. האלימות אילצה משפחות רבות לברוח על נפשן בהתראה של רגע. משפחות אלה, כשהן מופרדות מבעלי החיים שלהן, מתפרנסות בשולי הערים או מתפרנסות במחנות עקירה מוקפים בגידור ארוגים היטב.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> גם החברות שנבנתה על חילופי בעלי חיים מתפרקת. &quot;כשלאף אחד אין חיות, איך נוכל לעזור אחד לשני?&quot; אישה מטורקנה שאלה במהלך ראיון את האנתרופולוג אייבי פייק, שעובד באזור כבר 25 שנה.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> הסבל בתוך הקהילות הללו הוא עמוק, אומר פייק, מאוניברסיטת אריזונה בטוסון. נשים לא מצליחות לסרוק בבטחה את הנוף אחר צמחי מרפא, כגון עשבי תיבול לבלימת דימומים לאחר לידה או לרסן חום בילדים, נשים מתקשות למלא את תפקידן כמטפחות. זהויות של גברים, בינתיים, קשורות לעתים קרובות כל כך בבעלות על בעלי חיים, עד שלשפת הטורקנה יש <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/32799766/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">מילה לתאר אדם ללא חיות</a> - <em>ekebotonit</em> .</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> &quot;הבדידות שבהעדר חיות תופסת מקום מסוים של מצוקה שמתעלה על המזון והפרנסה שבעלי חיים מציעים&quot;, כתבו פייק ועמיתתו ב-2020 ב- <em>Transcultural Psychiatry</em> . &quot; <em>אקבוטוניט</em> ... לא רק מאבד את תחושת המטרה שלו והעדרים מציעים את החברות, אלא לפי הטורקנה, נמחק - אדם שאין לו שום דבר בחברה.&quot; </p><figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" width="1030" height="773" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_loneliness_inline1_1030.jpg" alt="צעיר טורקנה בצפון קניה מתרחק מהמצלמה בעוד כמה בקר צועדים מולו." class="wp-image-3132779" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_loneliness_inline1_1030.jpg 1030w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_loneliness_inline1_1030-510x383.jpg 510w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_loneliness_inline1_1030-600x450.jpg 600w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_loneliness_inline1_1030-248x186.jpg 248w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_loneliness_inline1_1030-768x576.jpg 768w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_loneliness_inline1_1030-773x580.jpg 773w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_loneliness_inline1_1030-263x197.jpg 263w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_loneliness_inline1_1030-560x420.jpg 560w" sizes="(max-width: 1030px) 100vw, 1030px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3132779">צעיר טורקנה בצפון קניה לוקח את הבקר שלו לסכר למים.</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3132779">פרנסיס נקאיו</span></figcaption></figure><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> חוויות הבדידות הללו בקרב רבים מאנשי טורקנה מדגימים כיצד התחושה מתנגדת לאפיון פשוט - זה יותר מניתוק חברתי. המורכבות הזו נראית בתרבויות ברחבי העולם. במחקר שנעשה בארצות הברית במהלך סגירות מגיפת ה-COVID-19, למשל, נשאלים רבים ייחסו את הבדידות שלהם למספר גורמים שהותירו אותם בתחושת ניתוק. אישה אחת החמיצה ללכת למכולת, דיווחה האנתרופולוגית מישל פרסונס מאוניברסיטת צפון אריזונה בפלגסטף בשנת 2022 ב- <em>SSM-Mental Health</em> . אישה אחרת השתוקקה לעיין בערימות בספרייה, פעילות בודדת בדרך כלל.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> המאמצים להרחיב את הגדרת הבדידות כך שתכלול תחושת ניתוק מבעלי חיים, מקומות, הרגלים, טקסים ואפילו מזג האוויר תפסו תאוצה ברחבי מדעי החברה. באוקטובר 2020, למשל, פרסונס כתב את המבוא לגיליון מיוחד על האנתרופולוגיה של בדידות <em>בפסיכיאטריה טרנס-תרבותית</em> .</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> התמודדות עם מרכיבי הבדידות - והצד השני שלה, השייכות - היא לא רק עיסוק אקדמי; זה עניין של בריאות הציבור, כך עולה ממחקר. בייעוץ מאי, <a href="https://www.hhs.gov/surgeongeneral/priorities/connection/index.html?" target="_blank" rel="noopener">הכריז המנתח האמריקני Vivek Murthy על בדידות כמגיפה של בריאות הציבור</a> , תוך ציטוט ממצאים ממחקרים רבים: נראה שבדידות מגבירה את הסיכון של אדם למחלות לב ב-29 אחוזים ואת הסיכון לשבץ ב-32 אחוזים. אצל מבוגרים, בדידות כרונית קשורה לעלייה של 50 אחוז בסיכון לפתח דמנציה. בידוד חברתי יכול להגביר את הסיכון למוות בטרם עת ב-29 אחוזים.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> הרחבת המושגים של בדידות יכולה לעזור להרחיב את ערכת הכלים של התערבויות אפשריות, אומר פרסונס.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> קשירת אנשים לעולם הרחב יכולה אפילו לעזור לאנשים לזהות ולטפל בשינויי האקלים, מציעה הגיאוגרפית שרה רייט מאוניברסיטת ניוקאסל בקלגהאן, אוסטרליה. תהליך זה מתחיל, לדבריה, ב&quot;בניית מערכות יחסים מכוונות עם יותר מבני אדם&quot;.</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> צורות עתיקות של שייכות</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> כדי להבין את השתייכות ובהרחבה את הבדידות, רייט פנה לקהילות הילידים. למרות שהקהילות הללו משתרעות על פני כדור הארץ והן מורכבות מאינספור שיטות ושפות, באופן כללי, הן חולקות אמונה שרווחה נובעת <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/apology-indigenous-communities-mental-health-rethink">מהרמוניה בין אנשים לכדור הארץ</a> ( <em>SN: 23/9/23, עמ&#39; 14</em> ).</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> רייט ועמיתיו למדו לאחרונה את הסיפורים שאנשי יולו האבוריג&#39;ינים מספרים באמצעות <a href="https://researchers.mq.edu.au/en/publications/songspirals-bring-country-into-existence-singing-more-than-human-" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">שירים פולחניים המכונים שירים ספירלים</a> . תרגול עתיק זה בוחן את הקשרים בין מקום, תרבות, אנשים והסיפורים שהם מספרים. הצוות של רייט, כולל חברי קהילת Yolŋu והסתמך על עבודתה של קבוצת הנשים של Gay&#39;wu, פרסם ניתוח של ספירלת השירים של מטריארך אחת בשנת 2022 ב- <em>Qulitative Inquiry</em> . בהתאם לתפיסת העולם של Yolŋu, ארץ Bawaka, מולדתו של השבט בצפון אוסטרליה, רשומה כמחברת הראשית.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> בעודה שוכבת על ערש דווי, החלה המטריארך לשיר על מקומה, על תחושת השייכות שלה, בתוך רשת רחבה של מערכות יחסים אנושיות ולא אנושיות. בהתאם למסורת של עמה, האמהית ראתה את המסע האחרון הזה כלוקח אותה לים; היא ראתה את עצמה כלויתן. &quot;אני יכול לראות את המים המלוחים נושאים אותי, נעים יחד עם הזרם; נושא אותי הלאה אל מעמקי האוקיינוס, שם טמון היסוד של קו הדם שלי.&quot;</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> המטריארך שנבנה מכתב עתיק, כזה שמתגלגל החוצה מארץ חסרת קול, מסבירים את המחברים. השיר הזה תמיד מתחיל משהו כמו: &quot;בתחילת הזמן מישהו היה צריך לדבר בשביל הארץ, זה היה שקט, כלום. ואז זה התחיל בצליל מעומק המים, &#39;הממממממ&#39;. זו הייתה נקודת ההתחלה...&quot;</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> משם, השיר של המטריארך נע קדימה ואחורה על פני דורות כדי לעגן אנשים בקשת הרחבה יותר של הזמן, אומר רייט. המטריארך שרה על שחייה לצד סבתה שנפטרה; היא שרה על בנותיה, נכדותיה ונכדותיה.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> השיר גם מעגן את אנשי יולו למולדתם על ידי מתן קול לדפוסי נדידת הלווייתנים, נקודות דייג מרכזיות וקשרים פיזיים ברחבי היבשה והים. ספירלת השירים &quot;ממפה את הארץ מנקודת מבט של הים&quot;, אומר רייט.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> ספירלת השירים של המטריארך מראה כיצד עבור אנשי Yolŋu, יחסים לא אנושיים הם אמיתיים כמו יחסים עם בני אדם, אומר רייט. עם מערכות יחסים כאלה, אנשים מרגישים שייכות לעולם. בלעדיהם, אנשים מרגישים אבודים.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> כפי שמסבירה בתה של המטריארך, Merrkiyawuy בעיתון, אם חוקי האיזון בין אנשים לאדמה, או מדינה, נשברים, &quot;הספירלה עלולה לרדת ולהתפרץ. זה מה שאנחנו אומרים, הוא יתפרץ ופשוט ירחף ואתה תהיה כמו עלה מרחף באוויר, שום דבר לא ישלוט בך... אם הספירלה הזו תתפרץ, אז השירים נעלמים&quot;.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> אובדן מקום - באמצעות הגירה, פיתוח, שינויי אקלים או סיבה אחרת - יכול <a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1023/B:MEDI.0000034412.24293.bf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">להתבטא כבדידות</a> בקהילות ילידים, כך עולה ממחקרים אחרים. לדוגמה, בשנת 1987, האנתרופולוגית תרזה אונל מאוניברסיטת אורגון ביוג&#39;ין החלה במחקר של 18 חודשים על דיכאון בקרב עמי סליש ופנד ד&#39;אוריל שחיים בשמורת Flathead במונטנה. אבל בכל פעם שאונל שאל אנשים אם הם אי פעם היו מדוכאים, הם תמיד היו מדברים על בדידות. </p><div class="wp-block-image  has-alignleft" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><figure class="alignleft size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="680" height="632" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_loneliness_inline2.jpg" alt="תמונה של המילים לשיר עתיק של ה-Yolŋu בספירלת שירים על רקע לבן." class="wp-image-3132780" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_loneliness_inline2.jpg 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_loneliness_inline2-412x383.jpg 412w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_loneliness_inline2-484x450.jpg 484w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_loneliness_inline2-200x186.jpg 200w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_loneliness_inline2-624x580.jpg 624w" sizes="(max-width: 680px) 100vw, 680px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3132780">קטע זה של ספירלת שירים ששרה אטריארך של יולו על ערש דווי שלה מתורגם כ&quot;אני יכולה לראות את המים המלוחים נושאים אותי, נעים יחד עם הזרם.&quot;</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3132780">Bawaka Country <em>et al</em> / <em>חקירה איכותית</em> 2022</span></figcaption></figure></div><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> &quot;פעם אחר פעם שאלתי על &#39;דיכאון&#39;, ופעם אחר פעם אמרו לי על &#39;בדידות&#39;&quot;, סיפר אונל בגיליון 2004 של <em>תרבות, רפואה ופסיכיאטריה</em> . כדוגמה, אונל ציטט את &quot;בדידותו של זקן המקונן על אובדן שיר שכבר לא מושר&quot;.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> אוניל ייחס את הבדידות הזו לכמה סיבות, כולל תחושת הדרה מהחברה, תחושה קיומית של הפרדה בין העצמי לכוח עליון, ושכול על אובדן טקסים ושפה. העמים סליש ופנד ד&#39;אוריי, היא ציינה, לא ראו את בדידותם כפתולוגית, אלא ראו בה תגובה טבעית לשחיקה באורח חייהם.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> &quot;אנשים הודים בעלי אוריינטציה מסורתית פחות רגישים לעצב ויותר רגישים לבדידות&quot;, אומר ג&#39;וזף פ. גונה, פסיכולוג באוניברסיטת הרווארד וחבר במדינת השבט <em>Aaniiih</em> -Gros Ventre הממוקמת במונטנה.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> אם אובדן קרקע קשור לבדידות, במיוחד בקהילות ילידים, אזי התחושה צפויה לגדול ככל ששינויי <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/australia-wildfires-climate-change">האקלים יזרעו הרס</a> על אדמות אבותיהם של אנשים. ( <em>SN: 28/3/20, עמ&#39; 6</em> ). למשל, שריפות השיחים של 2019-2020 שחרכו מיליוני דונם באוסטרליה גרמו <a href="https://theconversation.com/strength-from-perpetual-grief-how-aboriginal-people-experience-the-bushfire-crisis-129448" target="_blank" rel="noopener">סבל עצום לקהילות האבוריג&#39;ינים</a> , חוקרים באוסטרליה שעבדו עם קהילות אלו כתבו ב-2020 ל-Conversation, ארגון חדשות ללא מטרות רווח: &quot;עבור אבוריג&#39;ינים... שחיים עם טראומת הנישול וההזנחה ועכשיו, טראומת השריפה הקטסטרופלית, האבל שלנו שונה לאין שיעור מזה של אנשים שאינם ילידים&quot;.</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> געגועים לטקסים יומיומיים</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> דגש על הרמוניה בין אנשים לכדור הארץ מופיע בתדירות נמוכה יותר בתרבויות מתועשות, אומר רייט. &quot;העובדה שאתה יכול לקיים מערכת יחסים מזינה עם המקום נפסלה.&quot;</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> אבל כשהמגפה האירה, אפילו בתרבויות מתועשות, תחושת השייכות של אנשים רבים עדיין תלויה בקשרים לעולם היותר מאדם. עם זאת, במקום קשר בין אדם לנוף, מערכות יחסים אלו מופיעות לעתים קרובות בין אנשים והיבטים של הסביבה הבנויה.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> הצורך הזה בקשרים עם הסביבה הבנויה בא לידי ביטוי ברשומות ביומן הנשלחות <a href="https://pandemic-journaling-project.chip.uconn.edu/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">לפרויקט ה-Pandemic Journaling</a> , אומר פרסונס. יוזמה גלובלית זו לאיסוף חוויות של אנשים ממשבר הבריאות ההיסטורי צברה כ-22,000 כניסות מ-1,750 אנשים ממאי 2020 עד ינואר 2022.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> &quot;הבדידות מתגנבת אליי. זה מופיע מחוץ לשדה השמאלי. הרצון פשוט ללכת לבלות עם חברים, לצאת לאכול, אפילו לעיין בערימות בספרייה&quot;, כתבה דניז, שתוארה כאישה גרושה במערב התיכון השחורה בשנות ה-60 לחייה.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> הכלים האופייניים שפסיכולוגים משתמשים בהם כדי למדוד בדידות כנראה מפספסים את התחושות הללו, דיווחה פרסונס במאמרה ב-2022 ב- <em>SSM-Mental Health</em> . היא הגיעה למסקנה הזו לאחר שהסתכלה על 35 כותבי כתבי עת בארה&quot;ב, רבים עם מספר ערכים, שהשתמשו במילים המכילות את השברים &quot;בודד&quot; או &quot;מבודד&quot; בערך אחד לפחות. כותבי כתבי העת גם מילאו סקר בדידות בן חמש הצהרות לצד הערך הראשון שלהם ולאחר מכן כל שישה שבועות לאחר מכן. כותבי כתבי עת הגיבו &quot;כן&quot;, &quot;פחות או יותר&quot; או &quot;לא&quot; להצהרות כגון: &quot;אני מתגעגע שיש אנשים סביבי&quot;. &quot;יש הרבה אנשים שאני יכול לסמוך עליהם כשיש לי בעיות.&quot; &quot;יש מספיק אנשים שאני מרגיש קרוב אליהם.&quot;</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> למרות שנשאלים רבים דיווחו שהם מרגישים בודדים בערכים שלהם, הם <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S2666560322000615" target="_blank" rel="noopener">עדיין קיבלו ציון נמוך בסקר הבדידות</a> , מצא פרסונס. לדוגמה, באותו תאריך שטיילור, שתוארה כבן עשרים ומשהו, לבן רווק לא בינארי, כתבה שהם &quot;מעולם לא היו בודדים יותר&quot;, הם קיבלו ציון 0 בסקר הבדידות.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> פרסונס מייחס את אי ההתאמה למגבלות בסקר. הסקר הפסיכולוגי שנעשה בו שימוש בפרויקט היומן, שנקרא סולם הבדידות של De Jong Gierveld, וסקר נוסף בשימוש נרחב, UCLA Loneliness Scale, מגדירים שניהם בדידות כסוג של כאב חברתי הנגרם כתוצאה מהיעדר מורגש של רשת חברתית או מערכות יחסים משמעותיות. .</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> לפי תכנון, אם כן, רוב סקרי הבדידות מחמיצים את הקשרים של אנשים למקומות, פעילויות או אפילו היכרות מזדמנים. בפרויקט היומן, אנשים כתבו על חסרים טקסים ומנהגים אחרים, כגון חגיגות יום הולדת, חגים, שירותי דת והלוויות, או מקומות חסרים, כגון חדר כושר, חנות מכולת, ספרייה ובתי חברים, מציין פרסונס. אנשים כתבו גם על ההחמצה של מפגשים יומיומיים עם אחרים, על אינטראקציות ארציות לכאורה שיכולות להתעורר כאשר אנשים משוטטים בקהילות שלהם.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> תחושות הבדידות הללו מופיעות באחד הערכים של טיילור. הם כותבים: &quot;לא רק אני מתגעגע לחברים שלי, אלא גם לזרים. אני מתגעגע למפגשים האקראיים שהיו לי פעם עם אנשים ברחוב, בחנויות, בברים. אני מתגעגע ליצור קשר עם מישהו ואז ללכת בדרכים שלנו&quot;.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> סולם הבדידות של De Jong Gierveld הוא מצוין בללכוד כמיהה לסוג של מערכות יחסים עמוקות ומשמעותיות שאנשים מקשרים בדרך כלל עם בדידות, אבל הוא מפספס סוגים אחרים של בדידות, אומר פרסונס. &quot;זה לא תופס מקום בכלל. זה לא להרים שיטות&quot;.</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> הרחבת ערכת הכלים של בדידות</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> הכללת הסביבה הבנויה בהערכות של בדידות עדיין אינה שכיחה. אבל אדריכלים, שמקצועם נשען על הבנת האופן שבו אנשים נעים בקהילות שלהם, חושבים לעתים קרובות באופן אינטואיטיבי כיצד עיצוב הסביבה הפיזית יכול להחמיר את תחושות הבידוד או לטפח שייכות.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> &quot;בדרך כלל אנו חושבים על בדידות כעל חוויה מצבית, חברתית או נפשית יחידה של ניתוק ממקום, ממקום מגור או מבני אדם אחרים&quot;, נכתב בשורה הפותחת של <a href="https://projects.tuni.fi/uploads/2021/06/7cca87af-lobe_pallasmaa.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">הפרק של האדריכל הפיני ג&#39;והאני פלסמה</a> בספר החיבורים וההרצאות מ-2021 <em>. הסביבה הבנויה</em> .</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> אדריכלים רבים, כולל פלסמה, מצאו השראה בכתביו של הפילוסוף הגרמני מרטין היידגר, אשר האמין שדירות מספקות אמצעי מחסה וביטוי עצמי כאחד. לפיכך, אדריכלים מעצבים סביבות שמעניקות לחיים משמעות, הוא טען.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> מדעני חברה מתחילים להצטרף לאדריכלים לחשוב כיצד הסביבה הבנויה יכולה להשפיע על הבדידות. בייעוץ האחרון שלו לבריאות הציבור, המנתח הכללי מרתי התווה שישה עמודי תווך לקידום הקשר החברתי. בנדבך הראשון, הוא המליץ ​​להקל על חיבור בין אנשים באמצעות תכנון עירוני טוב יותר, כגון מתן גישה נוחה לשטחים ירוקים וחיזוק טווח ההגעה של התחבורה הציבורית.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> באופן דומה, בינואר, צוות חוצה-תחומי של חוקרים באוסטרליה ואנגליה, שתחומי התמחותם כוללים תכנון עירוני, בריאות הציבור וסוציולוגיה, זיהה כמה <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1353829222002234?via%3Dihub" target="_blank" rel="noopener">מאפיינים עיצוביים עירוניים שיש להם פוטנציאל להפחית את הבדידות</a> . מאפיינים אלה כוללים חללים משותפים, יכולת הליכה, תחבורה ציבורית, עיצוב דיור, תחושת בטיחות וגישה למרחבים טבעיים.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> בעוד שהפוקוס של פרויקטים של עיצוב עירוני שכאלה נועד לעתים קרובות לקרב אנשים, ישנה מודעות גוברת לכך שחיבור אנשים עם העולם הטבעי עשוי גם להקל על הבדידות. &quot;אנשים יכולים להיות מבודדים חברתית אבל עדיין לא להרגיש בודדים&quot;, אומרת אמילי רוגל, אפידמיולוגית סביבתית מאוניברסיטת סידני. &quot;הם עשויים למצוא את היכולת הזו להתחבר לקשר ביופילי ולצאת לראות חיות בר ולטייל בין העצים. [זה יכול להיות] מספיק כדי לגרום להם להרגיש מחוברים לעולם הרחב. הם לא בהכרח צריכים אינטראקציה עם חברים או בני משפחה כדי לעשות את זה&quot;.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> קחו למשל פרויקט קטן בניו זילנד שמטרתו להפיג את הבדידות, בין השאר, על ידי סיוע לאנשים להתחבר מחדש למשפחותיהם המורחבות ולאדמות אבותיהם. חברי תת-שבט מאורי אחד, Ngāti Whātua Ōrākei, פיתחו <em>פאפאקאינגה</em> בת 30 בתים, סוג של מערך מגורים מאורי קהילתי, על אדמת אבות. פרויקט זה, שהושלם בשנת 2016, הפגיש בין אנשים על ידי חיבור בין בתים דרך נתיבים משותפים, גינות קהילתיות ומרחבי משחק לילדים. </p><figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="680" height="450" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_loneliness_inline3.jpg" alt="מבט עילי של קהילה באוקלנד, ניו זילנד. אזור באמצע נצבע בעוד אזורים בקצוות החיצוניים הם בשחור-לבן." class="wp-image-3132781" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_loneliness_inline3.jpg 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_loneliness_inline3-579x383.jpg 579w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_loneliness_inline3-281x186.jpg 281w" sizes="(max-width: 680px) 100vw, 680px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3132781">כדי לטפח קשרים קהילתיים, קבוצה מאורית באוקלנד פיתחה קהילה משותפת המכונה <em>papakāinga</em> (אזור צבעוני במבט אווירי זה).</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3132781">קורות חיים Olin <em>et al</em> / <em>Wellbeing, Space and Society</em> 2022</span></figcaption></figure><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> מפתחים רצו שאנשים ירגישו כאילו הם <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S2666558122000094?via%3Dihub" target="_blank" rel="noopener">הולכים באותם נתיבים כמו אבותיהם</a> , כתבו חוקרים בגיליון 2022 של <em>Wellbeing, Space and Society</em> . הם קיוו שהתחושה הזו תעזור לתושבים להרגיש נטועים בתרבותם ובקשת הזמן הארוכה. גם כאשר בנייה על אדמות אבות אינה אפשרית, לקירוב חברי קהילה מרוחקים לעתים קרובות יש פוטנציאל להחיות שפות ומנהגים תרבותיים, מציינים המחברים. אבל יש צורך במחקר נוסף כדי לדעת אם חזרה ל- <em>papakāinga</em> מפחיתה את הבדידות.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> השורה התחתונה היא שלהרחבת האופן שבו אנו חושבים על בדידות יש פוטנציאל להרחיב את ערכת הכלים של התערבויות אפשריות, אומר פרסונס. &quot;אנחנו יכולים לווסת את הבדידות שלנו על ידי לא בהכרח להתקשר לחבר אלא על ידי יציאה, יציאה לטיול, או הליכה לספרייה, או ללכת ולשבת בבית קפה.&quot; </p><figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="680" height="450" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_loneliness_inline4.jpg" alt="ילד צעיר רוכב על אופניים חולף על פני בית." class="wp-image-3132782" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_loneliness_inline4.jpg 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_loneliness_inline4-579x383.jpg 579w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_loneliness_inline4-281x186.jpg 281w" sizes="(max-width: 680px) 100vw, 680px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3132782">ה- <em>papakāinga</em> באוקלנד כולל 30 בתים המחוברים בגנים משותפים ואזורי משחקים לילדים (ילד רוכב על אופניים בשכונה, מוצג).</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3132782">Ngāti Whātua Ōrākei</span></figcaption></figure><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> בדידות ושינויי אקלים</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> לפני שנים רבות עברתי לעיר קטנה בניו אינגלנד בעודי מספר חודשים בהריון. לא הכרתי אף אחד מלבד בעלי וביליתי את ימי הבדידות שלי בשיטוט ביער מאחורי הבית שלי. פעם אחת, אחרי שהתינוק שלי נולד, חגרתי אותו במנשא וצפצפתי במורד סוללה תלולה. שם, על שפת אגם, התמקם בול עץ בחוף הסלעי. היינו מבלים שעות בצפייה בגלים נובטים בקליפת העץ הגסה. כשצפיתי בלונים צוללים אחר דגים בקיץ ושמעתי גלים מנפצים קרח כמו זכוכית בחורף, הבדידות שלי ירדה לזמן קצר.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> נזכרתי ביומן הזה לאחר שדיברתי עם שרה רייט על ספירלות שירים ומדוע כולנו צריכים לטפח מערכות יחסים מכוונות עם העולם הטבעי. מעולם לא התייחסתי למערכת היחסים שלי עם היומן כחשובה במיוחד, או אפילו כמערכת יחסים בכלל. אבל רייט גרם לי להבין שבמקום החדש והלא מוכר הזה, העץ סיפק מקום מפלט. דבריה גם הסבירו את העצב שחשתי לאורך השנים כשהגלים קרעו את קליפת העץ - תהליך מואץ ללא ספק על ידי אגם שקפא במשך פחות ופחות בחורף.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> יש מילה לתאר את מה שהרגשתי. בתחילת שנות ה-2000, הפילוסוף הסביבתי גלן אלברכט מאוניברסיטת סידני טבע את המונח &quot; <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/18027145/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">סולסטלגיה</a> &quot; כדי לתאר את הכאב או המחלה שאדם חווה כאשר אסונות טבעיים או מעשה ידי אדם הורסים את ביתו. מבחינה אטימולוגית, מקור המילה הן בנחמה והן בשיממון. לשממה, כתב אלברכט ב-2007, יש &quot;משמעויות הקשורות לנטישה ולבדידות&quot;. סולסטלגיה היא גם משחק על נוסטלגיה. </p><figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1030" height="704" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_loneliness_inline5_1030.jpg" alt="תמונה של נער צעיר עומד על בול עץ התלוי מעל גוף מים. עצים לאורך גוף המים." class="wp-image-3132783" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_loneliness_inline5_1030.jpg 1030w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_loneliness_inline5_1030-560x383.jpg 560w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_loneliness_inline5_1030-658x450.jpg 658w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_loneliness_inline5_1030-272x186.jpg 272w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_loneliness_inline5_1030-768x525.jpg 768w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_loneliness_inline5_1030-849x580.jpg 849w" sizes="(max-width: 1030px) 100vw, 1030px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3132783">תרבויות רבות מכירות בכך שאנשים המנותקים ממקומות, מבעלי חיים ומאורחות חיים יכולים להרגיש בודדים. הסופרת סוג&#39;אטה גופטה חוותה סוג כזה של בדידות כשבול עץ שבו ביקרה לעתים קרובות (בנה מוצג עם היומן) צף משם.</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3132783">ס.גופטה</span></figcaption></figure><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> אלברכט הרגיש נאלץ ליצור מונח כזה לאחר שצפה וראיין למעלה מ-50 אנשים שחיים באזור האנטר ואלי מצפון לסידני, שם הייתה כרייה אינטנסיבית. תושבים הביעו דאגה לגבי האופן שבו הכרייה משפיעה על בריאותם ורווחתם. &quot;העובדה שאתה יכול לראות את ערמות המכרות הענקיות וכו&#39; גורמת לך לחשוב שמתישהו בעתיד עשויות להיות השלכות איומות על תנועת שולחן המים בעמק&quot;, אמר אדם בשם ליאו. אישה בשם איב אמרה, &quot;כשהפחם ייעלם, אנשי סינגלטון יישארו עם דבר מלבד &#39;החלל הסופי&#39;. ”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> חווית התושבים אירונית, ציין אלברכט. אנשים אלה הם צאצאים של המתיישבים שנישלו קהילות ילידים מארצם. כעת, &quot;הגל השני של הקולוניזציה&quot;, כתב אלברכט, &quot;מוביל לנישול מוחלט עבור חלקם ולסולסטגיה עבור אלה שנותרו מאחור&quot;. במילים אחרות: שממה, נטישה ובדידות.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> בשנים האחרונות צצו מונחים קשורים: <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/scientists-grief-climate-change-warming-mental-health-ecology">חרדה אקולוגית וצער אקלים</a> ( <em>SN: 29/2/20, עמ&#39; 22</em> ). אולם בניגוד לסולסטלגיה, חוקרים ממעטים לחבר את הרעיונות הללו לבדידות. זה משתנה. בשנת 2022, סקר מקוון של למעלה מ-3,000 מבוגרים גרמנים, למשל, הראה שאלו שקיבלו ציון גבוה בבדידות בסולם הבדידות של דה יונג גירבלד נטו גם <a href="https://www.mdpi.com/1660-4601/19/22/14991" target="_blank" rel="noopener">הם לקבל ציון גבוה בחרדת אקלים</a> בסולם אחר.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> מונחים אלה מבהירים כי בניית מערכת יחסים עם המרכיבים הלא אנושיים של העולם שלנו היא מתוקה מרירה בתקופה זו של שינויי אקלים מהירים. אנחנו באים לאהוב את מה שאנחנו עלולים להפסיד. עם זאת, בהיעדר מערכות יחסים עמוקות אלו, כיצד נוכל לדאוג לעולם בו אנו חיים?</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> בחורף שעבר בעיר שלי בניו אינגלנד, לא ירד שלג עד אמצע פברואר והמים סביב הבול מעולם לא קפאו. החודשים האלה של גלים מכים היו קשים על בול העץ. כשירדתי אל החוף הסלעי ההוא ביום אביב בוצי אחד, שני ילדיי בגיל בית הספר נגררו, הבול היה חלק למגע ולבן כעצם.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> בטיול סולו כמה שבועות לאחר מכן, גיליתי שהבול נעלם. זה היה, אחרי כל כך הרבה שנים של החזקה, ריחף משם.</p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_loneliness_feat-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="229042" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_loneliness_feat-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title> מותם המסתורי של עשרות הפילים של זימבבואה נפתר</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/death-zimbabwe-elephants-bacterium<dc:creator><![CDATA[Tawanda Karombo]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Tue, 07 Nov 2023 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Animals]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3132896 </guid><description><![CDATA[A bacterium never before identified in elephants or implicated in deadly internal hemorrhaging killed Zimbabwe elephants in 2020, genetic tests show. ]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<p>לפני שלוש שנים, עשרות פילים אפריקאים מתו באופן מסתורי בזימבבואה. כעת אישרו מדענים את הרוצח שלהם: חיידק נדיר ולא ידוע שיכול לגרום לדלקת באיברים המובילה לדימום קטלני.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> החיידק, שזכה לכינוי <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-023-41987-z" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Pasteurellaceae Bisgaard taxon 45, הופיע</a> בדגימות משישה מתוך 15 פילים שנותחו, כך מדווחים חוקרים ב-25 באוקטובר ב- <em>Nature Communications</em> . הפתוגן קשור קשר הדוק ל- <em>Pasteurella multocida,</em> הידוע כגורם לספטיקמיה דימומית, או הרעלת דם קטלנית, אך טקסון Bisgaard 45 לא היה מעורב בעבר בזיהומים כאלה.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> עדיין לא ברור כיצד נדבקו הפילים של זימבבואה, אומרים לורה רוזן ועמיתיה. רוזן הוא אפידמיולוג בקבוצת המשנה לבריאות בעלי חיים של אזור השימור חוצה הגבולות של קוונגו-זמבזי במפלי ויקטוריה, זימבבואה. אבל התוצאות אכן פותרות חלק אחד של תעלומה שרדפה מאמצים להגן על הפילים האפריקאים של האזור ( <em>Loxodonta Africana</em> ), שנמצאים <a href="https://www.iucn.org/news/species-survival-commission/202108/shrinking-spaces-worlds-largest-land-animal#:~:text=In%202021%2C%20African%20Savanna%20Elephants,time%20of%20about%2025%20years)." target="_blank" rel="noopener">בסכנת הכחדה</a> , על פי האיגוד הבינלאומי לשימור הטבע.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> מאוגוסט עד נובמבר 2020, 35 פילים נמצאו מתים בצפון מערב זימבבואה. בבוטסואנה השכנה, <a href="https://bioone.org/journals/african-journal-of-wildlife-research/volume-50/issue-1/056.050.0149/Mass-Die-Off-of-African-Elephants-in-Botswana--Pathogen/10.3957/056.050.0149.full" target="_blank" rel="noopener">לא פחות מ-350 פילים מתו לפתע</a> באותה שנה. <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/african-elephant-mass-death-botswana">מותם של הפילים הבוטסואנה יוחס לציאנובקטריה</a> ( <em>SN: 5/14/21</em> ).</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> אבל אין ראיות המעידות על ציאנובקטריה במותם של הפילים של זימבבואה, אומרים החוקרים. גם לא אנתרקס הראיות שלהם, חשוד נוסף ברוצח, אשמה: בעלי חיים אחרים היו נפגעים, ולגופות לא היו תסמינים מודיעים.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> תוצאות שלאחר המוות וממצאי מעבדה ראשוניים הצביעו על סוג הדימום הדלקתי של איברים פנימיים ורקמות גופניות ש- <em>P. multocida</em> יכול לגרום <em>.</em> הפילים סבלו מטחול וכבד מוגדלים ומדימום פנימי נרחב ומוות רקמות.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> בעוד שספטיקמיה דימומית לא נראתה בפילים אפריקאים בעבר, היא זוהתה כקוטל חיות בר באזורים אחרים. לדוגמה, בקזחסטן, זיהומי <em>P. multocida</em> <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/heres-why-so-many-saiga-antelope-mysteriously-died-2015">הפילו יותר מ-200,000 אנטילופות סייגה</a> בשנת 2015 ( <em>SN: 29/1/18</em> ). חוקרים חשדו כי טמפרטורות ולחות גבוהות מהרגיל גרמו לחיידק - שבדרך כלל חי ללא מזיק באף של האנטילופות - להתרבות ולהפוך לקטלני.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> אבל לאחר בדיקות מעבדה מתוחכמות יותר של הדגימות מהפילים של זימבבואה, גם <em>P. multocida</em> נשלל.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> &quot;מדגימות התרבות התברר שלא היה לנו <em>P. multocida</em> אלא משהו אחר דומה&quot;, אומר רוזן. ניתוח גנטי ובידוד של החיידק בשש הדגימות אישרו את החשדות הגוברים שטקסון 45 של Bisgaard הוא האשם.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> דגימות מתשעת הפילים האחרים לא הציגו את טקסון 45 של Bisgaard מכיוון שהם היו רקובים מדי, או שהצוות לא הצליח לקבל את האישורים הדרושים כדי לשלוח אותם למעבדות מתוחכמות יותר במהירות מספקת. אבל החיידק אשם בכל מקרי המוות, חושד הצוות, כמו גם בעוד 14 פילים שמתו בפתאומיות בשנת 2019. &quot;ייתכן שמקרים קודמים הוחמצו&quot;, כותבים החוקרים.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> טקסון 45 של ביסגורד בודד בעבר מפצעי נשיכת נמרים ואריות בבני אדם, כמו גם משבב ותוכים בריאים בשבי, אומרים החוקרים. עדיין לא ידוע אם החיידק הוא חלק מהפלורה הרגילה של הפילים והאם חום, מתח או גורמים אחרים יכולים לגרום לו להתרבות ולהפוך לקטלני. זה גם לא ברור איך או אם הפכידרמים החברתיים ביותר עשויים להעביר את הפתוגן זה לזה.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> אבל הממצאים מוסיפים לרשימה ההולכת וגדלה של פתוגנים שצריך לשים לב אליהם כאשר מתרחשים מוות מסתורי של פילים וחיות בר אחרות באפריקה, אומר שאהאן אזים, מיקרוביולוג וטרינרי באוניברסיטת וטרינריה ומדעי בעלי החיים בלאהור, פקיסטן, שלא היה מעורב ב המחקר.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> כמו כן, חשוב למדענים לבדוק עוד אילו בעלי חיים נושאים את החיידק באופן קבוע ולזהות את תפקידם ואת הסביבה הקשורה להם בהתפשטות טקסון ביסגורד 45 בקרב פילים אפריקאים, אומר אזים.</p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/103123_tk_Zimbabwe-elephant-deaths_feat-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="174452" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/103123_tk_Zimbabwe-elephant-deaths_feat-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title> ה-CDC מרחיב את מעקב המחלות שלו אחר נוסעים בינלאומיים</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/cdc-expand-disease-surveillance-international-travelers<dc:creator><![CDATA[Betsy Ladyzhets]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Mon, 06 Nov 2023 19:21:26 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Health & Medicine]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3132932 </guid><description><![CDATA[Passengers at four major U.S. airports will now be tested for over 30 pathogens through a mix of wastewater testing and voluntary nasal swabs.]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<p>המרכז האמריקאי לבקרת מחלות ומניעתן <a href="https://investors.ginkgobioworks.com/news/news-details/2023/Ginkgo-Bioworks-and-XWELL-Implement-Expanded-CDC-Traveler-based-Genomic-Surveillance-Program-to-Test-for-More-than-30-Known-Pathogens/default.aspx" target="_blank" rel="noopener">מרחיב את האופן שבו הוא עוקב אחר מחלות</a> בקרב מטיילים בינלאומיים, בדיוק בזמן לעונת הנגיפים החורפית.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> לנוסעים שחוזרים לארבעה שדות תעופה בינלאומיים גדולים יש כעת אפשרות להיבדק עבור יותר מ-30 פתוגנים, בהתבסס על תוכנית העוקבת אחר גרסאות של קורונה, <a href="https://www.cdc.gov/media/releases/2023/s1107-testing-respiratory-viruses.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">הודיע ​​ה-CDC ב-6 בנובמבר.</a></p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> בדיקה מורחבת זו, שהחלה זה עתה, תימשך במשך שלושה חודשים כתוכנית פיילוט שנועדה לעקוב אחר מחלות דרכי נשימה בחורף כגון שפעת עונתית. התוכנית גם תסנן מי שפכים ממטוסים ומטרמינלים של נמלי תעופה, ותוסיף נתונים ברמת האוכלוסייה למידע ממשטחי אף מרצון.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> תוכנית זו עלולה לתפוס איומים בריאותיים פוטנציאליים שעשויים להיות &quot;הקורונה הבאה&quot;, אומר סם סקרפינו, אפידמיולוג באוניברסיטת נורת&#39;איסטרן בבוסטון. הנתונים החדשים עשויים גם לספק הנחיות לבריאות הציבור במהלך התפרצויות של וירוסים עונתיים כמו שפעת, הוא אומר.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> מאז סתיו 2021, תוכנית <a href="https://covid.cdc.gov/covid-data-tracker/#traveler-genomic-surveillance" target="_blank" rel="noopener">המעקב הגנומי מבוסס הנוסעים</a> של ה-CDC עקבה אחר האבולוציה העולמית של SARS-CoV-2, הנגיף שאחראי ל-COVID-19, באמצעות בדיקת PCR רצונית של משטח אף בשדות תעופה בינלאומיים. באוגוסט, התוכנית <a href="https://www.cdc.gov/mmwr/volumes/72/wr/mm7243a3.htm?s_cid=mm7243a3_w" target="_blank" rel="noopener">קלטה את אחד המקרים הידועים הראשונים בכל מקום של גרסה חדשה, BA.2.86</a> , אצל נוסע שחזר מיפן. יותר מ-360,000 מטיילים השתתפו בבדיקה נכון לספטמבר 2023.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> נמלי התעופה המשתתפים בתוכנית המורחבת כוללים את נמל התעופה הבינלאומי של סן פרנסיסקו - <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/san-francisco-plane-waste-covid-19-variant">שהפך לנמל התעופה הראשון בארה&quot;ב לסנן את מי השפכים שלו לאיתור</a> גרסאות נגיף הקורונה באביב הקרוב ( <em>SN: 5/9/23</em> ) - יחד עם נמל התעופה הבינלאומי ג&#39;ון פ. קנדי ​​בניו יורק, נמל התעופה הבינלאומי לוגן בבוסטון ונמל התעופה הבינלאומי דאלס מחוץ לוושינגטון הבירה בדיקות ה-PCR והשפכים &quot;משלימים זה את זה&quot;, אומר סקארפינו, מכיוון שבדיקת ה-PCR מספקת מידע אנונימי על נוסעים בודדים בעוד שבדיקת השפכים מספקת דפוסים רחבים יותר ברמת האוכלוסייה.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> התוכנית המורחבת היא &quot;דרך ממש חכמה&quot; לחפש פתוגנים חדשים המגיעים לארצות הברית באמצעות נסיעות בינלאומיות, אומרת רייצ&#39;ל פורצקי, מיקרוביולוגית מאוניברסיטת אילינוי שיקגו המנהלת תוכניות ניטור שפכים מקומיות. היא הייתה רוצה לראות את ה-CDC מתרחב יותר לשדות תעופה נוספים, כמו גם למוקדי נסיעות אחרים כמו תחנות אוטובוס ורכבת.</p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/110623_bl_cdc_traveler_surveillance_feat-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="445873" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/110623_bl_cdc_traveler_surveillance_feat-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title> הנה כיצד שלדגים צלילה במהירות גבוהה עשויים להימנע מזעזוע מוח</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/how-diving-kingfishers-avoid-concussions<dc:creator><![CDATA[Claudia López Lloreda]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Mon, 06 Nov 2023 14:00:00 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Animals]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3132891 </guid><description><![CDATA[Understanding the genetic adaptations that protect the birds’ brains when they dive for food might one day offer clues to protecting human brains. ]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<p>שינויים גנטיים אצל שלדגים עשויים לעזור לרכך את המכה כאשר הציפורים הצוללות צוללות מקור ראשון למים כדי לתפוס דגים.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> ניתוח של ספר ההוראות הגנטי של כמה מדגי צלילה זיהה <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s42003-023-05359-z" target="_blank" rel="noopener">שינויים בגנים הקשורים לתפקוד המוח כמו גם להתפתחות הרשתית וכלי הדם</a> , שעשויים להגן מפני נזק במהלך צלילות, מדווחים חוקרים ב-24 באוקטובר ב- <em>Communications Biology</em> . התוצאות מצביעות על כך שהמינים השונים של שלדגים צוללים אולי הסתגלו כדי לשרוד את הצלילות שלהם ללא פגע באותן דרכים, אבל עדיין לא ברור כיצד השינויים הגנטיים מגנים על הציפורים.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> צלילות שלדג, כשהן פוגעות במהירויות של עד 40 קילומטרים לשעה, מפעילות כמויות אדירות של לחץ שעלול להזיק על ראשן, מקורן ומוחותיהם של הציפורים. הציפורים צוללות שוב ושוב, מכות את ראשן למים בדרכים שעלולות לגרום לזעזוע מוח בבני אדם, אומרת שאנון האקט, ביולוג אבולוציוני ואוצרת במוזיאון פילד בשיקגו. &quot;אז חייב להיות משהו שמגן עליהם מההשלכות הנוראיות של מכה חוזרת ונשנית בראשם במצע קשה&quot;.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> האקט החלה להתעניין לראשונה כיצד הציפורים מגינות על המוח שלהן בזמן שעבדה עם קבוצת ההוקי של בנה והחלה לדאוג מההשפעה של פגיעות חוזרות ונשנות על המוח האנושי. בערך באותו זמן, הביולוג האבולוציוני צ&#39;אד אליאסון הצטרף למוזיאון כדי לחקור שלדגים והתנהגות הצלילה שלהם.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> במחקר החדש, Hackett, Eliason ועמיתיו ניתחו את הגנום המלא של 30 מיני שלדגים, חלקם צוללים ואחרים לא, מתוך דגימות שהוקפאו ומאוחסנות במוזיאון. הציפורים שהשתמרו הגיעו מכל העולם; חלק ממיני הצלילה הגיעו מאזורי היבשת ואחרים מאיים והתפתחו לצלול באופן עצמאי ולא מאותו אב קדמון צולל. הצוות רצה לדעת אם מיני הצלילה השונים פיתחו שינויים גנטיים דומים כדי להגיע לאותן התנהגויות. מיני שלדגים רבים פיתחו התנהגות זו, אך לא היה ברור אם זה היה דרך התכנסות גנטית, בדומה לכמה מינים של ציפורים איבדו את מעופם או כיצד <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/many-genes-dolphins-and-bats-evolved-same-way-allow-echolocation">עטלפים ודולפינים פיתחו הד באופן עצמאי</a> <em>(SN: 9/6/2013)</em> .</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> מחקרים קודמים מצאו התכנסות על צורת המקור, מה שהופך את שלדגים צוללים ארוכים ומחודדים, מה שיכול לאפשר להם לצלול בצורה יעילה יותר לתוך המים. &quot;האם כולם [מסגלים לצלילה צלילה] באותו אופן עם המקור שלהם, המוח שלהם... ועם הגנים שלהם?&quot; תהה האקט.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The analysis revealed evidence of 93 changed genes that seemed to signal genetic convergence. Of those, one stood out: It was a tweak in a gene that holds the instructions for making the tau protein, which, when functioning normally, helps to stabilize cells&#39; structure and could be a change to help the birds adapt to diving, the team suggests.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> In humans, tau has been implicated in neurodegenerative diseases such as Alzheimer&#39;s disease and shows up in clumps in brain tissue of people who have suffered multiple concussions. “It&#39;s a very interesting hypothesis that the same [tau] protein has been reused to mitigate these hard impacts” in kingfishers, says Tim Sackton, a geneticist at Harvard University who was not involved with the study.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> But, he says, the type of genetic analysis done in the study is tricky. Some of the convergent genes identified might be due to chance and not be related to the evolution of plunge diving behavior. More in-depth studies to identify which genetic changes are relevant to the diving behavior are warranted.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The next steps are to test what these genetic mutations and resulting proteins, particularly tau, do in kingfishers and how the genetic differences in diving species might protect them. If similar studies offer insight into how the birds protect their brains, the results could possibly be applied to developing protective strategies against concussions and brain injury for humans. But that&#39;s in the distant future.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “We have a long way to go between understanding how the genotype and all of its modifications turn into what we see in the natural world,” Hackett says. “We&#39;re just at the beginning of asking those questions.”</p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/110223_cl_kingfishers-dive_feat-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="52168" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/110223_cl_kingfishers-dive_feat-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title> JWST spotted a new speedy jet stream in Jupiter&#39;s atmosphere</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/jwst-jet-stream-jupiter-space<dc:creator><![CDATA[Carolyn Wilke]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Fri, 03 Nov 2023 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Planetary Science]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3132741 </guid><description><![CDATA[Seen in images from the James Webb Space Telescope, the high-altitude feature may help untangle the inner workings of the giant planet’s atmosphere. ]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<p>New beauty shots of Jupiter, captured by the James Webb Space Telescope, reveal a speedy jet stream encircling the equator at an altitude never imaged before.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Researchers have known about Jovian jet streams since Voyager spacecraft flew by in 1979. Those relatively stable winds occur near the planet&#39;s main cloud decks, in the troposphere. The <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41550-023-02099-2" target="_blank" rel="noopener">newly spotted jet</a> lies 20 to 40 kilometers above, in the stratosphere, and moves at about 500 kilometers per hour, or roughly twice as fast as the jets below, astrophysicist Ricardo Hueso and colleagues report October 19 in <em>Nature Astronomy</em> .</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “We were not expecting to find these strange motions in the equatorial atmosphere,” says Hueso, of the University of the Basque Country in Bilbao, Spain. There is no theory that predicts a change in the winds at this altitude on Jupiter, he says.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> It&#39;s not clear yet what causes the speedy jet. “If you have very intense motions, you need energy to produce those motions,” Hueso says. This energy could come from storms below the jet. It may also be linked to happenings higher in the troposphere, where scientists have observed a band where temperature and wind intensity oscillate over four or so years. Similar cycles over the equator also occur on Saturn and Earth.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Earlier observations of Jupiter hadn&#39;t been able to image this part of the stratosphere. Its altitude lies below what ground-based telescopes on Earth glimpse and above what the Hubble Space Telescope captures. But using special infrared filters, JWST was able to peek into this mysterious region.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “Here they have this missing piece of the puzzle for the first time in this latitudinal range around the equator,” says Thibault Cavalié, a planetary scientist at the Laboratoire d&#39;Astrophysique de Bordeaux in France.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The high-resolution images are “stunning,” says Liming Li, a planetary scientist at the University of Houston, also not involved with the study. The researchers used two snapshots of Jupiter taken 10 hours apart. Based on how atmospheric features shifted in that time, the team clocked the stream&#39;s speed. </p><div
	class="container"
	data-component="slideshow"
 style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><div class="controls-wrapper" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"></div><ol class="slides" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><li class="wrapper item-1" role="list-item" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><figure class="figure"><img decoding="async" width="680" height="383" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/102723_cw_Jupiter-jet-stream_main-box_inline.jpg" class="attachment-medium size-medium" alt="A false-color infrared image of Jupiter where brighter objects lie at higher altitudes. Within an area (box) straddling the planet’s equatorial clouds (white band), researchers noticed a few bright features about 20 to 40 kilometers above the clouds." loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="3132744" data-permalink="https://www.sciencenews.org/102723_cw_jupiter-jet-stream_main-box_inline" data-orig-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/102723_cw_Jupiter-jet-stream_main-box_inline.jpg" data-orig-size="680,383" data-comments-opened="0" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="102723_cw_Jupiter-jet-stream_main-box_inline" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="&lt;p>;In this false-color infrared image of Jupiter, brighter objects lie at higher altitudes. Within an area (box) straddling the planet’s equatorial clouds (white band), researchers noticed a few bright features about 20 to 40 kilometers above the clouds.&lt;/p>;
" data-medium-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/102723_cw_Jupiter-jet-stream_main-box_inline.jpg" data-large-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/102723_cw_Jupiter-jet-stream_main-box_inline.jpg" /><figcaption class="gallery-caption"> <span class="caption">In this false-color infrared image of Jupiter, brighter objects lie at higher altitudes. Within an area (box) straddling the planet&#39;s equatorial clouds (white band), researchers noticed a few bright features about 20 to 40 kilometers above the clouds.</span> <span class="credit">NASA, ESA, CSA, STScI, R. Hueso/Univ. of the Basque Country, I. de Pater/UCB, T. Fouchet/Observatory of Paris, L. Fletcher/Univ. of Leicester, M. Wong/UCB, J. DePasquale/STScI</span> </figcaption></figure></li><li class="wrapper item-2" role="list-item" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><figure class="figure"><img decoding="async" width="680" height="383" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/102723_cw_Jupiter-jet-stream_10.52_inline.jpg" class="attachment-medium size-medium" alt="A close up of an area from the previous false-color image of Jupiter. The image is seen in black and white with three bright features outlined in colored boxes seen 10:52 UT." loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="3132742" data-permalink="https://www.sciencenews.org/102723_cw_jupiter-jet-stream_10-52_inline" data-orig-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/102723_cw_Jupiter-jet-stream_10.52_inline.jpg" data-orig-size="680,383" data-comments-opened="0" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="102723_cw_Jupiter-jet-stream_10.52_inline" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="&lt;p>;Zooming in on Jupiter’s equatorial clouds, three bright features (colored boxes) appear in this snippet from a July 2022 JWST image. Tracking those features over time let researchers clock the movement of a newly identified jet stream.&lt;/p>;
" data-medium-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/102723_cw_Jupiter-jet-stream_10.52_inline.jpg" data-large-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/102723_cw_Jupiter-jet-stream_10.52_inline.jpg" /><figcaption class="gallery-caption"> <span class="caption">Zooming in on Jupiter&#39;s equatorial clouds, three bright features (colored boxes) appear in this snippet from a July 2022 JWST image. Tracking those features over time let researchers clock the movement of a newly identified jet stream.</span> <span class="credit">NASA, ESA, CSA, STScI, R. Hueso/Univ. of the Basque Country, I. de Pater/UCB, T. Fouchet/Observatory of Paris, L. Fletcher/Univ. of Leicester, M. Wong/UCB, J. DePasquale/STScI</span> </figcaption></figure></li><li class="wrapper item-3" role="list-item" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><figure class="figure"><img decoding="async" width="680" height="383" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/102723_cw_Jupiter-jet-stream_20.55_inline.jpg" class="attachment-medium size-medium" alt="A close up of an area from the first false-color image of Jupiter. The image is seen in black and white with three bright features outlined in colored boxes seen 20:55 UT." loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="3132743" data-permalink="https://www.sciencenews.org/102723_cw_jupiter-jet-stream_20-55_inline" data-orig-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/102723_cw_Jupiter-jet-stream_20.55_inline.jpg" data-orig-size="680,383" data-comments-opened="0" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="102723_cw_Jupiter-jet-stream_20.55_inline" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="&lt;p>;An image of the same area 10 hours later, after one rotation of the planet, reveals that the bright features have shifted their positions. That movement led scientists to determine that the newly identified jet stream moves at about 500 kilometers per hour.&lt;/p>;
" data-medium-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/102723_cw_Jupiter-jet-stream_20.55_inline.jpg" data-large-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/102723_cw_Jupiter-jet-stream_20.55_inline.jpg" /><figcaption class="gallery-caption"> <span class="caption">An image of the same area 10 hours later, after one rotation of the planet, reveals that the bright features have shifted their positions. That movement led scientists to determine that the newly identified jet stream moves at about 500 kilometers per hour.</span> <span class="credit">NASA, ESA, CSA, STScI, R. Hueso/Univ. of the Basque Country, I. de Pater/UCB, T. Fouchet/Observatory of Paris, L. Fletcher/Univ. of Leicester, M. Wong/UCB, J. DePasquale/STScI</span></figcaption></figure></li></ol></div><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Future observations of this jet and others could help untangle the tricky physics occurring at planets&#39; equators, Hueso says. In swiftly turning planets, such as Earth and Jupiter, Coriolis forces steer atmospheric currents to their right in the northern hemisphere and to their left in the south. But at the equator, where there are no Coriolis forces, different factors are at play. With more investigation, researchers hope to refine the equations used to describe the atmosphere around the equator.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “We understand the physics of other latitudes because it&#39;s the same physics that occurs in the atmosphere of the Earth,” Hueso says. But at the equator, “we don&#39;t understand it on the Earth at the level that we would like, and we don&#39;t understand it on Jupiter.”</p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/102723_cw_Jupiter-jet-stream_planet_feature-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="109625" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/102723_cw_Jupiter-jet-stream_planet_feature-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title> In a Jedi-like feat, rats can move a digital object using just their brain</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/jedi-rats-move-digital-object-using-brain<dc:creator><![CDATA[Laura Sanders]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Thu, 02 Nov 2023 18:11:30 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Neuroscience]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3132875 </guid><description><![CDATA[In a new study, rats could imagine their way through a 3-D virtual world, hinting at how brains can think about places that they’re not physically in. ]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<p>Like tiny, hairy Yodas raising X-wings from a swamp, rats can lift digital cubes and drop them near a target. But these rats aren&#39;t using the Force. Instead, they are using their imagination.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> This <a href="https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.adh5206" target="_blank" rel="noopener">telekinetic trick,</a> described in the Nov. 3 <em>Science</em> , provides hints about how brains imagine new scenarios and remember past ones.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “This is fantastic research,” says Mayank Mehta, a neurophysicist at UCLA. “It opens up a lot of exciting possibilities.” A deeper scientific understanding of the brain area involved in the feat could, for instance, help researchers diagnose and treat memory disorders, he says.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Neuroscientist Albert Lee and his colleagues study how brains can go back in time by revisiting memories and jump ahead to imagine future scenarios. Those processes, sometimes called “mental time travel,” are “part of what makes our inner mental lives quite rich and interesting,” says Lee, who did the new study while at Howard Hughes Medical Institute&#39;s Janelia Research Campus in Ashburn, Va.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> To dip into these complex questions, the researchers began with a simpler one: “Can you be in one place and think about another place?” says Lee, who is now an HHMI investigator at Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center in Boston. “The rat isn&#39;t doing anything fancier than that. We&#39;re not asking them to recall their summer vacation.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Neuroscientist and engineer Chongxi Lai, also now at Beth Israel Deaconess, Lee and colleagues trained rats to move on a spherical treadmill in the midst of a 3-D virtual world projected onto a surrounding screen. While the rats poked around their virtual world, electrodes recorded signals from nerve cells in the rats&#39; hippocampi, brain structures known to hold complex <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/neuroscientists-garner-nobel-discovering-brains-inner-gps">spatial information</a> , among other things ( <em>SN: 10/6/14</em> ). In this way, researchers matched patterns of brain activity with spots in the virtual world.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Next, the researchers wanted to know if the rats could imagine their way through the world. The animals were trained to mentally move a virtual cube to a twisty column, using only brain activity patterns in the hippocampus. If the rodents Jedied the cube correctly, they&#39;d get a reward of water. In this experiment, the virtual reality world was controlled by the rats&#39; brains; the rats&#39; physical movements on the treadmill no longer mattered.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> After some training, the furry apprentices mastered the task, their brain activity showed. By activating the right pattern of cells in their hippocampi, the rats could concentrate and hold the cube near the twisty column for several seconds. In another task, the rats mentally teleported through the virtual world to reach the twisty column. </p><figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="680" height="383" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/110223_ls_jedi-rats_inline.jpg" alt="A representation of a gray and white virtual world with twisty columns, geometric shapes tiling the floor and gear-like decorations toward the back." class="wp-image-3132880" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/110223_ls_jedi-rats_inline.jpg 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/110223_ls_jedi-rats_inline-330x186.jpg 330w" sizes="(max-width: 680px) 100vw, 680px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3132880"><p class="BodyA" style="margin-bottom: 0in;text-align:right;direction:rtl"><span class="NoneA">A view from inside the virtual world that rats saw in a new study shows a tall, twisty column (left). Using only their brains, rats could reliably move a virtual cube to that column, researchers found.</span></p></span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3132880">Chongxi Lai, HHMI Janelia Research Campus</span></figcaption></figure><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The results are “strong evidence that rats can use imagination to perform novel, artificial tasks,” says neuroscientist Daoyun Ji of Baylor College of Medicine in Houston, who wasn&#39;t involved in the new study. And it&#39;s not just rats. “It is likely we humans imagine by activating hippocampal memories too,” he says.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The hippocampus, a seahorse-shaped structure deep on each side of the brain, is very complex, and still quite mysterious, Mehta says. His work and others have shown that cells there are influenced by all sorts of things, beyond abstract spatial locations. “There is clearly a lot to be considered,” Mehta says.<br><br> Electrodes implanted in different parts of the human brain have allowed people to <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/paralyzed-people-implants-brain-computer-interface-tablets">control computers</a> and robotic limbs, for instance ( <em>SN: 11/21/18</em> ). Devices that incorporate neural signals from the hippocampus might one day allow more abstract jobs, Lee says. Compared with rats, he says, “humans can probably control their hippocampus for longer durations with a larger repertoire, and the concepts being encoded in the brain are probably much more complex.”</p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/110223_ls_jedi-rats_feat-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="53093" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/110223_ls_jedi-rats_feat-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title> How neutron imaging uncovers hidden secrets of fossils and artifacts</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/neutron-imaging-uncovers-fossils-artifacts<dc:creator><![CDATA[James R. Riordon]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Thu, 02 Nov 2023 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Physics]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3132612 </guid><description><![CDATA[The technique can complement X-ray scanning and other tools to uncover details of dinosaur fossils, mummies and more. ]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<p>Shattered crocodile. Formally, <em>Confractosuchus</em> . It was discovered in Australia when a bulldozer clearing a boulder broke a stone into pieces. Exposed portions of the broken-up rock made clear that fossils were inside, but there was no immediate sign that this discovery would later reveal an unprecedented snapshot of life from the Cretaceous Period.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Paleontologist Matt White of the University of New England in Armidale, Australia, and colleagues arranged to have the fossil-laden rock scanned with X-ray computed tomography. Like a medical CT scan, the method takes multiple images of an object that can be assembled into a 3-D map of the interior. The team hoped to use the scans as guides to isolate individual bones in the fossil without removing them, then manipulate the 3-D images to virtually put the shattered croc back together.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> But one section of the fossil puzzle gave them trouble. Iron-rich stone surrounding the bones made it difficult to get good X-ray images. So the researchers decided to try another approach.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> They sent the mystery chunk to chemist Joseph Bevitt of the <a href="https://www.ansto.gov.au/facilities/australian-centre-for-neutron-scattering" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Australian Centre for Neutron Scattering</a> in Sydney, who specializes in using subatomic neutron particles to image ancient objects. Along with the expected croc bones, Bevitt discovered one that looked like a dinosaur leg bone. It was in the portion of rock where the crocodile&#39;s stomach cavity would have been.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “When I saw the neutron result and the little dino femur, I was shaking with shock,” Bevitt says, “both in awe and doubt with what we had seen.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Years of analysis plus more X-ray and neutron scanning eventually confirmed that the remains of a previously unknown species of dinosaur, bitten into chunks and scored with tooth marks, were in the croc&#39;s belly. The finding earned the shattered crocodile the second half of its name: <em>sauroktonos</em> , for lizard killer. White, Bevitt and colleagues published their discovery of both the newly identified species of crocodile and <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/crocodile-ancestor-ate-dinosaur-fossil-stomach">the never-before-seen dinosaur inside</a> last year <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1342937X22000338?via%3Dihub" target="_blank" rel="noopener">in <em>Gondwana Research</em></a><em> </em>( <em>SN: 3/26/22, p. 5</em> ). </p><div class="wp-block-columns alignwide is-layout-flex wp-container-3" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><div class="wp-block-column is-layout-flow" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_neutron-imaging-inline-2.jpg" alt="A photo of a pile of rocks on a black background." class="wp-image-3132617" width="422" height="186" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_neutron-imaging-inline-2.jpg 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_neutron-imaging-inline-2-330x146.jpg 330w" sizes="(max-width: 422px) 100vw, 422px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3132617">By scanning these rocks, scientists discovered an ancient crocodile inside that had eaten a dinosaur as its last meal.</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3132617">MA White <em>et al</em> / <em>Gondwana Research</em> 2022</span> </figcaption></figure></div><div class="wp-block-column is-layout-flow" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_neutron-imaging-inline-1.jpg" alt="An image of a 3-D reconstruction of an ancient crocodile that has been x-ray scanned." class="wp-image-3132616" width="427" height="188" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_neutron-imaging-inline-1.jpg 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_neutron-imaging-inline-1-330x146.jpg 330w" sizes="(max-width: 427px) 100vw, 427px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3132616">X-ray scanning revealed the embedded crocodile (3-D digital reconstruction, shown). But it took neutron scanning to discover dinosaur bones (red) in the croc&#39;s belly.</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3132616">MA White <em>et al</em> / <em>Gondwana Research</em> 2022</span></figcaption></figure></div></div><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> It&#39;s a stunning discovery: <em>Confractosuchus sauroktonos</em> , the shattered crocodile lizard killer, and the remains of its last meal, its dinosaur victim, frozen in stone 100 million years ago. It&#39;s a vignette that may never have come to light if not for neutron tomography. Although neutrons have been used for imaging in industrial and military applications since shortly after the <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/century/atom-matter-neutron-nuclear-power-fusion">neutron was discovered in 1932</a> , it&#39;s only in the last few decades that these subatomic particles have begun to provide scientists with unprecedented views inside fossils and antiquities.</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Look, don&#39;t touch</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> There was a time when studying fossils and artifacts often meant damaging or destroying them. Mummified remains were dissected. Sealed containers were cracked open. Fossils were pried loose from rock. In some cases, fossil-containing samples were ground down, layer by layer, to create images of sequential portions in slices that revealed the fossilized structures inside.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Fortunately, X-rays offer nondestructive insights. As a high-energy form of electromagnetic radiation, or light, X-rays interact with the electric and magnetic fields associated with electrically charged particles. In a doctor&#39;s office, when a technician shines a beam of X-rays at a broken leg, the light gets scattered or absorbed by the fields of the electrons around atoms in the leg. The denser a material is, the more electrons are packed in it, and the less effectively X-rays can pass through. That&#39;s why higher-density portions of the body — like bones — stand out in X-ray images more than lower-density portions. Skin, muscle and other soft tissues are essentially invisible because X-rays pass straight through.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> X-rays have provided views into the hidden interiors of artifacts since the radiation was discovered in 1895. But after <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/ct-scan-50-years-anniversary-first-image-medicine-physics">computationally intensive X-ray CT was developed</a> in the 1970s, it became the standard approach to studying objects in paleontology and archaeology ( <em>SN: 12/18/21 &amp; 1/1/22, p. 44</em> ). X-ray CT scanning is now the modern-day alternative to the grinding that 19th century scientists often relied on. Recent examples include scans of <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/microct-xray-ancient-animal-mummies">mummified animals from ancient Egypt</a> ( <em>SN: 9/12/20, p. 17</em> ); newly uncovered inscriptions on the <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/crusty-old-computer-new-imaging-techniques-reveal-construction-ancient-marvel">2,000-year-old Antikythera mechanism</a> , an ancient Greek astronomical calculator used to predict eclipses and other celestial events ( <em>SN: 12/2/06, p. 357</em> ); and a study of the brain cavity in a <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/skull-fossil-suggests-primate-brain-areas-evolved-separately">20-million-year-old monkey skull</a> ( <em>SN: 9/14/19, p. 11</em> ). Many large museums and research institutions have their own X-ray CT scanners on hand that are essentially the same systems that doctors use.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> For all that X-ray imaging has revealed about the past, though, it still has some drawbacks. X-rays can&#39;t penetrate a particularly dense material, like lead or thick layers of other metals, to see an object hidden inside. On the flip side, an object made of low-density material, such as soft tissue, will be invisible to X-rays.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Neutrons can fill in the picture. </p><figure class="wp-block-image "><picture class="sn-responsive-image"><source srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_neutron-imaging-inline-3_desktop.png 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_neutron-imaging-inline-3_desktop-579x383.png 579w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_neutron-imaging-inline-3_desktop-281x186.png 281w" width="680" height="450" media="(min-width: 600px)" sizes="(max-width: 1023px) 100vw, 680px"></source><source srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_neutron-imaging-inline-3_mobile.png 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_neutron-imaging-inline-3_mobile-579x383.png 579w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_neutron-imaging-inline-3_mobile-281x186.png 281w" width="680" height="450"></source><img src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_neutron-imaging-inline-3_mobile.png" class="attachment-large size-large" alt="An illustration showing what materials x-ray and neutron scanning can pass through. X-ray scanning passes through paper, thin layer of wood, aluminum but not lead, iron and other dense materials. Neutrons pass through all of those materials but not water." decoding="async" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_neutron-imaging-inline-3_mobile.png 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_neutron-imaging-inline-3_mobile-579x383.png 579w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_neutron-imaging-inline-3_mobile-281x186.png 281w" sizes="(max-width: 1023px) 100vw, 680px" data-attachment-id="3132619" data-permalink="https://www.sciencenews.org/110423_neutron-imaging-inline-3_mobile" data-orig-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_neutron-imaging-inline-3_mobile.png" data-orig-size="680,450" data-comments-opened="0" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="110423_neutron-imaging-inline-3_mobile" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="&lt;p>;Scientists rely on X-ray and neutron scanning to penetrate materials that hide objects of interest. Differences in how X-rays and neutrons interact with atoms explain why neutrons, unlike X-rays, can pass through lead but get blocked by water.&lt;/p>;
" data-medium-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_neutron-imaging-inline-3_mobile-579x383.png" data-large-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_neutron-imaging-inline-3_mobile.png" /></picture><figcaption> <span class="caption mobile-caption wp-caption-3132619">Scientists rely on X-ray and neutron scanning to penetrate materials that hide objects of interest. Differences in how X-rays and neutrons interact with atoms explain why neutrons, unlike X-rays, can pass through lead but get blocked by water.</span> <span class="credit mobile-credit wp-credit-3132619">T. Tibbitts</span> <span class="caption desktop-caption wp-caption-3132618">Scientists rely on X-ray and neutron scanning to penetrate materials that hide objects of interest. Differences in how X-rays and neutrons interact with atoms explain why neutrons, unlike X-rays, can pass through lead but get blocked by water.</span> <span class="credit desktop-credit wp-credit-3132618">T. Tibbitts</span></figcaption></figure><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The difference is in the scattering</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Neutrons, as their name implies, are neutral. These subatomic particles have no electric charge, so neutron beams don&#39;t notice the electrons in orbit around atoms. Instead, neutrons pass right by electrons and hit nuclei packed with protons and neutrons at the centers of atoms. Incoming neutrons can bounce off an atom&#39;s nucleus or be absorbed into the atom. The interactions are more complicated than with X-rays and depend on how fast the neutrons are moving and on complex quantum mechanical interactions.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Neutrons suitable for tomography are produced with comparatively massive particle accelerators or as by-products from nuclear reactors. The neutrons are relatively slow moving, with energies one-hundred-millionth those of X-rays in CT scanners. These slow neutrons interact strongly with some low-density materials that X-rays pass through blithely, including lithium, boron and hydrogen.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “Water to neutrons is like lead for X-rays,” because of the hydrogen atoms, Bevitt says. Too much hydrogen-rich material can hide details from neutron beams. But in the same way that a metal hip joint stands out in a medical X-ray, hydrogen can also make some features visible in neutron images. Lead, iron and copper, on the other hand, are essentially transparent to low-energy neutrons. </p><figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="680" height="329" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_neutron-imaging-inline-4.jpg" alt="Two photos side by side. On the left is an overhead view of two lilies in a lead cask while the photo on the right is a side view showing the two lilies after neutron imaging." class="wp-image-3132620" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_neutron-imaging-inline-4.jpg 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_neutron-imaging-inline-4-330x160.jpg 330w" sizes="(max-width: 680px) 100vw, 680px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3132620">Lilies in a lead cask demonstrate the abilities of neutron imaging. Neutrons can sail through the lead, which would stop X-rays, to reveal the flowers within, including water in the vascular structure (right).</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3132620">Daniel Hussey/NIST</span></figcaption></figure><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Physicist Jacob LaManna of the National Institute of Standards and Technology in Gaithersburg, Md., likes to demonstrate the comparative capabilities of neutron and X-ray imaging with a CT “still life” of Asiatic lilies tucked inside a hollow cask with thick lead walls. “The neutrons can go right through the lead, and then you can see basically all the water [in the] vascular structure of the flowers,” LaManna says. An X-ray scan would show nothing but the opaque outer surface of the cask.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The ability to glide through dense materials that block X-rays has made neutron imaging an important technology for industrial testing of automobiles and planes. The particles can reveal the flow of hydrogen-rich oil inside engine blocks or expose flaws in metal castings. Since the 1970s, US national laboratories have relied on neutron imaging to develop and maintain the nation&#39;s nuclear weapons stockpiles; the neutrons are powerful quality-control tools for mapping out the insides of dense bomb parts and for studying hydrogen-rich fusion explosives inside warhead components.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> At NIST, LaManna leads the <a href="https://www.nist.gov/programs-projects/imaging-advanced-neutron-imaging-facility" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Neutron and X-ray Tomography, or NeXT, facility</a> , which can simultaneously run X-ray and neutron imaging. The dual views provide distinct yet complementary information about things that contain combinations of materials — like hydrogen fuel cells, building materials and soil samples — that would be difficult to study with only one or the other imaging approach.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Over the last couple decades, as word has spread about the capabilities, a growing number of paleontologists, archaeologists and anthropologists have added neutron imaging to their analytical toolboxes. Despite neutron imaging being around for a while, “we are really the new kids on the block,” Bevitt says.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> In addition to revealing multiple dinosaur bones in the belly of a shattered crocodile, along with the femur that initially caught Bevitt&#39;s eye, neutron computed tomography has allowed researchers to study <a href="https://www.mrforum.com/wp-content/uploads/open_access/9781644900574/39.pdf?" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the fabric swaddling cat mummies</a> without unwrapping them, find signs of recently applied glues holding together fraudulently assembled artifacts, and uncover <a href="https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.abf3289" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the most ancient vertebrate heart ever found</a> , in a 380-million-year-old fish. </p><figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="642" height="450" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_neutron-imaging-inline-7-642x450.png" alt="An image showing the different kinds of scans taken of a mummified cat from ancient Egypt. The image on the left is a photo of the cat, the scan in the middle was taken by x-ray and the scan on the left was taken with neutron imaging. There is an inset showing details of the cloth wrappings." class="wp-image-3132623" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_neutron-imaging-inline-7-642x450.png 642w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_neutron-imaging-inline-7-546x383.png 546w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_neutron-imaging-inline-7-265x186.png 265w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_neutron-imaging-inline-7.png 680w" sizes="(max-width: 642px) 100vw, 642px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3132623">Together, X-ray and neutron scanning provided an inside view of this mummified cat from ancient Egypt, with no unwrapping required. X-rays (center) revealed the cat&#39;s skeleton while neutrons (right) showed details of the cloth wrappings, including layers of varying tightness and coarseness (inset).</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3132623">CA Raymond and JJ Bevitt/ <em>MATERIALS RESEARCH PROCEEDINGS</em> 2020 ( <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">CC by 3.0</a> )</span></figcaption></figure><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Rewards and risks</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Paleontologist James Clark places a pair of fossilized crocodile skulls on the table in his basement lab at George Washington University in Washington, DC The 165-million-year-old fossils are dwarfed by a nearby modern alligator skull. While the alligator skull is about as long as my forearm, the fossilized croc skulls are only slightly bigger than my thumb tip.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The fragile skulls, which Clark collected in Mexico four decades ago, are embedded in hardened blobs of sediment with just a few bones and teeth peeking through. At first glance, the specimens resemble wads of chewed gum, but made of gritty, iron-rich mudstone. “If you try to X-ray that, you basically end up with … these bright sparkles from all the iron,” Clark says. The result is blurring and streaking that hide the skeletal structures.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Clark could have hired preparers to clean away the sediment surrounding the delicate bones. But it&#39;s a slow and expensive process that can end up damaging the specimen, he says.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> It wasn&#39;t until 2019 that he finally got a good look at the hidden bones. After a seminar where he met Bevitt, Clark realized that neutron scanning could be the answer. The event led to an introduction to LaManna and the NIST facility 25 kilometers up the road in Maryland. </p><div class="wp-block-columns alignwide is-layout-flex wp-container-6" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><div class="wp-block-column is-layout-flow" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="680" height="400" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_neutron-imaging-inline-5.png" alt="A photo of an ancient crocodile skull embedded in iron-rich mudstone." class="wp-image-3132621" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_neutron-imaging-inline-5.png 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_neutron-imaging-inline-5-651x383.png 651w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_neutron-imaging-inline-5-316x186.png 316w" sizes="(max-width: 680px) 100vw, 680px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3132621">To see the bones of an ancient crocodile embedded in iron-rich mudstone, researchers turned to neutron scanning.</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3132621">J. STIEGLER</span> </figcaption></figure></div><div class="wp-block-column is-layout-flow" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="680" height="400" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_neutron-imaging-inline-6.png" alt="An image of a 3-D view of the crocodile skull incased in mudstone." class="wp-image-3132622" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_neutron-imaging-inline-6.png 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_neutron-imaging-inline-6-651x383.png 651w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_neutron-imaging-inline-6-316x186.png 316w" sizes="(max-width: 680px) 100vw, 680px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3132622">Neutron imaging allowed for a 3-D view of the croc skull without damaging the specimen</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3132622">J. Stiegler</span></figcaption></figure></div></div><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Because iron is essentially transparent to neutrons, LaManna says, “it&#39;s much easier to basically isolate just the fossil portion of the object.” Images from the NIST neutron CT scans revealed the intricate details of the tiny bones. “You can then start playing digital jigsaw puzzles with the bone fragments to try to reconstruct the particular creature.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> While the material around a fossil or object may present a problem for X-rays, sometimes it&#39;s the object itself that&#39;s the issue. Tissues, fibers, wood and other low-density materials can be difficult to resolve with X-rays, and metals within an object can block other features from view. Both challenges plague researchers studying antiquities like the 3,000-year-old dagger-axes that I saw on display in the Smithsonian&#39;s Freer Gallery of Art in Washington, DC</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> These ceremonial weapons from China&#39;s Shang dynasty are suspended in a vertical glass case, where I could get my nose just a few centimeters from the jade blades and turquoise-encrusted bronze handles. I found it was best to lean up close so that I could appreciate the intricate blue-green patterns of gemstones sunk into the metal. </p><figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="680" height="258" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_neutron-imaging-inline-8.jpg" alt="A photo of a 3,000-year-old dagger axe from China's Shang dynasty." class="wp-image-3132624" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_neutron-imaging-inline-8.jpg 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_neutron-imaging-inline-8-330x125.jpg 330w" sizes="(max-width: 680px) 100vw, 680px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3132624">Researchers at the Smithsonian&#39;s Freer Gallery of Art want to know how 3,000-year-old dagger-axes (one shown) from China&#39;s Shang dynasty were made. Neutron imaging could help reveal the artifact&#39;s hidden interior.</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3132624">Freer Gallery of Art</span></figcaption></figure><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Smithsonian art conservator Ariel O&#39;Connor would love to know how the dagger-axes were put together. X-ray CT doesn&#39;t work on the combination of stone, metal, fibers and other materials that may be within. Neutron imaging could help, but it comes with a risk. Neutron beams make things radioactive. It&#39;s not always clear in advance how radioactive a sample will become, but materials often exceed the level of radioactivity that&#39;s safe for humans to handle, or even view in a museum, for days to weeks after exposure to neutron beams.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “We could actually do calculations and determine what&#39;s going to be the problematic element and how long would it be radioactive and how much,” LaManna says. “[But,] in the case of the jade, where it&#39;s material basically just completely dug up from the ground, it can have all sorts of stuff in it that you might not necessarily expect.” That makes residual radioactivity difficult to predict.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> So, O&#39;Connor decided to do a test. She and colleagues made a crude replica of an ancient dagger-ax. They used jade from Wyoming in lieu of the ancient Chinese jade, stacks of brass from a repurposed door kickplate to simulate the bronze handle, and some silk thread similar to the type that holds some Shang dynasty dagger-axes together. Then <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S2352409X18301482" target="_blank" rel="noopener">LaManna scanned the dagger with X-rays and neutrons</a> at NIST.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> As expected, the brass was entirely opaque to the X-rays, hiding features of the replica&#39;s construction. But the neutron beam revealed key details, including a view of the jade inserted inside the brass handle and even individual silk threads.</p><div class="wp-block-sciencenews-content-sidebar alignleft" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Hidden no more </h4><figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="680" height="300" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_neutron-imaging-inline-9.png" alt="A x-ray image of a replica dagger-axe made from jade, stacks of brass plates and silk thread. A yellow outline surrounds a dark box of the replica that was neutron imaged." class="wp-image-3132625" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_neutron-imaging-inline-9.png 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_neutron-imaging-inline-9-330x146.png 330w" sizes="(max-width: 680px) 100vw, 680px" /><figcaption> <span class="credit wp-credit-3132625">R. Livingston <em>et al</em> / <em>Journal of Archaeological Science: Reports</em> 2018</span></figcaption></figure><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> To test how neutron imaging might work on a dagger-axe, researchers made a replica from jade, stacks of brass plates and silk thread. In an X-ray of the replica (above), the shaft is obscured by brass, so the team used neutron scanning to image the portion outlined in yellow. That imaging (below) revealed details not visible in the X-ray scans. </p><figure class="wp-block-image "><picture class="sn-responsive-image"><source srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_neutron-imaging-inline-10_desktop-532x450.jpg 532w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_neutron-imaging-inline-10_desktop-453x383.jpg 453w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_neutron-imaging-inline-10_desktop-220x186.jpg 220w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_neutron-imaging-inline-10_desktop.jpg 680w" width="532" height="450" media="(min-width: 600px)" sizes="(max-width: 1023px) 100vw, 680px"></source><source srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_neutron-imaging-inline-10_mobile-532x450.jpg 532w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_neutron-imaging-inline-10_mobile-453x383.jpg 453w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_neutron-imaging-inline-10_mobile-220x186.jpg 220w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_neutron-imaging-inline-10_mobile.jpg 680w" width="532" height="450"></source><img src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_neutron-imaging-inline-10_mobile-532x450.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large" alt="An image of the replica dagger-axe using neutron imaging. The image is in shades of gray with materials labeled." decoding="async" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_neutron-imaging-inline-10_mobile-532x450.jpg 532w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_neutron-imaging-inline-10_mobile-453x383.jpg 453w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_neutron-imaging-inline-10_mobile-220x186.jpg 220w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_neutron-imaging-inline-10_mobile.jpg 680w" sizes="(max-width: 1023px) 100vw, 680px" data-attachment-id="3132627" data-permalink="https://www.sciencenews.org/110423_neutron-imaging-inline-10_mobile" data-orig-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_neutron-imaging-inline-10_mobile.jpg" data-orig-size="680,575" data-comments-opened="0" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="110423_neutron-imaging-inline-10_mobile" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_neutron-imaging-inline-10_mobile-453x383.jpg" data-large-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_neutron-imaging-inline-10_mobile-532x450.jpg" /></picture><figcaption> <span class="credit mobile-credit wp-credit-3132627">R. Livingston <em>et al</em> / <em>Journal of Archaeological Science: Reports</em> 2018</span> <span class="credit desktop-credit wp-credit-3132626">R. Livingston <em>et al</em> / <em>Journal of Archaeological Science: Reports</em> 2018</span></figcaption></figure></div><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> As for residual radioactivity, the replica showed none of any significance nine days later. In general, Bevitt says, residual radiation dies down quickly. One fossil he studied remained radioactive for three months, due to the presence of radium, but most samples are safe to send back to labs and museums within a few weeks or less.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Still, with that uncertainty and questions about how chemically similar the replica is to the real dagger-axes, O&#39;Connor is not yet ready to risk scanning the artifacts.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “As a conservator, I am entrusted with the preservation and safety of these remarkable 3,000-year-old objects to ensure they remain for future generations. If an analytical technique such as neutron imaging might answer our research questions but would alter the objects and prevent them from being accessible” due to induced radioactivity, O&#39;Connor says, “we will look for other options.”</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Opening a new window to the past</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Despite the increasing popularity of neutron tomography for studying fossils and antiquities, X-ray CT remains the go-to imaging choice for most researchers. In the 1990s, a few dozen scholarly papers on using neutrons to study the past were published annually; recently, it&#39;s been hundreds per year. Publications related to imaging fossils and artifacts with X-ray CT, though, number in the thousands every year.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Most of the time, X-rays suffice, and the advantages are clear. They offer high resolution to uncover small details with no lingering radioactivity. X-ray CT machines are also widely available because they&#39;ve been used in medical settings for over 50 years, and they&#39;re small enough to fit in most labs and museum research spaces.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> At the moment, there are <a href="https://nucleus.iaea.org/sites/accelerators/Pages/Interactive-Map-of-NB-Instruments.aspx" target="_blank" rel="noopener">only a few dozen neutron tomography facilities on the planet</a> . The particle accelerators and nuclear reactors that produce suitable neutrons are large, expensive and heavily regulated. Only a handful of the facilities worldwide are available to analyze fossils and antiquities, according to Burkhard Schillinger, a physicist at the Technical University Munich who runs the neutron imaging beamline there. He ticks off a few facilities in the United States, a half dozen in Europe and one in Australia.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Still, LaManna says the lack of access doesn&#39;t seem to be the bottleneck in widespread adoption of the technique. Along with the concerns over lingering radioactivity, the novelty of the technology and general lack of awareness may stand in the way.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “I try to recruit as broad a range of users as I can” to submit fossils and antiquities for imaging at NIST, LaManna says. “It&#39;s not like they&#39;re getting pushed out of the way” to make space for more conventional neutron studies. “It&#39;s just more of getting the correct people interested to then write proposals, come to us [and] work with us to get beam time.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> In the last decade, Australia-based Bevitt has spread the word on neutron tomography through lectures and outreach around the world. Most of the experts contacted for this story trace their initial interest in neutron imaging to Bevitt&#39;s influence. Many researchers in his home country have already embraced the technology.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “Basically, in Australia, when a new dinosaur is discovered,” Bevitt says, “the first thing that happens is it comes to our lab.”</p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_neutron_feat-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="951140" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/110423_neutron_feat-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title> Rock from the impact that formed the moon may linger in Earth&#39;s mantle</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/impact-formed-moon-earth-mantle<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sid Perkins]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Wed, 01 Nov 2023 16:42:04 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3132833 </guid><description><![CDATA[When the young Earth and a Mars-sized body collided 4.5 billion years ago, it left behind dense mantle rock that survives to today, a study finds. ]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<p>About 4.5 billion years ago, a Mars-sized object smashed into the young Earth, spraying debris that coalesced to form the moon, many scientists think. Some remnants of <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-023-06589-1" target="_blank" rel="noopener">that object, called Theia, exist today</a> as large amounts of dense material sitting atop Earth&#39;s core, researchers propose November 1 in <em>Nature</em> .</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> In recent years, geophysicists have discovered continent-sized zones of rock at the base of Earth&#39;s mantle where seismic waves travel abnormally slowly, suggesting the rock there is denser than the rest of the mantle rock. One of these blobs, known as large low-velocity provinces, lies beneath Africa. The other lies half a world away beneath the Pacific Ocean, says Qian Yuan, a planetary geodynamicist at Caltech.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Some researchers have suggested these masses are the remnants of tectonic plates that were shoved beneath others and then sunk down to the boundary between Earth&#39;s outer core and the overlying mantle. But Yuan and his colleagues offer a different origin story.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The moon is only about 2 percent the mass of Earth, which leaves a substantial amount of Theia unaccounted for. So, using supercomputer simulations, the researchers tracked the fallout from a smashup between the nascent Earth and another object about 10 percent as massive.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> In the simulations, each body before the collision had a dense iron core swaddled by a mantle of lighter rocks. Each object was digitally subdivided into particles about 10 kilometers across, so that the postimpact fragments could be tracked, says study coauthor Vincent Eke, a computational physicist at Durham University in England. In all, the team&#39;s simulations tracked about 100 million particles, he notes.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The simulations suggest that a large part of Theia&#39;s core — equivalent to about 3 percent of Earth&#39;s mass today — was left on our planet. Soon after the collision, that dense molten material would have sunk to join Earth&#39;s core. Meanwhile, a large volume of Theia&#39;s mantle, up to 5 percent of Earth&#39;s mass, was embedded in the uppermost 1,400 kilometers or so of Earth&#39;s mantle, the study finds. </p><figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="680" height="835" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/103123_sp_moon-forming_collision-inline.jpg" alt="An illustration of a Mars-size protoplanet smashing into Earth (on the left) with a cut out of Earth's core seen on the right while the Moon orbits." class="wp-image-3132835" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/103123_sp_moon-forming_collision-inline.jpg 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/103123_sp_moon-forming_collision-inline-312x383.jpg 312w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/103123_sp_moon-forming_collision-inline-366x450.jpg 366w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/103123_sp_moon-forming_collision-inline-151x186.jpg 151w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/103123_sp_moon-forming_collision-inline-472x580.jpg 472w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/103123_sp_moon-forming_collision-inline-632x776.jpg 632w" sizes="(max-width: 680px) 100vw, 680px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3132835">Almost 4.5 billion years ago, a Mars-size protoplanet smashed into Earth (left panel in this illustration). That collision, scientists think, ultimately created the moon (gray orb, right panel), and may have left behind continent-sized masses of dense rock atop Earth&#39;s core (red lumps, right).</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3132835">Hernán Cañellas</span></figcaption></figure><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Moon rocks suggest that Theia&#39;s mantle contained higher proportions of iron oxide minerals. That means it was probably a few percent denser than Earth&#39;s mantle, Yuan says. Over the few tens of millions of years that followed the collision, that denser-than-average material slowly sank to accumulate and form the large low-velocity provinces, the researchers suggest.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Although many researchers have suggested that these low-velocity provinces are the remnants of tectonic plates, others have proposed that they&#39;re high-density remnants of Earth&#39;s original magma ocean that sank to the lowermost levels of Earth&#39;s mantle. Attributing them to material left in the wake of the collision between Theia and the nascent Earth “is a new idea, I think,” says Paul Tackley, a geodynamicist at ETH Zurich who was not part of the new study.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Whether or not a run-in with Theia is what created the low-velocity provinces, it&#39;s at least plausible that they&#39;ve lasted the nearly 4.5 billion years since the moon&#39;s formation, Tackley says. If the materials in those zones are dense enough to resist mixing with the overlying mantle as it slowly flows across them, he says, “they can survive over geological time.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Known as the “giant impact hypothesis,” a collision between Earth and a protoplanet remains the leading theory of how the moon formed. Previously, researchers have suggested that <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/moons-origins-revealed-rocks-chemistry">such a collision</a> would help explain the slight chemical differences between moon rocks and Earth&#39;s ( <em>SN: 6/5/14</em> ). And scientists recently proposed that a collision between the nascent Earth and Theia, besides creating our planet&#39;s moon, also <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/moon-planet-collision-earth-plate-tectonics">may have jump-started plate tectonics</a> ( <em>SN: 3/15/23</em> ).</p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/103123_sp_moon-forming_collision_feat-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="1142782" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/103123_sp_moon-forming_collision_feat-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title> Faking death lets some female frogs slip the mating grip of a male</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/faking-death-female-frogs-mate-male<dc:creator><![CDATA[Susan Milius]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Wed, 01 Nov 2023 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Life]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3132699 </guid><description><![CDATA[Suddenly looking dead, grunting like a guy or vigorously rotating can help female frogs survive mating balls in species with aggressively grabby males. ]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<p>Grab fast and hang on for hours. A fierce grip is all the courtship finesse a male frog needs in species that reproduce in frenzied mobs.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Female European common frogs, however, have<a href="https://royalsocietypublishing.org/doi/10.1098/rsos.230742" target="_blank" rel="noopener">at least three moves that give them a chance</a> of escaping overbearing male grasps, say evolutionary behavioral ecologist Carolin Dittrich and curator of herpetology Mark-Oliver Rödel of the Berlin Natural History Museum. The pair describe those tactics October 11 in <em>Royal Society Open Science</em> .</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> With hundreds of Europe&#39;s <em>Rana temporaria</em> frogs gathering at a natural pool, “it can look quite like a mess,” says Dittrich, now at the University of Veterinary Medicine Vienna. And dangerous. Females can drown.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Two, three or more males can clamp onto the same female, creating a tight tangle of frogs called a mating ball. Frogs don&#39;t do internal fertilization, so males hold tight and squirm for a good position for releasing sperm onto eggs put into the water by females. Males of this species typically hold their collective grip on a female for several hours, Dittrich says, but “we know from the literature it can last up to two days.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Dittrich started wondering about female defenses during an “Oh no!” moment when reviewing video she had captured of European common frogs mating in a lab setup. She had wanted to see if the males show any size preference in the females they target. (Sizewise “not choosy at all,” she reports now. “They grab what they can.”) In the mating videos, however, Dittrich noticed something more interesting.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> During filming, she had left the room so her presence wouldn&#39;t somehow disturb the frogs. Afterward, working her way through analyzing all the videos, she was startled. “There can&#39;t be a dead female in this box!” Dittrich remembers thinking. Surely, she would have noticed.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The male in that video had clasped a large female, clearly alive, who then apparently died in his embrace. Her legs stretched out in dead-frog abandon. He let go and pursued the other female in the box. After about two minutes, however, the “dead” female revived and started moving again. Dittrich now proposes that looking dead — or the term she prefers, “tonic immobility” — could let a female escape a male&#39;s grasp. </p><figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><iframe loading="lazy" title="Watch a female frog play dead and ward off a male mate | חדשות המדע" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/-PxqgVfSO_E?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe></div><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> As seen in this lab tub setup, suddenly looking dead can free a female frog from a male&#39;s intense embrace in the just-grab-her mass mating frenzies among European common frogs ( <em>Rana temporaria</em> ).</figcaption></figure><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Intentionally playing dead would be hard to prove, and even to observe, in frogs&#39; competitive scrambles, says wildlife ecologist Brandon Güell of Florida International University in Miami. When female frogs go limp, “sometimes that&#39;s the first step of drowning and dying because they&#39;re probably exhausted — or they&#39;re playing dead.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> A limp female eventually reviving could be easily overlooked in the chaos, he says. He may have caught a glimpse in his own field work in Costa Rica. In a wild mating scramble of Central American milk frogs ( <em>Trachycephalus</em> “ <em>vermiculatus</em> ”), a female just <a href="https://journals.ku.edu/reptilesandamphibians/article/view/18452/17486" target="_blank" rel="noopener">stopped moving while still alive</a> , he and a colleague reported earlier this year in <em>Reptiles &amp; Amphibians</em> .</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> In Dittrich&#39;s videos of her lab test, she saw 54 occasions of a male grabbing a female, but 25 times his grip was broken. Going limp was not the only move that looked to Dittrich like female resistance. Females often combined several of moves in what look like struggles to escape.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The most common possible resistance to a male&#39;s grab was what Dittrich calls rotation. Females clutched by a male in the study started rotating around the long axis of their body, depending on the angle, somewhere between a log roll and a frog ballerina twirl. Males would move their legs to counteract the spin but on occasion lost their grip.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Females also grunted, in what could sound like a male&#39;s “release call,” Dittrich says. The term comes from males making the noise when, in mating chaos, a guy finds himself mistakenly embraced by another male. He grunts and often gets released. Females in Dittrich&#39;s test on occasion grunted while in mating balls, perhaps a form of male impersonation.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Güell also has heard females make guylike sounds when grabbed. They were Costa Rica&#39;s gliding tree frogs ( <em>Agalychnis spurrelli</em> ), tiny and green with orange flanks and big red eyes. They gather by the hundreds or thousands in trees above pools of water, but drowning isn&#39;t the big peril. Males struggling for position can cause the whole writhing tangle to tumble into the pool below, where hungry “caimans are just sitting there and waiting,” he says. </p><div class="wp-block-image  has-alignleft" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><figure class="alignleft size-full" data-component="lightbox"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="680" height="810" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/102623_SM_lady-frog_inline.jpg.jpg" alt="A photo of a ball of mating frogs dangles from foliage above a pond in Costa Rica." class="wp-image-3132700" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/102623_SM_lady-frog_inline.jpg.jpg 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/102623_SM_lady-frog_inline.jpg-322x383.jpg 322w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/102623_SM_lady-frog_inline.jpg-378x450.jpg 378w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/102623_SM_lady-frog_inline.jpg-156x186.jpg 156w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/102623_SM_lady-frog_inline.jpg-487x580.jpg 487w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/102623_SM_lady-frog_inline.jpg-651x776.jpg 651w" sizes="(max-width: 680px) 100vw, 680px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3132700">A ball of mating frogs dangles from foliage above a pond in Costa Rica. These gliding tree frogs mate in frantic gatherings of males grabbing a female as more males pile on and struggle for position. Predators wait below for frog clusters that lose their grip. (Click to enlarge the image)</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3132700">Brandon A. Güell</span></figcaption></figure></div><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The female&#39;s “Let go!” could turn out to be common among frogs that mate in grabfests, Güell says. Dogma had been that only male frogs did much vocal communication, but he has seen that attitude change in recent years after discoveries of species with female calling. “I do think that it is not commonly described; it&#39;s not commonly heard; it&#39;s not commonly recorded … and published,” he says.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Dittrich notes that female resistance of any kind has not gotten much mention in the modern literature on her frogs. She found one 20th century paper, but otherwise had to go back to the 18th century for discussion of female resistance to male power among European common frogs.</p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/102623_sm_lady-frog-survival-tricks_feature-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="334546" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/102623_sm_lady-frog-survival-tricks_feature-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title> On some Australian islands, sea level rise may be helping mangroves thrive</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/australia-island-sea-level-rise-mangroves-thrive<dc:creator><![CDATA[Darren Incorvaia]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Wed, 01 Nov 2023 00:01:00 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Plants]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3132822 </guid><description><![CDATA[Rising seas usually spell trouble for mangroves. But the first survey of the Howick Islands in 50 years finds that mangroves there have expanded a lot.]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<p>Some mangrove forests off Australia have flourished in the last several decades, a new study reports. And, counterintuitively, rising sea levels may be responsible.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Off Australia&#39;s northern coast, the skeletal remains of ancient coral reefs form the bedrock of numerous wooded islands. These low-lying tropical oases are home to diverse animals and plants, including mangrove forests that pepper their coasts and serve as vital habitat and carbon storers. A recent survey of one cluster of those islands — the first in 50 years — shows that swelling seas might have led <a href="https://royalsocietypublishing.org/doi/10.1098/rspb.2023.1183" target="_blank" rel="noopener">to a massive mangrove expansion</a> , researchers report November 1 in <em>Proceedings of the Royal Society B</em> .</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> In other parts of the world, rising seas <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/sea-level-rise-mangrove-forests">have put mangroves at risk</a> ( <em>SN: 6/4/20</em> ). But at the Howick Islands in the Great Barrier Reef, the story is different because of its unique geologic history.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “We usually are focusing on areas of mangrove loss,” says Temilola Fatoyinbo, a forest ecologist at NASA&#39;s Goddard Space Flight Center in Greenbelt, Md., who was not involved with the study. “So it&#39;s always encouraging to see areas where there&#39;s mangrove gain.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Mangroves — groupings of different plants that have <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/kenya-mangrove-trees-forest-carbon-storage-climate">adapted to thrive along coastlines</a> — <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/climate-change-natural-carbon-stores-new-map">soak up carbon dioxide</a> and store it as “blue carbon,” a term for carbon that is sequestered in marine environments ( <em>SN: 9/14/22</em> ; <em>SN: 11/18/21</em> ).</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “There&#39;s a lot of interest in using mangrove blue carbon to mitigate climate change,” says Kerrylee Rogers, an environmental scientist at the University of Wollongong in Australia. “But there remains a lot of questions around their capacity to adapt to sea level rise.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> In 2021, a team led by Wollongong environmental scientist Sarah Hamylton visited the Howick Islands to see how the mangroves there are coping with sea level rise. Hamylton flew a drone over the mangroves to capture aerial imagery, while others walked through the brine to assess the plant diversity and measure individual trees. Using the measured widths and heights of several mangroves, the team extrapolated tree widths for the rest of the forest from the drone&#39;s height data to estimate the total mangrove biomass.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The islands host nearly 54,000 metric tons of mangroves, the team estimates, which is roughly 10,000 more metric tons than was there in 1973. The forest&#39;s reach has also expanded on many islands. While about 25 hectares of every 100 on Newton Island were covered by mangroves in 1973, for example, the forest now blankets close to 40 hectares out of 100. </p><figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="675" height="450" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/103123_di_mangroves_inline-675x450.jpg" alt="A photo of several mangroves growing in the foreground while white ships are visible in the background." class="wp-image-3132821" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/103123_di_mangroves_inline-675x450.jpg 675w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/103123_di_mangroves_inline-575x383.jpg 575w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/103123_di_mangroves_inline-279x186.jpg 279w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/103123_di_mangroves_inline.jpg 680w" sizes="(max-width: 675px) 100vw, 675px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3132821">Mangrove cover on Bewick Island (pictured) has grown by 50 percent since 1973. Researchers attribute this expansion to rising sea levels, which opens new habitat for the coast-loving plants.</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3132821">Oxana Repina</span></figcaption></figure><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The Howick Islands are uniquely suited to supporting mangroves as the ocean rises. At the end of the Last Glacial Maximum, around 12,000 years ago, water levels rose around northern Australia, and coral reefs grew upward to fill the space that had opened for them. When sea levels fell thousands of years later, the exposed reefs eroded into sediment. With <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/jacky-austermann-climate-sn-10-scientists-to-watch">sea levels now rising again</a> , the researchers suspect the mixture of saltwater and sediment makes a perfect home for the salt-tolerant mangroves ( <em>SN: 9/29/22</em> ).</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “As sea level came back down, it wasn&#39;t suitable mangrove habitat,” Rogers says. With those parts of the island now submerged, “it now is suitable again, and it&#39;s largely because it was set up for those conditions [2,000] to 4,000 years ago.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The new findings highlight the need for mangrove research on a local scale, Rogers says. “In a global model, this would get lost.” Fatoyinbo agrees. “Studies on the local scale are really useful,” she says, “to better understand big patterns.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Rogers and Hamylton are now working on a bigger effort to study mangroves around Australia. “If we&#39;re going to invest in mangroves … to provide us blue carbon and to protect shorelines, we need to understand how dynamic they are,” Rogers says. “And then get some more understanding of how they&#39;re going to adapt to sea level in the future.”</p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/103123_di_mangroves_feat-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="348758" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/103123_di_mangroves_feat-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title> Newfound fossil species of lamprey were flesh eaters</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/new-fossil-species-lamprey-flesh-eaters<dc:creator><![CDATA[Carolyn Gramling]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Tue, 31 Oct 2023 16:00:00 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Paleontology]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3132796 </guid><description><![CDATA[In China, paleontologists have unearthed fossils of two surprisingly large lamprey species from the Jurassic Period.]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<p>Found in roughly 160-million-year-old rocks in North China, the Yanliao Biota is a diverse array of beautifully preserved fossils, including dinosaurs, pterosaurs and even early mammals. But it isn&#39;t all fur and feathers. Paleontologists have now unearthed fossils of two surprisingly large ancient lamprey species, swimming menaces that latched onto and bored holes into their unsuspecting neighbors.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Modern parasitic lampreys&#39; funnel-shaped, toothy mouths tend to be adapted to consume blood or flesh. Based on the arrangement of teeth and other feeding apparatuses in the fossils, the <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-023-42251-0" target="_blank" rel="noopener">newly discovered species probably weren&#39;t bloodsuckers — they were flesh eaters</a> , the team reports October 31 in <em>Nature Communications</em> .</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The fossils are the oldest lamprey specimens to clearly indicate a preference in feeding mode, say paleontologist Feixang Wu of the Chinese Academy of Sciences in Beijing and colleagues. In fact, the tooth arrangement of both ancient species strongly resembles that of a modern species of Southern Hemisphere flesh-eating lamprey.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <em>Yanliaomyzon occisor</em> — “occisor” is Latin for “killer” — was the bigger of the two, about 64 centimeters long, the length of a small dog. The species name for its smaller cousin, <em>Y. ingensdentes</em> , comes from the Latin for “large teeth.” Modern adult lampreys range in length from about 15 to 120 centimeters. </p><figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="680" height="383" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/103023_cg_giant_lamprey_inline.jpg" alt="An artists rendition of Yanliaomyzon ingensdentes on the left and Yanliaomyzon occisor on the right in black and white." class="wp-image-3132798" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/103023_cg_giant_lamprey_inline.jpg 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/103023_cg_giant_lamprey_inline-330x186.jpg 330w" sizes="(max-width: 680px) 100vw, 680px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3132798">These reconstructions depict the mouth and part of the body of two newly discovered lamprey species that lived 160 million years ago: <em>Yanliaomyzon ingensdentes</em> (left) and <em>Y. occisor</em> (right).</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3132798">Heming Zhang</span></figcaption></figure><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Lampreys, a lineage of jawless vertebrates, have been around for 360 million years. But they rarely fossilize well, leaving large gaps in their evolutionary record and uncertainty about their ecology and when their feeding styles evolved.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The earliest lampreys weren&#39;t such fierce predators: They were only a few centimeters long and lacked the powerful teeth of later species. They also didn&#39;t have modern lampreys&#39; distinct life cycle, which consists of a larval filter-feeding stage, a juvenile parasitic stage and an adult spawning stage.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The newfound fossils suggest that by this time in the Jurassic Period, lampreys had become fierce predators, acquiring larger body sizes and complex feeding structures.</p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/103023_cg_giant_lamprey_feat-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="1083777" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/103023_cg_giant_lamprey_feat-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item></channel></rss>