<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/" xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/" xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"><channel><title> חדשות המדע </title><atom:link href="https://www.sciencenews.org/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org<description> עיתונאות עצמאית מאז 1921</description><lastbuilddate> יום ה&#39;, 14 בספטמבר 2023 16:02:48 +0000</lastbuilddate><language> en-US</language><sy:updateperiod> מדי שעה</sy:updateperiod><sy:updatefrequency> 1</sy:updatefrequency><generator> https://wordpress.org/?v=6.2.2</generator><item><title> ציפורים עם כישורים ווקאליים מורכבים יותר פותרות בעיות טובות יותר</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/birds-complex-vocal-skills-problem-solvers<dc:creator><![CDATA[Darren Incorvaia]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Thu, 14 Sep 2023 18:00:00 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3131325 </guid><description><![CDATA[Evidence for a relationship between bird vocal learning and cognitive prowess has been mixed. Now, a massive new study confirms they are linked. (]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<p>עד עכשיו, זה לא סוד שהביטוי &quot;מוח ציפור&quot; צריך להיות מחמאה, לא עלבון. חלק מחברינו הנוצות מסוגלים לבצע משימות קוגניטיביות מורכבות, כולל <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/cockatoos-tool-kit-national-park">שימוש בכלים</a> ( <em>SN: 2/10/23</em> ). בין ההישגים המושכלים ביותר שציפורים מסוגלות לעשות הוא למידה ווקאלית, או היכולת ללמוד לחקות צלילים ולהשתמש בהם כדי לתקשר. אצל ציפורים זה מוביל לקריאות ושירים יפים; אצל בני אדם זה מוביל לשפה.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> טובי לומדי הקול של העופות, כמו עורבים ותוכים, נוטים גם הם להיחשב לציפורים האינטליגנטית ביותר. אז זה טבעי לחשוב ששתי התכונות יכולות להיות קשורות. אבל מחקרים עם ציפורים חכמות <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0003347219300168" target="_blank" rel="noopener">מצאו ראיות סותרות</a> . למרות שלמידה ווקאלית עשויה להיות קשורה ליכולת קוגניטיבית גדולה יותר במינים מסוימים, נראה שהקשר ההפוך מתקיים אצל אחרים.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> כעת, ניתוח מסיבי של 214 ציפורים מ-23 מינים מראה שאכן יש קשר בין <a href="http://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.adh3428" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">למידה קולית ולפחות יכולת קוגניטיבית מתקדמת אחת</a> - פתרון בעיות. המחקר, המתואר ב-15 בספטמבר <em>,</em> הוא הראשון לנתח מיני ציפורים מרובים במקום רק אחד. </p><figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><iframe title="ציפורים עם כישורים ווקאליים מורכבים יותר טובים יותר בפתרון בעיות | חדשות המדע" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/pI2-AfLzgJ8?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe></div><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> יותר מ-200 ציפורים מ-23 מינים עברו מבחנים קוגניטיביים שונים כדי לאמוד את האינטליגנציה שלהם. אחת המשימות לפתרון בעיות ביקשה מציפורים למשוך מכסה שעם מבקבוק זכוכית כדי לגשת לפינוק טעים (משמאל למטה). השוואת מבחנים אלה ליכולת של ציפורים ללמוד שירים וקריאות הראתה כי הלומדים הקוליים הטובים יותר גם טובים יותר בפתרון בעיות.</figcaption></figure><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> כדי להשוות בין מינים, הביולוג ז&#39;אן ניקולס אודט מאוניברסיטת רוקפלר בניו יורק ועמיתיו היו צריכים לתכנן דרך להעריך את כל היכולות הקוגניטיביות והלמידה הקוגניטיביות של הציפורים.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> לצורך למידה ווקאלית, הצוות חיפש את הספרות המדעית כדי למצוא כמה שירים ושיחות מין מסוים יכול ללמוד, האם הוא יכול ללמוד קוליות לאורך חייו או רק לתקופת התפתחות מוגדרת והאם הוא יכול לחקות מיני ציפורים אחרים. &quot;הדרך החדשה שלנו למדידת מורכבות ווקאלית משלבת את שלושת התכונות הללו יחד&quot;, אומר אודט.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> בהמשך פיתחו החוקרים מבחנים קוגניטיביים שניתן להתאים לציפורים שונות. בדיקה שנבנתה עבור כנרת בית זעירה ( <em>Troglododytes aedon</em> ), למשל, עשויה שלא לעבוד עבור יונת אבל מסורבלת ( <em>Zenaida macroura</em> ). אודט ועוזרת המחקר מלני קוטור הציגו בסופו של דבר לציפורים שבע משימות קוגניטיביות במשך שישה ימים.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> ארבע מהמשימות בדקו יכולת פתרון בעיות. לדוגמה, משימה אחת כללה משיכת מכסה שעם מהבקבוק כדי לגשת למזון שבתוכו. שלוש המשימות האחרות העריכו למידה ושליטה עצמית, סימנים אחרים של קוגניציה מתקדמת.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> לאחר מכן, הצוות ניתח האם מיני העופות בעלי יכולות למידה ווקאליות מורכבות יותר, כמו רפרטואר שירים גדול יותר, חיקוי ולמידה לכל החיים, גם הצליחו טוב יותר במבחני האינטליגנציה שלהם.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> פתרון בעיות, אך לא למידה או שליטה עצמית, קשור מאוד ללמידה ווקאלית מורכבת יותר בציפורים, מצאו החוקרים. &quot;ככל שיכולת למידה ווקאלית מתקדמת יותר, כך מיומנויות פתרון בעיות מתקדמות יותר&quot;, אומר מחבר המחקר אריך ג&#39;רוויס, ביולוג מאוניברסיטת רוקפלר.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> קח את הציצית המצומצמת ( <em>Baeolophus bicolor</em> ). המין הזה לומד בערך 63 קולות ויכול ללמוד לאורך כל חייו. הוא השלים את משימות פתרון הבעיות מהר יותר מציפור הפרה חומת הראש ( <em>M</em> <em>olothrus ater</em> ), שלומדת רק על תשע קולות בתוך חלון התפתחותי מוגדר. </p><figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="680" height="397" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/091323_DI_birdsong-smarts_bird_inline.jpg" alt="צילום של אגוז לבן חזה יושב על ידו של אדם." class="wp-image-3131328" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/091323_DI_birdsong-smarts_bird_inline.jpg 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/091323_DI_birdsong-smarts_bird_inline-656x383.jpg 656w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/091323_DI_birdsong-smarts_bird_inline-319x186.jpg 319w" sizes="(max-width: 680px) 100vw, 680px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3131328">אגוז לבן חזה ( <em>Sitta carolinensis</em> ) היה אחד מפותרי הבעיות הטובים ביותר בקרב ציפורים שיכולות ללמוד קולות רק בשלב מסוים של חייהן.</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3131328">מ&#39; קוטור</span></figcaption></figure><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> הממצא החדש הוא &quot;תוצאה מאוד משכנעת וחיובית&quot;, אומר ויליאם סירסי, ביולוג מאוניברסיטת מיאמי <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0003347219300168" target="_blank" rel="noopener">שחוקר שירת ציפורים</a> . הצוות של אודט גם מצא קשר בין למידה ווקאלית מורכבת, יכולת פתרון בעיות טובה יותר ומוחות גדולים יותר ביחס לגודל הגוף. זה יכול להסביר חלקית את התוצאה, אומר Searcy. סביר להניח שמוח גדול יותר נחוץ כדי להצטיין הן בלמידה ווקאלית והן בפתרון בעיות.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> החוקרים הצילו את המוח של כמה מהציפורים, אז הם מקווים לחפש אחר הגנים שבבסיס התכונות המקושרות. לעבודה זו עשויה להיות השלכות על הבנתם של מדענים כיצד התפתחה השפה האנושית. &quot;יש סיכוי שנגלה גנים הקשורים לפתרון בעיות וללמידה קולית, שאולי משמשים גם בבני אדם לאותן התנהגויות&quot;, אומר אודט.</p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/091323_DI_birdsong-smarts_bird_feature-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="212912" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/091323_DI_birdsong-smarts_bird_feature-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title> מדענים גילו לבסוף חמצן-28. חוסר היציבות שלו הפתיע אותם</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/oxygen-28-instability-surprise-physics<dc:creator><![CDATA[Elise Cutts]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Thu, 14 Sep 2023 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Particle Physics]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3131095 </guid><description><![CDATA[The elusive isotope was predicted to be very stable, thanks to “magic” numbers of neutrons and protons. It fell apart almost immediately.]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<p>&quot;מספר קסם&quot; של פיזיקה אולי לא כל כך קסם אחרי הכל.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> באמצעות מאיץ חלקיקים רב עוצמה, חוקרים <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-023-06352-6" target="_blank" rel="noopener">הבחינו בגרסה חמקמקה של חמצן</a> בפעם הראשונה. האיזוטופ, חמצן-28, נחזה להיות יציב הודות לשמונה הפרוטונים ו-20 הנייטרונים שלו - מספרים &quot;קסמים&quot; הקשורים ליציבות נוספת בגרעיני האטום. אבל התצפיות הראשונות של חמצן-28, שדווחו ב-31 <em>באוגוסט</em> , חושפות שהוא חולף יותר מאשר מתמשך: הגרעינים שלו מתפוררים לאחר כ-0.000000000000000000000001 שניות בערך (או 0.00000000000000000000001 שניות).</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> הממצא &quot;היה הפתעה גדולה&quot;, אומר הפיזיקאי Rituparna Kanungo מאוניברסיטת Saint Mary&#39;s בהליפקס, קנדה, שלא היה מעורב במחקר. &quot;יש לנו כמה תיאוריות עדכניות שניסו לחזות ולהסביר איך חמצן-28 צריך להיראות&quot;, אומר קאנונגו, אבל &quot;אף אחת מהן לא מסוגלת להסביר את [התצפיות]&quot;.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> גרעיני אטום מורכבים מפרוטונים ונייטרונים, שכל אחד מהם נחשב ככובש &quot;קליפות&quot; משלו - רמות אנרגיה נפרדות המופרדות על ידי פערי אנרגיה גדולים. גרעיני אטום עם קליפות חיצוניות מלאות קשורים בחוזקה במיוחד, מה שהופך אותם ליציבים מאוד. קונכיות מתמלאות כשהן פוגעות <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/blog/science-ticker/magic-number-34">בשני, שמונה, 20, 28, 50, 82 ו-126</a> חלקיקים תת-אטומיים ( <em>SN: 10/9/13)</em> .</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> לאטומים של יסוד מסוים יש מספר מוגדר של פרוטונים אך יכולים להיות להם מספר משתנה של נויטרונים. לדוגמה, האוויר שאנו נושמים מכיל את האיזוטופ חמצן-16, שיש לו שמונה פרוטונים ושמונה נויטרונים. זה הופך אותו ל&quot;קסם כפול&quot; ויציב בצורה יוצאת דופן. חמצן-28, קסם כפול עם 20 הנייטרונים ושמונה הפרוטונים שלו, היה צפוי להיות יציב מדי.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> מציאת האיזוטופ לקחה שילוב של כוח גס ואלגנטיות ניסיונית. הפיזיקאי יוסוקה קונדו מהמכון הטכנולוגי של טוקיו ועמיתיו השתמשו במאיץ חלקיקים כדי לרסק אטומי סידן-48 כנגד מטרת בריליום. זה פיצל את אטומי הסידן-48 לאיזוטופים קלים יותר, כולל פלואור-29. זריקת הפלואור-29 על מטרת מימן נוזלי הפיל פרוטון בודד, ויצר חמצן-28.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> בניגוד לציפיות, החמצן-28 התפרק כמעט מיד. כמו דלי מלא בכדורים רבים מדי, הגרעין הממולא יתר על המידה שלו עלה על גדותיו, הוריד ארבעה נויטרונים והותיר מאחור חמצן-24. על ידי זיהוי תוצרי ריקבון אלה בו זמנית, המדענים הראו שהם יצרו חמצן-28.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> חוסר היציבות המפתיעה של חמצן-28 מרמזת שמשהו חסר בתיאוריות הנוכחיות של מדענים על הכוח הגרעיני החזק, הקושר פרוטונים וניוטרונים בגרעיני אטום. &quot;אני חושב שזה כנראה יגרום להרבה התפתחויות תיאורטיות&quot;, אומר קאנונגו. &quot;זה מצביע שוב על המשימה המאוד מאתגרת הזו של הבנה מוחלטת של כוח הטבע החזק ביותר.&quot;</p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090823_ec_oxygen-28_feat-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="103501" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090823_ec_oxygen-28_feat-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title> רופאים מצאו טפיל פיתון חי במוח של אישה</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/doctors-live-python-parasite-brain<dc:creator><![CDATA[Meghan Rosen]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Thu, 14 Sep 2023 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Health & Medicine]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3131072 </guid><description><![CDATA[The infection is the first known case of the worm <em>Ophidascaris robertsi באדם. זה לא סוג התולעת היחיד שיכול להדביק את המוח האנושי.]]>; </description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<p>התסמינים המסתוריים של האישה החלו בבטנה.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> שבועות של כאבי בטן ושלשולים הובילו להזעות לילה ושיעול יבש. לאחר מכן, הרופאים מצאו נגעים בריאות, בכבד ובטחול. זיהום, אולי. אבל בדיקות לאיתור חיידקים, פטריות, טפיל אנושי ואפילו מחלה אוטואימונית עלו כולן שליליות.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> שלושה שבועות לאחר מכן, האשה הייתה בבית החולים עם חום ושיעול. סריקות CT גילו רמז שסיפר, בדיעבד: נראה שחלק מנגעי הריאות שלה נודדים. רמז שני הגיע חודשים לאחר מכן, כאשר האישה הפכה שכחנית ומדוכאת. &quot;היה לה רופא משפחה מאוד נבון שחשב, &#39;משהו לא בסדר כאן, כדאי שאעשה בדיקת MRI של המוח&#39;&quot;, אומרת סנג&#39;איה סננאייק, רופאה למחלות זיהומיות באוניברסיטה הלאומית של אוסטרליה ובבית החולים בקנברה.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> סריקת המוח הזו גילתה זוהר רפאים באונה הקדמית שלה. זה יכול היה להיות סרטן, מורסה או מחלה אחרת, אומר סנאיאק. &quot;אף אחד לא חשב שזו הולכת להיות תולעת.&quot; </p><div class="wp-block-image  has-alignleft" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><figure class="alignleft size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="451" height="450" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090723_MR_brain-worm_inline-1-451x450.jpg" alt="תמונת MRI המציגה אזור אפור בהיר במוחו של אדם." class="wp-image-3131076" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090723_MR_brain-worm_inline-1-451x450.jpg 451w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090723_MR_brain-worm_inline-1-384x383.jpg 384w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090723_MR_brain-worm_inline-1-187x186.jpg 187w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090723_MR_brain-worm_inline-1-582x580.jpg 582w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090723_MR_brain-worm_inline-1-214x214.jpg 214w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090723_MR_brain-worm_inline-1.jpg 680w" sizes="(max-width: 451px) 100vw, 451px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3131076">בדיקת MRI של המוח של האישה הראתה נגע (אזור אפור בהיר). במהלך הניתוח שלה, הרופאים הסירו תולעת חיה מתוך הנגע.</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3131076">ME Hossain <em>et al</em> / <em>מחלות זיהומיות מתעוררות</em> 2023</span></figcaption></figure></div><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> במהלך ביופסיה של המוח של האישה, הנוירוכירורג שלה הבחין במבנה דמוי מיתר חשוד ועקר אותו בעזרת מלקחיים. הוא היה ורדרד-אדום, בערך חצי אורך של עיפרון - ועדיין חי.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> &quot;זה בהחלט היה אחד מרגעי ה&#39;וואו&#39; האלה&quot;, אומר סנאייק. &quot;תולעת במוח!&quot; אבל גם הרופאים חשו הקלה. זה אומר שיש להם אבחנה, הוא אומר. סוף סוף הצוות ידע איך לטפל בחולה שלו.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> התולעת, <em>Ophidascaris robertsi,</em> הייתה <a href="https://wwwnc.cdc.gov/eid/article/29/9/23-0351_article" target="_blank" rel="noopener">נמטודה שהמארח העיקרי שלה הוא נחש</a> , כך מדווחים Senanayake ועמיתיו ב- September <em>Emerging Infectious Diseases</em> . האישה, המתגוררת בניו סאות&#39; ויילס, אוסטרליה, היא המקרה המתועד הראשון של זיהום בבני אדם.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> &quot;התולעת המתפתלת החיה הייתה... מה שעורר את כולם כל כך עניין&quot;, אומר סנאייק, &quot;אבל יש לזה צד חשוב יותר.&quot; <em>O. robertsi</em> הוא טפיל שקפץ מחיות בר לאדם. ככל שאוכלוסיות בני אדם ובעלי חיים חופפות, הוא אומר, &quot;אנחנו מתחילים לראות יותר ויותר מהזיהומים הללו&quot;.</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> בני אדם יכולים להיות מארחים מקריים לטפילים של בעלי חיים אחרים</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> הטפיל שמצאו הרופאים במוחה של האישה היה רחוק מביתו הרגיל. תולעים אלה עוברות בדרך כלל בין נחשים ליונקים קטנים. תולעים בוגרות חיות בתוך פיתוני שטיח ( <em>Morelia spilota</em> ), אשר משילים ביצי תולעים בצואה. חולדות או פוסומים, למשל, יכולים לבלוע את הביצים, שגדלות לזחלים שמתחפרים בבשר. לאחר מכן פיתונים אוכלים את החיות הנגועות, והמחזור ממשיך.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> בני אדם ורוב בעלי החיים האחרים קיימים מחוץ ללולאה זו - אם כי בשנת 2019, מדענים דיווחו על <a href="https://bvajournals.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1136/vetreccr-2019-000821" target="_blank" rel="noopener">מקרה אחד של <em>O. robertsi</em> בקואלה</a> . לא ברור בדיוק איך האישה במחקר של Senanayake נדבקה, אבל הרופאים חושדים שייתכן שהיא צרכה בטעות ביצי תולעים שהוסוו בכמה צמחי מאכל. היא גרה ליד אגם המאוכלס בפיתונים משטיח ולעתים קרובות אספה ירקות מלחיים מקומיים, שבהם אנשים משתמשים בדרך כלל לסלטים או מוקפצים.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> הביצים כנראה בקעו בגופה, והולידו זחלים שנדדו לאיבריה, וגרמו לנזק בדרך. לתולעים <em>של O. robertsi</em> &quot;אין שיניים, אבל הן נודדות דרך הרקמה והורסות אותה&quot;, אומרת מירה נאיר, מדענית למחלות זיהומיות מאוניברסיטת קליפורניה, ריברסייד, שחוקרת תולעי קרס ותולעים טפיליות אחרות. טפיל הפיתון מפריש חומרים שיכולים להמיס חלבונים ורקמות.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> הנגעים האלה שראו הרופאים בסריקות ה-CT של האישה נבעו כנראה מזחלים נודדים והדלקת של הגוף, אומר נאיר. היא חושבת שכמעט בטוח שהתולעת הייתה אשמה בתסמינים הנוירולוגיים הפתאומיים של האישה.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> הצוות של Senanayake לא הצליח למצוא דוגמאות קודמות של <em>O. robertsi</em> שפלש למוח של חיות אחרות. אבל תולעים אחרות כן.</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> תולעים טפיליות שחיות בחתולים ובכלבים עלולות גם להדביק אנשים</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> מינים שונים של תולעים עגולות <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/medical-mystery-reveals-new-host-rat-lungworm-parasite">יכולים לחיות בתוך חולדות</a> ודביבונים ואפילו חיות מחמד של אנשים ( <em>SN: 30/7/18</em> ).</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> טפילים אלה יכולים להדביק אנשים ולתול את דרכם אל המוח - וזיהומים כאלה התרחשו באנשים שחיים בארצות הברית, אומר ג&#39;יל וות&#39;רהד, רופא למחלות זיהומיות וטפילולוגית במכללת ביילור לרפואה ביוסטון. תולעי <em>Toxocara</em> טפילות חתולים וכלבים, שעלולים לעשות קקי בחצרות אחוריות, ארגזי חול או פארקים ציבוריים, ולהפיץ ביצים בהן ילדים משחקים. &quot;זו הסיבה וטרינרים מעודדים תילוע&quot;, היא אומרת.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> אם ילדים לועסים חול מזוהם, הזחלים יכולים לבקוע בגופם כמו בכלב או חתול. אבל אצל אנשים, הזחלים לא יגיעו למעיים ויתפתחו למבוגרים. במקום זאת, הם ייתקעו ברקמות אחרות.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> כמו תולעי <em>O. robertsi</em> <em>, זחלי Toxocara</em> יכולים לקשקש את הבטן ולהדליק את האיברים. רופאים דיווחו על מקרים שבהם התולעים התפתלו עד לעין של אדם. &quot;למרות שאנחנו מארחים מקריים&quot;, אומר וות&#39;רהד, הטפיל &quot;עדיין יכול לגרום למחלה משמעותית בבני אדם&quot;. </p><figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="680" height="383" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090723_MR_brain-worm_inline-2.jpg" alt="תמונה מקרוב של פניו של פיתון שטיח." class="wp-image-3131079" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090723_MR_brain-worm_inline-2.jpg 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090723_MR_brain-worm_inline-2-330x186.jpg 330w" sizes="(max-width: 680px) 100vw, 680px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3131079">תולעים טפיליות יכולות להדביק כל מיני בעלי חיים, כולל חתולים, כלבים, חולדות, דביבונים ופיתוני שטיח (אחד המוצג). ייתכן שאישה באוסטרליה בלעה בטעות ביצי תולעים שהתפשטו על ידי צואת נחשים.</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3131079">AlizadaStudios/istock/Getty Images Plus</span></figcaption></figure><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> למרות שמקרים אנושיים של תולעים עגולות חופרות מוח הם נדירים, זיהומים באופן כללי עשויים להיות שכיחים יחסית. מחקר אחד העריך שכ <a href="https://academic.oup.com/cid/article/66/2/206/4103318" target="_blank" rel="noopener">-1 מכל 20 אנשים בארצות הברית</a> נחשפו <em>לטוקסוקרה</em> .</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> אבל קשה להצביע על המספר האמיתי, כתבו Weatherhead ועמיתיה ב-23 באוגוסט ב- <em>Pediatric Infectious Disease Journal</em> . הניתוח שלהם של מקרי <em>Toxocara</em> בבית חולים לילדים בטקסס העלה כי <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/37625080/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">ילדים שחיים באזורים בעלי הכנסה נמוכה נוטים יותר להידבק</a> - במיוחד באזורים עם כלבים וחתולים משוטטים.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> &quot;אנחנו לא צריכים לפחד&quot;, אומר וות&#39;רהד, אבל חשוב להתמקד במניעה, במיוחד כשבני אדם פולשים לבתי הגידול של בעלי חיים אחרים.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Senanayake מסכים: &quot;אם אתה מטפל בצמחייה או חיות בר, רק תדאג לשטוף ידיים&quot;, הוא אומר. &quot;ואם אתם מבשלים וצורכים צמחייה, הקפידו לבשל אותה היטב, רק כדי להפחית את הסיכוי לאחד מהזיהומים החריגים הללו.&quot;</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> הוא זוכר מקרה חריג אחד לפני כ-20 שנה של טפיל בגבר צעיר שבלע שבלול ופיתח צורה חריגה של דלקת קרום המוח. כמו הגבר הזה, יהיה קשה לשכוח את האישה עם התולעת. &quot;למצוא טפיל חי במוח זה משהו... שאתה לא בהכרח מצפה לפגוש בקריירה שלך&quot;, אומר סננאייק.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> לאחר הניתוח, הרופאים טיפלו באישה בתרופות אנטי-טפיליות, ומאז השתפרו הסימפטומים שלה. כשסיפרו לה על התולעת, היא &quot;ברור שלא התלהבה&quot;, הוא אומר. אבל כמו הרופאים שלה, הוקל לה שסוף סוף יש דרך לטיפול.</p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090723_MR_brain-worm_feat-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="105293" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090723_MR_brain-worm_feat-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title> מה גורם למספר הולך וגדל של הוריקנים להתעצם במהירות?</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/increasing-number-hurricane-rapidly-intensify<dc:creator><![CDATA[Carolyn Gramling]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Wed, 13 Sep 2023 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Climate]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3131209 </guid><description><![CDATA[Hurricane Lee is just the latest storm to explode in power in only hours. The phenomenon is linked to a warming world.]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<p>בבוקר ה-5 בספטמבר נוצרה מול החוף המערבי של אפריקה מערכת מתערבלת רופפת של סופות רעמים. עד ה-6 בספטמבר, המערכת הפכה לסערה בקטגוריה 1, עם רוחות מקסימליות של לפחות 130 קילומטרים לשעה (80 מייל לשעה).</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> רק 24 שעות לאחר מכן, מונע על ידי מימי השיא החמימים של האוקיינוס ​​האטלנטי, הוריקן לי חילץ את עצמו למפלצת קטגוריה 5. בטווח הזמן הקצר הזה, מהירויות הרוח שלו הוכפלו, ל-260 קמ&quot;ש (160 מייל לשעה).</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> ככל שהאוקיינוסים בעולם ממשיכים לאגור חום מההתחממות הגלובלית, הסיפורים על התעצמות מהירה כזו של ציקלונים טרופיים הופכים להיות שכיחים יותר, ולא רק באוקיינוס ​​האטלנטי.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> &quot;בזמן שכל העיניים נשואות ל[הוריקן לי],<a href="https://twitter.com/EricBlake12/status/1699524831505518631" target="_blank" rel="noopener">[ההוריקן ג&#39;ובה] מפציץ במזרח האוקיינוס ​​השקט</a> &quot;, כתב המטאורולוג של מרכז ההוריקנים הלאומי של ארה&quot;ב אריק בלייק ב-X, שנקרא בעבר טוויטר, ב-6 בספטמבר. &quot;זה היה רק שמו לפני 36 שעות והתפוצץ להוריקן בקטגוריה 4&quot;.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> סערות אלו נוצרו שבועות ספורים לאחר הוריקן אידליה, שגם הוא התגבר במהירות. מהירויות הרוח שלו עלו מכ-120 קמ&quot;ש ל-209 קמ&quot;ש (או 75 קמ&quot;ש ל-130 קמ&quot;ש) תוך 24 שעות. זמן קצר לאחר מכן, אידליה נחבטה בחוף המפרץ של פלורידה.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> כל ההוריקנים הללו עמדו בקלות - וחלקם חרגו בהרבה - מההגדרה של מרכז ההוריקנים הלאומי להתעצמות מהירה, שבה הרוחות המרביות המתמשכות של סערה קופצות לפחות 56 קמ&quot;ש (35 מייל לשעה) תוך פחות מיממה. סערות כאלה עלולות להשאיר לאנשים מעט זמן להתכונן, מה שהופך את ההוריקנים למסוכנים במיוחד לחיים ולרכוש.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> הנה מה שצריך לדעת על סערות כאלה שמתעצמות במהירות.</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> אוקיינוס ​​ואווירה חמים יותר יכולים להניע סערות</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> המרכיבים העיקריים להגברת כוחה של סערה במהירות הם <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/warm-tropical-atlantic-waters-juiced-2017-hurricane-season">מי אוקיינוס ​​חמים מאוד</a> , <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/how-climate-change-fueling-hurricane-florence">לחות רבה באטמוספירה</a> וגזירה נמוכה של רוח אנכית, אומר מדען האטמוספירה פיליפ קלוצבאך מאוניברסיטת קולורדו סטייט בפורט קולינס ( <em>SN: 28/9/18; SN : 13/9/18</em> ).</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> גזירת רוח אנכית היא מה שקורה כאשר רוחות בגבהים שונים באטמוספירה נעות במהירויות שונות ובכיוונים שונים. הרוחות הללו יכולות להתנתק בסערה כשהיא מנסה להתארגן למערבולת הדוקה על ידי משיכת חום ולחות ממרכז הסופה וסוחפת את המבנה העליון של הסופה.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> השנה החל שלב אל ניניו של דפוס האקלים של האוקיינוס ​​אל ניניו-תנודה דרומית, שלב שנוטה להביא יותר תנאי גזירת רוח אנכית לצפון האוקיינוס ​​האטלנטי. זה אומר ששנות אל ניניו נוטות להכיל פחות <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/atlantic-hurricane-season-prediction">סופות טרופיות אטלנטיות</a> ( <em>SN: 26/5/23</em> ).</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> אבל עד כה בשנת 2023, אל ניניו לא עשה הרבה כדי למזער היווצרות סופות הוריקן, או להפחית את כוחן של הסופות. &quot;במחצית הראשונה של העונה לא נרשמו תנאי הרוח הלא נוחים במערב האוקיינוס ​​האטלנטי, הנצפים בדרך כלל בשנת אל ניניו&quot;, אומר ריאן טרוכלוט, נשיא ומטאורולוג ראשי של WeatherTiger, חברת ייעוץ מזג אוויר שבסיסה בטלהאסי. , פלורידה. זה נכון אפילו בים הקריבי, שם כוח הגזירה של אל ניניו נוטה להיות החזק ביותר, מוסיף Truchelut.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> באופן כללי, יש יותר ניגוד בטמפרטורה בין אגן האוקיינוס ​​האטלנטי והשקט במהלך שנת אל ניניו - דפוס מזג האוויר מחמם את מזרח האוקיינוס ​​השקט הטרופי בעוד האוקיינוס ​​האטלנטי נשאר קריר יחסית. אבל 2023 ראתה <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/north-atlantic-heat-record-sea-surface-temperature">טמפרטורות אוקיינוסים שוברות שיא</a> בצפון האוקיינוס ​​האטלנטי ובמפרץ מקסיקו ( <em>SN: 6/15/23</em> ). בעוד שהאוקיינוס ​​השקט המחומם באל ניניו נמצא ב-1.5 מעלות צלזיוס מעל הרגיל, חלקים מהאוקיינוס ​​האטלנטי נמצאים ב-1 עד 3 מעלות צלזיוס מעל הרגיל.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> &quot;ניגודי טמפרטורה מניעים מטוסי סילון&quot;, אומר טרכלוט, &quot;והיעדר הניגודיות הזו אחראי כנראה לגזירה החסרה&quot;.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> המים החמים ביותר של האוקיינוס ​​האטלנטי ומפרץ מקסיקו קבעו את הבמה - כל הסערות הדרושות היה חלון זמן עם תנאי רוח נוחים, אומר ג&#39;ון קפלן, מודל הוריקנים במעבדה לאוקיאנוגרפיה ומטאורולוגית של המינהל הלאומי לאוקיאנוגרפיה ואטמוספירה של ארה&quot;ב. , מבוסס במיאמי. &quot;מה שבאמת מסתכם הוא האם התנאים להתעצמות מהירה נוחים אפילו לפרק זמן קצר&quot;, הוא אומר. &quot;אם יש חלון - גם אם לא ארוך במיוחד - המערכת יכולה לנצל אותו. זה היה המקרה גם ללי וגם לאידליה&quot;.</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> סופות נוספות מתעצמות במהירות ככל שכדור הארץ מתחמם</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> זה בהחלט <em>מרגיש</em> כאילו <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/2020-extreme-weather-climate-change-hurricane-derecho-wildfire">רוב ההוריקנים בשנים האחרונות</a> מתעצמים במהירות ( <em>SN: 27/8/20</em> ). אבל האם זו מגמה אמיתית? ואם כן, האם זה קשור לשינויי אקלים?</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> מחקרים מראים שזה לא רק אנקדוטלי. באוגוסט דיווחו חוקרים כי המספר השנתי של סופות טרופיות ברחבי הגלובוס שהתגברו במהירות ממש מול החוף (בתוך 400 קילומטרים מהיבשה) <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-023-40605-2" target="_blank" rel="noopener">גדל בכ-3 בעשור</a> ב-40 השנים האחרונות, מפחות מחמש בשנה בשנות ה-80 לכ 15 לשנה עד 2020.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> סופות באוקיינוס ​​פתוח, שהסתובבו הרחק בחוץ בכחול הגדול, לא הראו שום מגמה ניכרת, כך מצא הצוות. אבל זה אולי לא לגמרי מרגיע, שכן הסופות הקרובות יותר לחוף הן המאיימות ביותר על אוכלוסיות החוף. ומחקר משנת 2021 דיווח <a href="https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.abb9038" target="_blank" rel="noopener">שציקלונים טרופיים נודדים קרוב יותר לחופים</a> מאז 1982.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> בשנת 2019, צוות אחר התמקד בתיעוד תצפית של שינויים במהירות הרוח במרווחים של 24 שעות. בהתבסס על הנתונים הללו, החוקרים מצאו כי פרקים של התעצמות מהירה בסערות טרופיות <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-019-08471-z" target="_blank" rel="noopener">שולשו מ-1982 ל-2009</a> . באמצעות סימולציות אקלים, חוקרי הצוות קבעו שמגמת ההתעצמות המהירה קשורה קשר חזק לשינויי אקלים אנתרופוגניים שנגרמו על ידי אדם.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> טרוכלוט מציין כי אותו צוות חיבר מחקר משנת 2022 <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-022-34321-6" target="_blank" rel="noopener">שתמך עוד יותר במגמת עלייה</a> בעשורים האחרונים, וקבע כי חלק גדול יותר של ציקלונים טרופיים עוברים כעת התעצמות מהירה בשלב מסוים במחזור החיים שלהם.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> דפוסי מזג אוויר אזוריים ומקומיים - כמו אירועי La Niña תכופים יותר (הצד האחורי של דפוס התנודה הדרומית אל ניניו) - &quot;יכולים לבלום מגמות התעצמות מהירה באופן מקומי&quot;, אומר Truchelut. &quot;אבל יש ראיות אובייקטיביות חזקות לכך שהתחממות כדור הארץ אנתרופוגנית גורמת להגדלת הפרופורציות של ציקלונים טרופיים לעבור התעצמות מהירה ברחבי העולם&quot;.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> קלוצבך ועמיתיו, בינתיים, מצאו טביעת אצבע נוספת של שינויי אקלים בהתעצמות המהירה של ציקלון. החוקרים דיווחו בשנת 2022 שהעלייה בטמפרטורות פני הים העולמיות מתאימות היטב <a href="https://agupubs.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1029/2021GL095774#grl63907-bib-0020" target="_blank" rel="noopener">לעלייה בעוצמה הפוטנציאלית של ציקלונים טרופיים</a> ברחבי העולם - בעצם, עד כמה חזקות הרוחות מסוגלות להיות - במהלך 30 השנים האחרונות. העלייה שנצפתה הייתה בולטת במיוחד עבור הסופות המפלצתיות ביותר - אלו שמהירות הרוח שלהן עלתה ב-93 קמ&quot;ש (57 קמ&quot;ש) ביום אחד.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> למרות זעמם של לי וג&#39;ובה, האיום שלהם התפוגג במידה רבה. הוריקן לי ירד לדרגה 3 עד ה-12 בספטמבר והתעקל צפונה; עם זאת, הוא גם גדל פי שלושה, ומאיים על ברמודה עם רוחות סופות טרופיות. הוריקן ג&#39;ובה, בינתיים, הסתובב בסופו של דבר ללא מזיק באוקיינוס ​​השקט לפני שנחלש.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> אבל כשעונת ההוריקנים רק נגמרה, עדיין יש זמן לכל המים החמים האלה לתדלק את המים הגדולים הבאים.</p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090823_cg_hurricane-ian_feat-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="292232" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090823_cg_hurricane-ian_feat-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title> לגימה גדולה של נחש קטן עלולה להבייש את כל הנחשים האחרים</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/snakes-big-gulp-gans-egg-eater<dc:creator><![CDATA[Maria Temming]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Wed, 13 Sep 2023 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Animals]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3131054 </guid><description><![CDATA[The humble Gans’ egg-eater can wrap its mouth around bigger prey than any other snake of its size. ]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<p>ציידים כפולים כמו פיתונים בורמזיים עשויים להיות מפורסמים בשל <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/blog/wild-things/python-every-meal-thanksgiving">צעיף צבאים, תנינים וטרף עצום אחר</a> ( <em>SN: 25/11/15</em> ). אבל נחש אפריקאי קטן וצנוע עשוי לקחת את התואר עבור רוב הארוחות הגדולות. ה- <em>Dasypeltis gansi</em> הלא ארסי, כמעט חסר שיניים, יכול <a href="https://zslpublications.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1111/jzo.13102" target="_blank" rel="noopener">לפתוח את פיו רחב יותר מכל נחש אחר בגודלו</a> , מדווח הביולוג ברוס ג&#39;יין ב-8 באוגוסט ב- <em>Journal of Zoology</em> .</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <em>D. gansi</em> , הנקרא לפעמים אוכל הביצים של הגאנס, בולע ביצי ציפורים בשלמותן, סודק אותן עם עמוד השדרה שלו ולולע את התוכן לפני שיורק את הקליפות. באוניברסיטת סינסינטי באוהיו, ג&#39;יין בדק 15 אוכלי ביצים באורך של כ-20 עד כ-90 סנטימטרים. לאחר שהרדים את החיות, הוא החליק צילינדרים מודפסים תלת-ממדיים רחבים יותר ויותר לתוך הכתם הפעורים שלהם כדי לקבוע את הדבר הגדול ביותר שהם יכולים לבלוע. </p><div class="wp-block-image  has-aligncenter" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><figure class="aligncenter size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="622" height="450" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090723_mt_little_snake_big_gulp_inline-622x450.jpg" alt="בצד שמאל מופיע נחש גדול עם גליל בתוך פיו, בעוד נחש קטן מופיע בצד ימין עם גליל בתוך פיו." class="wp-image-3131057" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090723_mt_little_snake_big_gulp_inline-622x450.jpg 622w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090723_mt_little_snake_big_gulp_inline-529x383.jpg 529w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090723_mt_little_snake_big_gulp_inline-257x186.jpg 257w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090723_mt_little_snake_big_gulp_inline.jpg 680w" sizes="(max-width: 622px) 100vw, 622px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3131057">אוכל הביצים הגדול ביותר של גאנס שהביולוג ברוס ג&#39;יין בדק (משמאל) היה באורך של כ-94 סנטימטרים ויכול לעטוף את פיה סביב גליל ברוחב 5 ס&quot;מ. אוכל הביצים הקטן ביותר שנבדק (מימין) היה באורך של כ-21 ס&quot;מ ויכול להתאים בפיה גליל ברוחב 1.4 ס&quot;מ.</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3131057">BC Jayne/ <em>Journal of Zoology</em> 2023</span></figcaption></figure></div><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> לאוכל הביצים הגדול ביותר שג&#39;יין נבדק היה בעל ראש ברוחב של 1 סנטימטר אחד, אבל יכול היה לבלוע גליל של כחמישה סנטימטרים. נתונים קודמים מראים שפיתון בורמזי קטן ( <em>Python molurus bivittatus</em> ) באותו אורך יכול לזלול טרף ברוחב של 4.4 סנטימטרים בלבד. נחש הרעשן המערבי ( <em>Crotalus atrox</em> ) התחרה במתנה של הפיתון ללגימה, אבל אף מין אחר לא התקרב.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> אוכלת הביצים יכולה להיפתח לרווחה כל כך מכיוון שהרקמה הרכה בין קצות הלסת התחתונה השמאלית והימנית ב&quot;סנטר&quot; כל כך נמתחת. &quot;בפיתונים הבורמזיים, כ-40 אחוז מאזור הפער הזה הוא תוצאה של מתיחה של העור בין הלסתות התחתונות, אבל החבר&#39;ה האלה מרחיקים את הפיתונים&quot;, אומר ג&#39;יין, כשבערך מחצית מהפערים של אוכלי הביצים של הגאנסים. למתוח רקמות רכות.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> יכול להיות שהמין הזה התפתח למתיחה כה מרשימה מכיוון שבהשוואה לטרף שנחשים אחרים אוכלים, כמו מכרסמים, &quot;ביצה היא קצרה במיוחד&quot;, הוא אומר. &quot;יש לך יכולת מוגבלת לקבל ביצה ארוכה מאוד. אבל אם אתה מרחיב את הפה שלך, אז אתה יכול לצרוך את הביצים הגדולות האלה&quot;. </p><figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><iframe loading="lazy" title="צפו בנחש אוכל ביצים של גאנס אוכל ביצה | חדשות המדע" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/bJRyoo9UNrg?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe></div><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> פתוח לרווחה! הנחש אוכל הביצים של גאנס הזה בולע ביצת ציפור בשלמותה, משתמש בעמוד השדרה שלה כדי לפצח את הביצה, בולע את התוכן ומחזיר את הקליפה המנופצת.</figcaption></figure><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> עד כה, גודל הפה המרבי נמדד רק עבור 13 מתוך יותר מ-3,500 מינים ידועים של נחשים. &quot;מכיוון שכמות המתיחה בעור משתנה כל כך באופן קיצוני במינים שונים&quot;, אומר ג&#39;יין, &quot;הרבה יותר קשה למדוד פערים מאשר פשוט לקחת כמה קליפרים על דגימה ממוזיאון משומרת ולמדוד עצמות.&quot;</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> ג&#39;יין מתכנן להמשיך ולחקור את גדלי הפה עבור מגוון רחב יותר של נחשים, כמו אלה שסועדים דגים. נתונים אלה יכולים לחשוף האם לאוכלי ביצים באמת יש את הלגימה הגדולה ביותר מהגלם שלהם.</p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090723_mt_little_snake_big_gulp_feat-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="806389" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090723_mt_little_snake_big_gulp_feat-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title> קקדו פראי דקל זכר מתנדנד עם מקלות תיפוף מותאמים אישית</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/wild-male-palm-cockatoos-drumsticks<dc:creator><![CDATA[Elise Cutts]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Tue, 12 Sep 2023 23:01:00 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Animals]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3131196 </guid><description><![CDATA[Along with flashy dances and distinctive drumbeats, these birds craft their own signature drumsticks to win over mates. ]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<p>כמו רומיאו בגיל ההתבגרות עם נרתיקים לגיטרה עם מדבקה, קקדו דקל זכר מראים שלרומן אהבה עם שיר אהבה זה לא רק מוזיקה - זה גם עניין של סגנון.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> קקדויי דקל בר ( <em>Probosciger aterrimus</em> ) <a href="https://royalsocietypublishing.org/doi/10.1098/rspb.2023.1271" target="_blank" rel="noopener">מייצרים כלי נגינה מותאמים אישית לטקסי הזדווגות מוזיקליים</a> לפי טעמם האישי, חוקרים מדווחים ב-13 בספטמבר ב- <em>Proceedings of the Royal Society B.</em> חלק מהזכרים היו חסידי מקלות תיפוף, אחרים הכינו שילוב של מקלות תיפוף וכלי תרמיל זרעים, ו זכר אחד לא שגרתי צעד בקצב התרמילים שלו - הוא כמעט לא הכין מקלות תופים בכלל. הנגיעות האישיות הללו קשורות יותר להעדפות אישיות מאשר לחומרים זמינים, מצא הצוות, ורמז כי בני הזוג של הקקדו הרוקינים הללו עשויים להעניק פרס ליצירתיות או אינדיבידואליות. </p><figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><iframe loading="lazy" title="קקדו זכרים שומרים על הקצב | חדשות המדע" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/gEDiwH2143I?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe></div><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> סרטון זה משנת 2017 מראה קקדו זכרי דקל פראי שומר על פעימות תוף במהלך תצוגות הזדווגות. מחקר חדש של אותו צוות מראה כעת בחירת הכלים של הציפורים היא אינדיבידואלית כמו הסגנון המוזיקלי שלהן.</figcaption></figure><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> הוספת נגיעות ייחודיות למכשירים שלהם אינה &quot;שגרה שתמיד זהה בכל חיה&quot;, אומרת הביולוגית הקוגניטיבית אליס אורספרג מהאוניברסיטה לרפואה וטרינרית וינה, שלא הייתה מעורבת במחקר. &quot;יש בזה איזה אלמנט של חדשנות.&quot;</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> אם בני אדם היו ציפורים, אולי היינו משהו כמו תוכים. כמו לנו ולבני הדודים הפרימטים שלנו, לתוכים יש מוח גדול וחכם, חיי חברה מורכבים וילדות ממושכת שבהם למדו מהוריהם.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> בניגוד לפרימטים, רוב התוכים אינם ידועים בשימוש בכלים בטבע. ו&quot;רוב התוכים שנחקרו באמצעות כלים נחקרו בשבי&quot;, אומר אורספרג. לדוגמה, הצוות שלה מצא כי קקדו של גופין ( <em>Cacatua goffiniana</em> ) שנתפסו בטבע, שהוחזקו באופן זמני בציפורי מחקר, <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/cockatoos-tool-kit-national-park">החזיקו ערכות כלים מתוחכמות לחיפוש מזון</a> ( <em>SN</em> : <em>2/10/23</em> ).</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> קקדו דקל בר הם חריג מדהים ומרתק. הציפורים המדהימות הללו, שנמצאות בסכנת הכחדה, חיות בחלקים מצפון אוסטרליה וגינאה החדשה, והן מייצרות ומשתמשות בכלים לא כדי למצוא מזון, אלא כדי למצוא בן זוג - דבר נדיר שבולט אפילו בחברת פרימטים.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> קקדו דקל זכר מציג תצוגת הזדווגות מוזיקלית מעצים בטריטוריה שלו. הוא <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/male-cockatoos-have-beat">שר, מסתובב ומתופף בקצב על העץ, לעתים קרובות באמצעות כלי הקשה</a> , מקל או תרמיל זרעים, צמוד ברגלו השמאלית ( <em>SN</em> : <em>28/6/17</em> ). כחלק מהתצוגה, הוא מייצר את המכשיר בעצמו והנקבה צופה כשהוא מנתק ענפי עצים ומקשקש אותם בדיוק כך. הוסיפו פנימה את הנוצות השחורות והאדומות והדרמטיות של הציפורים ופסגות גבוהות עם קוצים וקיבלתם אולי את הטבע הכי קרוב שיכול לבוא לקונצרט רוק. </p><figure class="wp-block-image "><picture class="sn-responsive-image"><source srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/091223_EC_cockatoos_sticks-seeds_inline_desktop.jpg 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/091223_EC_cockatoos_sticks-seeds_inline_desktop-330x165.jpg 330w" width="680" height="339" media="(min-width: 600px)" sizes="(max-width: 1023px) 100vw, 680px"></source><source srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/091223_EC_cockatoos_sticks-seeds_inline_mobile-271x450.jpg 271w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/091223_EC_cockatoos_sticks-seeds_inline_mobile-231x383.jpg 231w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/091223_EC_cockatoos_sticks-seeds_inline_mobile-112x186.jpg 112w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/091223_EC_cockatoos_sticks-seeds_inline_mobile-349x580.jpg 349w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/091223_EC_cockatoos_sticks-seeds_inline_mobile-467x776.jpg 467w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/091223_EC_cockatoos_sticks-seeds_inline_mobile.jpg 680w" width="271" height="450"></source><img src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/091223_EC_cockatoos_sticks-seeds_inline_mobile-271x450.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large" alt="שתי תמונות של מקלות ותרמילים בשימוש קקדו." decoding="async" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/091223_EC_cockatoos_sticks-seeds_inline_mobile-271x450.jpg 271w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/091223_EC_cockatoos_sticks-seeds_inline_mobile-231x383.jpg 231w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/091223_EC_cockatoos_sticks-seeds_inline_mobile-112x186.jpg 112w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/091223_EC_cockatoos_sticks-seeds_inline_mobile-349x580.jpg 349w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/091223_EC_cockatoos_sticks-seeds_inline_mobile-467x776.jpg 467w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/091223_EC_cockatoos_sticks-seeds_inline_mobile.jpg 680w" sizes="(max-width: 1023px) 100vw, 680px" data-attachment-id="3131200" data-permalink="https://www.sciencenews.org/091223_ec_cockatoos_sticks-seeds_inline_mobile" data-orig-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/091223_EC_cockatoos_sticks-seeds_inline_mobile.jpg" data-orig-size="680,1129" data-comments-opened="0" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="091223_EC_cockatoos_sticks-seeds_inline_mobile" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="&lt;p>;As part of their mating ritual, male palm cockatoos craft individualized percussion instruments — either sticks or seed pods — to drum against their trees.&lt;/p>;
" data-medium-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/091223_EC_cockatoos_sticks-seeds_inline_mobile-231x383.jpg" data-large-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/091223_EC_cockatoos_sticks-seeds_inline_mobile-271x450.jpg" /></picture><figcaption> <span class="caption mobile-caption wp-caption-3131200">כחלק מטקס ההזדווגות שלהם, קקדו דקל זכר יוצרים כלי הקשה אישיים - מקלות או תרמילי זרעים - כדי לתופף על העצים שלהם.</span> <span class="credit mobile-credit wp-credit-3131200">ד. אפלבי</span> <span class="caption desktop-caption wp-caption-3131199">כחלק מטקס ההזדווגות שלהם, קקדו דקלים זכרים יוצרים כלי הקשה אישיים - מקלות או תרמילי זרעים - כדי לתופף על העצים שלהם.</span> <span class="credit desktop-credit wp-credit-3131199">ד אפלבי</span></figcaption></figure><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> &quot;למסכי ההקשה האלה יש למעשה את כל הסממנים של מוזיקה אנושית באמצעות כלים&quot;, אומר ביולוג השימור רוב היינסון מהאוניברסיטה הלאומית האוסטרלית בקנברה. &quot;ולכל הזכרים יש חתימות תיפוף משלהם. יש כאלה שאוהבים לעשות את זה ממש לאט, יש כאלה שהולכים מהר מאוד ואז אחרים זורקים פריחה קטנה&quot;.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> היינסון ועמיתיו רצו לראות אם ציפורי הרוק הללו מבטאות את הסגנון הייחודי שלהן גם באמצעות הכלים שלהן.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> במשך שנתיים, החוקרים שוטטו בפארק הלאומי קוטיני-פיימו באוסטרליה ובארצות האבוריג&#39;ינים שמסביב, והאזינו לקריאות של הצגת קקדו זכרים. זה הוביל את הצוות ל-70 עצי תצוגה, שם אספו המדענים בסך הכל 227 מקלות תופים ו-29 מכשירי תרמיל זרעים שהושלכו על ידי הציפורים. כמו מוזיקאי שמנפץ גיטרה בסוף קונצרט, קקדו זכרים זורקים את הכלים שלהם לקרקע לאחר תצוגה.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> השוואת מכשירים שהושלכו על ידי 12 קקדו בודדים חשפה את מה שהחוקרים מפרשים כראיה להעדפה אינדיבידואלית בעיצובי המכשירים שלהם. אורך מקל התיפוף השתנה יותר מציפור לציפור ממה שניתן היה לצפות במקרה אקראי. חלקם העדיפו מקלות תופים קצרים ועקשים, בעוד שאחרים יצרו ארוכים ודקים יותר.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> &quot;כל אחד פיתח רעיון משלו לגבי מה יוצר מקל תיפוף מיוחד&quot;, אומר היינסון. יש הרבה &quot;דרכים שונות לעשות את זה נכון - להיות אמן טוב, גם בביצועים המוזיקליים שלהם, אבל גם ביצירת הכלים האלה&quot;, הוא אומר. &quot;אני חושב שלהיות באמת אינדיבידואלי ולהיות יצירתי ולהיות שם בחוץ זה חלק ממה שהנקבות מחפשות.&quot;</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> בעוד שכלי נגינה הם כמעט אוניברסליים על פני תרבויות אנושיות, ואנו משלבים לעתים קרובות חפצים נוצצים בטקסים הרומנטיים שלנו, בעלי חיים אחרים ממעטים להשתמש בכלים למוזיקה או לתצוגות הזדווגות. Scientists also rarely find evidence for individual creative choices among nonhuman toolmakers.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> This makes palm cockatoos triply fascinating: With their signature styles in music and craftsmanship, these feathered flirts are a good reminder that humanity isn&#39;t always as special as it seems.</p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/091223_EC_cockatoos_cockatoo_feature-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="99340" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/091223_EC_cockatoos_cockatoo_feature-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title> Filipino math teacher Emma Rotor helped develop crucial WWII weapons tech</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/emma-rotor-filipino-math-teacher-wwii-weapons-fuse<dc:creator><![CDATA[Erwin R. Tiongson]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Tue, 12 Sep 2023 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Physics]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3130845 </guid><description><![CDATA[Devoted wife of a famed Filipino writer, Emma Unson Rotor worked on the proximity fuze at a U.S. agency in the 1940s.]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<p>As an amateur historian studying Philippine-American history in Washington, DC, I&#39;ve long been familiar with the story of Arturo Rotor and Emma Unson Rotor.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The couple moved from the Philippines to Baltimore in 1941 for graduate studies, but World War II disrupted their plans. Shortly after the attack on Pearl Harbor, the Japanese invaded the Philippines, occupying it for three years. The Philippine Commonwealth Government (the Philippines had not yet gained independence from the United States) escaped to Washington in May 1942; Arturo joined the government in exile soon after.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Arturo, who became secretary to the Philippine president and secretary to the Commonwealth cabinet, was something of a Renaissance man. He was an accomplished medical doctor and professor, a prize-winning writer, a classically trained pianist and an orchid enthusiast. Both Rotor syndrome and an orchid variety ( <em>Vanda merrillii var. rotorii</em> ) are named for him. He was a man “surrounded by myth,” cultural historians Edilberto Alegre and Doreen Fernandez wrote in 1984.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> In contrast, his wife Emma was seen as a supportive, background presence. “Emma Unson Rotor sat quietly by [then] made an occasional comment, illustrating the supportive, companionable intelligence with which she had seen master short story craftsman Dr. Arturo Rotor through his long and shining career,” Fernandez wrote in an article describing an oral history project focused on Filipino writers. In the postwar period, Arturo and Emma lived back in the Philippines. Arturo remained a public figure, active in medical and literary circles, while Emma taught math at Assumption College, a private school in Makati. </p><div class="wp-block-image  has-alignleft" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><figure class="alignleft size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="680" height="698" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/070323_unsung_rotor_inline_couple.jpg" alt="Emma Rotor and Arturo Rotor appear side-by-side in a black and white photo." class="wp-image-3130843" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/070323_unsung_rotor_inline_couple.jpg 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/070323_unsung_rotor_inline_couple-373x383.jpg 373w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/070323_unsung_rotor_inline_couple-438x450.jpg 438w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/070323_unsung_rotor_inline_couple-181x186.jpg 181w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/070323_unsung_rotor_inline_couple-565x580.jpg 565w" sizes="(max-width: 680px) 100vw, 680px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3130843">Emma Rotor was often portrayed as a devoted and supportive wife to her more famous husband, the writer Arturo Rotor.</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3130843">Delia Unson and Ria Unson</span></figcaption></figure></div><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> But Emma Rotor was not only a devoted wife and math teacher. While living in the United States, she conducted groundbreaking weapons research.</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> How the fuze changed warfare</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> In late 2021, I read an article by Ma. Isabel Ongpin published in the <em>Manila Times</em> claiming that <a href="https://www.manilatimes.net/2021/10/15/opinion/columns/dr-arturo-b-rotor-and-emma-unson-rotor-filipino-lives-worth-remembering/1818446" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Emma Rotor was involved in weapons research</a> during the war. I was astonished. “Mrs. Rotor was a teacher of higher mathematics, a subject I stayed away from, knowing my non-quantitative mind,” Ongpin wrote. “But I had her in geography, and she was great. Mrs. Rotor as a mathematician had worked in the Manhattan Project, the secret project that produced the atomic bomb.” I reached out immediately to Ongpin to ask for any reference material she might have that documented Emma Rotor&#39;s time with the Manhattan Project. She replied that it was simply known by everyone who studied at Assumption College, where Emma taught until the 1980s.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> After searching through archival material for several months, I found no evidence that Emma was involved in the Manhattan Project. But Emma was indeed part of another weapons research program, arguably just as consequential. She became a key member of a government division that developed an early version of the proximity fuze, the mechanism that makes a shell or bomb detonate when it gets close to its target rather than on impact.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Before the proximity fuze, bombs were known to be inefficient, detonating prematurely and away from their intended targets. An often mentioned and telling statistic is that it took 20,000 shells to take down one aircraft during the London Blitz. First used in June 1943 to bring down a Japanese aircraft, the proximity fuze, which relied on radar technology, was used in major battles in Europe and Asia. In June 1944, the fuze enabled the British to take down nearly 80 percent of German V-1 “buzz bombs.”  The fuze was, according to the War Department, “one of the outstanding scientific developments of World War II” and “second only to the atomic bomb.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> First headed by the British in the 1930s, proximity fuze research was later largely led by the US government. The National Research Defense Committee assigned the task of developing fuzes “for non-rotating (eg, fin-stabilized) munitions such as bombs, rockets and mortar shells,” to the Ordnance Development Division at the National Bureau of Standards, or NBS, an agency of the US Department of Commerce. The work on rotating projectiles was assigned to the Department of Terrestrial Magnetism at the Carnegie Institution and to the Johns Hopkins Applied Physics Laboratory. </p><figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="680" height="435" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/070323_unsung_rotor_inline_proximity-fuse.jpg" alt="a proximity fuse" class="wp-image-3130844" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/070323_unsung_rotor_inline_proximity-fuse.jpg 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/070323_unsung_rotor_inline_proximity-fuse-599x383.jpg 599w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/070323_unsung_rotor_inline_proximity-fuse-291x186.jpg 291w" sizes="(max-width: 680px) 100vw, 680px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3130844">The proximity fuze caused a shell or bomb to explode when it got close to its target, rather than requiring an impact.</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3130844">National Institute of Standards and Technology Digital Collections, Gaithersburg, MD 20899</span></figcaption></figure><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Emma Rotor worked on the fuze</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Emma Rotor first came to the United States in October 1941, at the age of 28, a few months after Arturo moved to Baltimore to begin his studies of allergies and medical history at John Hopkins. She had planned to study physics there while on leave from the University of Santo Tomas in Manila, where she was a mathematics instructor. The war interrupted those plans. She was undeterred, however, and worked briefly as stenographer at the Enoch Pratt Free Library in Baltimore.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “Oh I was not discouraged,” she said in 1942 in an interview with the Baltimore <em>Evening Sun</em> . “Did I not see in the papers long columns of advertisements — girls wanted, no experience, good salaries? Well, I can work, can&#39;t I?” Though cut off from their families, “we had to learn not to worry, not to think about the things we could not change,” she said. As Emma talked, the article said, “[h]er face is rich with smiles that soften the features and round out the contours.” She is telling a story that is not happy, it continued, “except in that she makes it so.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> In January 1944, Arturo having already joined the Philippine government in exile, Emma joined the Ordnance Development Division, led by radio engineer pioneer Harry Diamond, at NBS, now known as the National Institute of Standards and Technology. Hired as a physicist in a “war time appointment,” she was tasked with supporting “experimental investigations connected with the development of new ordnance devices,” including the “design, construction and testing of mechanical, electrical and radio devices,” according to her appointment letter, which I tracked down with the help of independent researcher Emma Prince, based in St. Louis.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Keith Martin, a librarian at NIST, who I exchanged email messages with, estimates a total of 155 staff members in the division at the time, including those not involved in proximity fuze research, and about 31 in Emma&#39;s section.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> She was promoted in less than a year. And in March 1945, her supervisor, physicist William B. McLean, gave her an “excellent” performance rating. “Regardless of grade, Mrs. Rotor is one of the most valuable individuals in the present project,” McLean wrote.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> During her time with NBS, which ended in 1947, Emma wrote several scientific papers or coauthored them with colleagues, including Albert G. Hoyem, a physics professor at the University of Iowa in Iowa City who later became a senior official of the Naval Ordnance Test Station at China Lake in California. Her work on “Air travel required for release of arming cover” and on “Measurement of dynamic propeller unbalance” are cited in the 1946 summary report of the Ordnance Development Division&#39;s work on the proximity fuze, titled “ <a href="https://archive.org/details/radioproximityfu01elle/page/n5/mode/2up" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Radio Proximity Fuzes for Fin-Stabilized Missiles</a> .”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “Evaluation of the toss technique” (which she authored with Hoyem) reports the results of tests to map out trajectories of bombs. The paper appears in a collected volume of scientific articles on “ <a href="https://archive.org/details/bombrockettorped00unit" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Bomb, Rocket, and Torpedo Tossing</a> ” published in 1946 that also credits Emma “not only for the contributions mentioned above but also for her diligent supervision of the review and assembly of the final manuscript.” She appears to be the only woman among the authors.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> NIST&#39;s museum features a proximity fuze and a fin-stabilized missile that, as Martin wrote via email, “she, and others, had a hand in developing.” </p><figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/070323_unsung_rotor_inline_art.jpg" alt="A painting of Emma Rotor smiling and wearing a peach tunic appears on one side of a book. The opposite page displays mathematical calculations." class="wp-image-3130842" width="680" height="406" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/070323_unsung_rotor_inline_art.jpg 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/070323_unsung_rotor_inline_art-641x383.jpg 641w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/070323_unsung_rotor_inline_art-312x186.jpg 312w" sizes="(max-width: 680px) 100vw, 680px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3130842">The visual artist Ria Unson keeps her great aunt Emma Rotor alive through art. Unson altered a book with a portrayal of Rotor to “write her back into history.”</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3130842">“Eminence grise” by Ria Unson</span></figcaption></figure><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Emma Rotor&#39;s legacy</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Arturo died in 1988 and Emma in 1998. Arturo and Emma never had children of their own, but a niece, Delia Unson, and a grandniece, Ria Unson, remember Emma fondly. “Tita Emma was an amazing teacher,” Delia Unson, a retired clinical psychologist, recalls. “She could teach anyone and get them to love or at least like math. I met some of her students and found that they loved her!” Emma thought math was easy, Delia Unson says, “because you didn&#39;t have to remember a lot. As long as one remembered the basic formulas and laws.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Ria Unson remembers spending many afternoons when she was young at Emma&#39;s house. “She was an accepting, nonjudgmental person,” Ria Unson says. A visual artist, Ria Unson has been keeping alive her memories of Emma through her art.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> I asked Ria Unson if she thought Emma would have been comfortable with an article highlighting her role in weapons research. She paused. “I don&#39;t think she looked for the spotlight,” Ria Unson said. “She just did what was asked.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> It is clear, however, that Emma didn&#39;t talk openly with her family about this aspect of her life. A couple of family members did think briefly that she might have been part of the Manhattan Project. “Tita, did you work on the bomb?” Ria Unson recalls her father asking Emma likely at a family gathering decades ago. No, Emma replied, a faint smile. “I worked on the fuze.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> No one understood what she meant then, Delia Unson and Ria Unson said, until I showed them a few months ago her work on the proximity fuze. “That was so like her,” Ria Unson said, thinking of that moment at the family gathering. “She wanted people to know but didn&#39;t want people to know.”</p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/070323_unsung_rotor_feat-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="181129" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/070323_unsung_rotor_feat-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title> The world&#39;s highest-dwelling mammal isn&#39;t the only rodent at extreme elevation</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/highest-elevation-mammal-mouse-rodent<dc:creator><![CDATA[Meghan Rosen]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Mon, 11 Sep 2023 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Animals]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3130902 </guid><description><![CDATA[After discovering a mouse living nearly 7,000 meters above sea level, scientists scoured other extreme environments to make sure the find wasn’t a fluke. ]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<p>On a series of expeditions along the spine of the Andes Mountains, a team of high-climbing researchers has found mammalian life scampering through some of Earth&#39;s harshest environments.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> From 2020 to 2022, evolutionary biologist Jay Storz and colleagues trekked to the peaks of 21 volcanoes in South America. They&#39;ve seen plumes of gas billowing from rocky vents, endured ferocious winds and subfreezing temperatures, and spent nights camping nearly 6,000 meters above the sea. “It&#39;s really hard to exaggerate how inhospitable these super high elevation environments are,” says Storz, of the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The austere landscapes look like something you might see on Mars, he says — not the kind of places you&#39;d expect to see wildlife. But for some mammals, such extreme locales are home. <a href="https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2023.08.22.554215v1?ct=" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Multiple species of rodents live at or near the high-altitude peaks of Andean volcanoes</a> , well above where alpine herbs, dwarf shrubs and other plants can grow, Storz and his colleagues report in a paper posted August 23 at bioRxiv.org.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Finding mammalian life above the vegetation line is “pretty unique and incredible, because what do they eat?” asks Jonathan Velotta, a biologist at the University of Denver who studies how animals adapt to extreme environments. He thinks Storz&#39;s new work could change how scientists think about where life exists. It “suggests that animals live higher than we thought was possible,” Velotta says.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Storz and his colleagues are no strangers to altitudinous adventures. Three years ago, the researchers reported the world-record holder for highest-dwelling mammal. They found the animal, <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/south-american-mouse-world-highest-dwelling-mammal">a yellow-rumped leaf-eared mouse</a> , on the summit of Volcán Llullaillaco at an altitude of 6,739 meters, more than three quarters the height of Mount Everest <em>(SN: 7/29/20)</em> .</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> But the scientists wondered if finding that mouse meant more mammals actually lived at extreme elevations — or if spotting it was just a fluke. The team embarked on a series of elevational surveys — the broadest ever conducted — over a wider geographic area, catching small mammals from the coastline of northern Chile to the crest of the Andean mountain chain. Researchers have performed other surveys at different high-altitude sites, Velotta says, but the areas Storz&#39;s team explored are higher, more remote and require more specialized training and equipment. “It takes mountaineering expertise to do what they do,” Velotta says.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Trips can last three weeks or more, and Storz&#39;s team packs everything they&#39;ll need in a couple of pickup trucks. Their destinations are so remote, there&#39;s typically no opportunity to resupply. They&#39;ll bring food, fuel, water, ice axes, crampons, climbing rope and hundreds of live traps. The team will start catching mice at low altitudes, then work their way up, acclimatizing to higher elevations along the way. Eventually, the researchers will set up base camp at around 5,000 meters above sea level, and sometimes a second camp even higher. </p><figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1030" height="680" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090123_mr_mice_inline1.jpg" alt="mountain climbers" class="wp-image-3130904" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090123_mr_mice_inline1.jpg 1030w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090123_mr_mice_inline1-580x383.jpg 580w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090123_mr_mice_inline1-682x450.jpg 682w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090123_mr_mice_inline1-282x186.jpg 282w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090123_mr_mice_inline1-768x507.jpg 768w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090123_mr_mice_inline1-879x580.jpg 879w" sizes="(max-width: 1030px) 100vw, 1030px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3130904">Jay Storz (in yellow) and Naim Bautista (in black) descend from the summit of Volcán Guallatiri, an active volcano on the border of Chile and Bolivia where the researchers surveyed for small mammals.</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3130904">Mario Pérez Mamani</span></figcaption></figure><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Oxygen levels drop as elevation rises; at base camp and beyond, the researchers may be breathing about half the amount of oxygen they would at sea level. That makes it hard to sleep and hard to do science, says Guillermo D&#39;Elía, an evolutionary biologist at Austral University of Chile. “Everything gets slower,” he says. At sea level, he can set twenty traps in 20 or 30 minutes. At altitude, it takes him about double that time.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Dealing with the lack of oxygen gets easier after a few days, Storz says, but the expeditions&#39; hardships underscore just how difficult it is to survive in cold, low oxygen conditions. “We&#39;re experiencing the same kind of environmental challenges that our study animals are.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> On his team&#39;s latest trips, the researchers found species of mice that take second through fifth place for highest elevational record for mammals.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Though their work focuses on small mammals, D&#39;Elía says, there&#39;s so much more to explore. He&#39;s seen wandering lizards, insects, subterranean rodents called tuco-tucos and puma tracks near high-altitude hot springs. Rabbitlike viscacha hop along the volcanoes&#39; rocky slopes, and on one memorable trip, Storz saw a pack South American ostriches rush by. “They look so prehistoric,” Storz says, like velociraptors. Add in the volcanic vistas and you&#39;ve got something straight out of <em>The Land Before Time</em> , he says.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The team&#39;s expeditions have given him a new appreciation for the capacity of animals to survive in unimaginably harsh conditions. “Even in these hostile environments,” Storz says, “life finds a way.”</p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090123_mr_mice_feat-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="1334992" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090123_mr_mice_feat-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title> Flashes in Venus&#39; atmosphere might be meteors, not lightning</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/venus-atmosphere-meteor-lightning-space<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sid Perkins]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Mon, 11 Sep 2023 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Planetary Science]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3131048 </guid><description><![CDATA[With upcoming missions planned for Venus, scientists are eager to figure out the origin of the mysterious flashes.]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<p>Occasional flashes light up Venus&#39; shroud of clouds. Previous analyses have hinted that the bursts of light could be lightning in the hellish world&#39;s atmosphere. But a new study suggests most of the flashes may be nothing more than the brief yet brilliant blazes of meteors.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> With <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/nasa-venus-mission-davinci-veritas-space-planetary-science">upcoming missions planned for Venus</a> , scientists are eager to figure out the light&#39;s origin ( <em>SN: 6/2/21</em> ). If the flashes are lightning, the electrical phenomenon could pose risks to future probes dropping through the Venusian atmosphere or carried by balloons for extended periods in the planet&#39;s clouds, says Claire Blaske, a planetary scientist now at Stanford University. Small meteors that burn up in the atmosphere, however, wouldn&#39;t pose much of a danger.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Previous landers on Venus have often detected electromagnetic static similar to the type picked up on AM radio and caused by lightning during thunderstorms on Earth, Blaske says. And orbiters and Earth-based telescopes have discerned brief, bright flashes in the atmosphere.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> But the static and optical flashes have never been detected simultaneously, Blaske says. And, notes Paul Byrne, a planetary scientist at Washington University in St. Louis who was not involved in the study, “it&#39;s not clear there is the potential for lightning on Venus” given how little is known about the dynamics of its atmosphere.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Blaske, then at Arizona State University in Tempe, and her colleagues wondered whether meteors could be masquerading as lightning on Venus. Two surveys counted the flashes of light: one by a telescope on Arizona&#39;s Mount Bigelow and one by instruments aboard Japan&#39;s <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/japanese-spacecraft-reaches-venus-five-years-late">Akatsuki orbiter</a> ( <em>SN: 12/8/15</em> ).</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Given that data, there are probably <a href="https://agupubs.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1029/2023JE007914" target="_blank" rel="noopener">between 10,000 and 100,000 of these flashes each year</a> , the researchers report in the September <em>Journal of Geophysical Research</em> <em>:</em> <em>Planets.</em></p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> That may seem like too many flashes to all be caused by meteors. After all, Venus is a slightly smaller cosmic target than Earth. But meteors there will be substantially brighter — and thus more noticeable — because they are traveling faster on average: The space rocks zip through Venus&#39; atmosphere at about 25 kilometers per second, compared with 20.3 kilometers per second for meteoroids entering Earth&#39;s atmosphere. In part, that&#39;s because Venus is traveling around the sun faster than Earth is.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Overall, these factors and others led Blaske and her colleagues to conclude that meteors could be numerous enough to account for most, if not all, of the flashes expected to occur in Venus&#39; atmosphere.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The team&#39;s analysis “is convincing and does a nice job of establishing a plausible explanation for these flashes,” Byrne says. Future observations that simultaneously measure the flashes and electromagnetic static on Venus could help resolve the mystery. But other big questions remain. For example, it&#39;s unknown whether Venus might experience a form of lightning, or other type of electrical discharge, in its carbon dioxide–rich atmosphere that isn&#39;t accompanied by flashes of light but could still pose a risk to probes.</p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090623_sp_venus-lightning-meteors_feat-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="57103" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090623_sp_venus-lightning-meteors_feat-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title> &#39;Crossings&#39; explores the science of road ecology</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/crossings-book-science-road-ecology-goldfarb<dc:creator><![CDATA[Amanda Heidt]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Fri, 08 Sep 2023 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Ecosystems]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3130858 </guid><description><![CDATA[Ben Goldfarb talks about his new book, which looks at the science that’s helping to prevent animals from becoming roadkill.]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[



<div class="wp-block-image  has-alignleft"><figure class="alignleft size-medium is-resized"><a href="https://bookshop.org/a/21798/9781324005896" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/082623_reviews_cover-1-254x383.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-3130865" width="191" height="287" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/082623_reviews_cover-1-254x383.jpg 254w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/082623_reviews_cover-1-298x450.jpg 298w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/082623_reviews_cover-1-123x186.jpg 123w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/082623_reviews_cover-1-384x580.jpg 384w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/082623_reviews_cover-1-514x776.jpg 514w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/082623_reviews_cover-1.jpg 680w" sizes="(max-width: 191px) 100vw, 191px" /></a></figure></div><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <a href="https://bookshop.org/a/21798/9781324005896" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Crossings</a><br> <em>Ben Goldfarb<br> WW Norton &amp; Co., $30</em></p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Nearly 65 million kilometers of roadway crisscross the Earth — enough to encircle the planet more than 1,600 times — and that number will likely double by 2050. These roads have intruded into even the most remote corners of the world, and that has come at a cost: Vehicles are responsible for a staggering number of animal deaths. For instance, 1 million vertebrates are thought to die daily in collisions in the United States alone. Roads also kill indirectly, in part by fracturing migration routes and degrading pristine habitat.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> In <em>Crossings</em> , journalist Ben Goldfarb delves into the burgeoning field of road ecology and introduces the impassioned, sometimes eccentric scientists who invite us to perceive our roads as animals do to better understand the ecological impacts. Goldfarb journeys alongside these researchers as they bike through Montana and wrestle anteaters in Brazil, squint at roadkill and rhapsodize about the design quirks that engineers can leverage to attract animals to safe overpasses and culverts. Road ecology, many of its proponents say, is a win-win: Building dedicated wildlife crossings, for example, is relatively cheap compared with other infrastructure projects, and minimizing collisions between drivers and animals preserves lives and lowers insurance premiums.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <em>Science News</em> spoke with Goldfarb about roads and how to minimize their harm. The following conversation has been edited for clarity and brevity.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <strong><em>SN</em> : How did you get interested in road ecology? It seems very different from your <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/got-environmental-problem-beavers-could-be-solution">previous book on beavers</a> ?</strong></p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <strong>Goldfarb:</strong> The origins of this book date back to 2013, when I was on a reporting trip about habitat connectivity. I caught wind of wildlife crossings on Highway 93 in northern Montana, and I ended up taking a tour of them with Marcel Huijser, a wonderful road ecologist at the Western Transportation Institute in Montana.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The most powerful moment of that tour was when we moved to the one big wildlife overpass on Highway 93. The sun was going down on this beautiful October evening, and it was just incredibly inspiring to be on top of this piece of infrastructure that humans had built for wild animals. We do so much on this planet to make animals&#39; lives more difficult, and as a conservation journalist, it felt like a form of ecological empathy manifested as a science.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <strong><em>SN</em> : You dedicate a lot of the book to small animals like reptiles, amphibians, insects and fish. Is that where the science led you?</strong></p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <strong>Goldfarb:</strong> It&#39;s where the field of road ecology is going in a lot of ways. A lot of the early history is focused on deer because that&#39;s what safety-oriented engineers worry about. But as the field has evolved [to become more focused on conservation than human safety], it&#39;s gotten more concerned with less charismatic, less dangerous organisms. They are important to think of because in some ways they&#39;re the taxa most harmed by roads.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <strong><em>SN</em> : How has this book changed your perceptions of roads?</strong></p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <strong>Goldfarb:</strong> One of the biggest takeaways is just how deleterious road noise pollution is. When you read the literature about the health effects and the ecological effects of road noise, you realize that it&#39;s truly one of the great unsung public health crises of our time. It&#39;s elevating our cortisol levels, raising our blood pressure, and making us more susceptible to cardiac disease and stroke.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <strong><em>SN</em> :</strong> <strong>You make a lot of comparisons between roads and climate change and the actions that are needed to address them.</strong></p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <strong>Goldfarb:</strong> The climate movement has evolved a lot over the last decade away from individual blaming and towards indicting larger corporate power structures. The same holds true in the world of road ecology. Most of us have had the experience of hitting wild animals. I&#39;ve killed animals, unfortunately, and I always feel incredibly guilty about it and complicit in this car culture. But car culture is the product of this very intensive marketing campaign that the whole automotive industrial complex has waged.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Instead of blaming drivers for roadkill, the real answers are these larger systemic solutions. Maybe that&#39;s modifying infrastructure to build more wildlife crossings to make highways permeable; maybe it means improved mass transit systems.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <strong><em>SN</em> :</strong> <strong>You end the book talking about how roads have been leveraged as a tool of oppression against Black and brown communities. Why was it important to include that aspect?</strong></p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <strong>Goldfarb:</strong> The parallels between the ways that roads impact ecological communities and the ways they impact human communities are striking. Highways are forces of division in both ecosystems and cities, and we humans fall victim to cars, just as wild animals do. But I also wanted to recognize that we&#39;re not all harmed equally — roads, especially urban freeways, have been very deliberately weaponized against communities of color throughout the last century. And that&#39;s still happening today.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <strong><em>SN</em> : You quote an early US Forest Service employee as saying “roads are such final and irretrievable facts,” yet the book argues that roads can be made into “visitors” in a landscape.</strong></p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <strong>Goldfarb:</strong> We have the capacity to change them. The Forest Service, one of the world&#39;s largest road managers, is decommissioning thousands of roads, recognizing that they still have harmful ecological effects. On the other end of the spectrum, you have places like Syracuse, where an urban freeway was punched through the middle of the city, deliberately wiping out a Black neighborhood. This old viaduct will be torn down in recognition of the disproportionate harms that it inflicted on people of color.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> It&#39;s remarkable to think that everything from tiny dirt roads to this enormous urban freeway are being unmade. Our roads aren&#39;t necessarily fatal, permanent mistakes after all.</p><hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" /><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <em>Buy</em> <a href="https://bookshop.org/a/21798/9781324005896" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Crossings</a> <em>from Bookshop.org.</em> Science News <em>is a Bookshop.org affiliate and will earn a commission on purchases made from links in this article.</em></p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/082623_reviews_feat-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="632447" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/082623_reviews_feat-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title> Here&#39;s why mathematicians are so interested in cake cutting</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/cake-cutting-math-problem-fairness-envy<dc:creator><![CDATA[Stephen Ornes]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Fri, 08 Sep 2023 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Math]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3130994 </guid><description><![CDATA[The question of how to fairly divide resources attracts game theorists, computer scientists, economists, legal experts and more. ]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<p>Ariel Procaccia has thought a lot about how to cut cake over the last 15 years. That&#39;s partly because the Harvard computer scientist has three children who among them have celebrated more than two dozen birthdays. He knows what it&#39;s like to stand with a knife before a layered masterpiece, frosted with buttercream and chocolate curls, while pressed on all sides by small partygoers who instinctively recognize when someone else gets a better slice.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> But it&#39;s also because much of Procaccia&#39;s work focuses on exploring the mathematical rules for dividing stuff up. One way to do that is to think abstractly about dessert. For more than 75 years, he and other researchers trying to formalize fairness have been asking the deceptively simple question: What methods for cutting a cake guarantee that everyone who shows up to the party is happy with what they get?</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The answers reach far beyond birthday parties. Cake-cutting contemplation is part of a sprawling mathematical subfield focused on the fair division of resources. It has spurred a raft of algorithms informing how to allocate food among hungry communities, <a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/00029890.1999.12005142" target="_blank" rel="noopener">how to split rent</a> or chores among roommates, <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/mathematician-answers-supreme-court-plea">how to draw boundaries for fair voting districts</a> and more. A mathematical problem at its heart, cake cutting connects rigorous reasoning to questions of human preferences and real-world issues, and so attracts not only mathematicians, but also computer scientists, economists, social scientists and legal experts. Questions of fairness (and unfairness) are decidedly universal. Of course, so is dessert. “It&#39;s this very elegant model in which you can really distill what fairness is, and reason about it,” Procaccia says.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The cake, says Steven Brams, a game theorist and political scientist at New York University, is a metaphor for any divisible good, like land or time or limited resources. When cake-cutting insights are applied to settling international disputes, he says, “we are potentially helping the world find solutions.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Experts have come up with cake-cutting algorithms — the mathematical rules for describing how to cut a cake fairly — many times and in many guises. (The approaches almost always focus on rectangular cakes. The related but more recent <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/cutting-pie-no-piece-cake">“pie-cutting” problem</a> addresses circular desserts or pizza.) The easiest rules reveal how to fairly share a cake between two people: One person cuts the cake into two pieces that they believe to be equal in value, and the other person picks first. Each eater receives a piece that they feel is at least as valuable as the other&#39;s, if not better. Reports of this fair division strategy date back to ancient Greece.</p><figure class="wp-block-pullquote alignleft"><blockquote style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> You can argue that fairness, or the lack thereof, is one of the most important problems in the world today.</p> <cite>Steven Brams</cite></blockquote></figure><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> In the 1940s, mathematicians began taking serious interest in a mathematical approach to fairness, using cake cutting as an access point. They started exploring how to fairly share among three people, since I-cut-you-choose is a two-player game. That led to looking for ways to extend those algorithms to arbitrarily large numbers of people, and to asking more nuanced questions, like what is fairness exactly, and how do you prove it?</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Cake cutting is easy to formulate and easy to relate to, says game theorist Bettina Klaus of the University of Lausanne in Switzerland, who studies fairness in real-world situations like school choice allocation and equal access to housing. “But at the same time, the problem is mathematically interesting and challenging because of its complexity once the number of agents to share the cake grows.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Recent years have brought progress in identifying the fewest number of cuts needed for a given number of people, as well as the maximum number of cuts, which can get ridiculously high but at least shows that cake cutting is finite. And new variations on the question keep emerging. What if you <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2001.03327" target="_blank" rel="noopener">divide a cake for multiple groups of people</a> instead of individuals? Or, as explored in a paper published last year, what if cake eaters <a href="https://dl.acm.org/doi/abs/10.1145/3490486.3538321" target="_blank" rel="noopener">lie about their preferences</a> ? And what if you&#39;re divvying up something that comes in discrete, indivisible pieces, like unopened Halloween candies, instead? By focusing on precise definitions and new scenarios, mathematicians have found new applications and kept cake cutting at the forefront of investigations into fairness.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “You can argue that fairness, or the lack thereof, is one of the most important problems in the world today,” says Brams, who over four decades has published hundreds of works on cake cutting or fairness more generally. “And we&#39;re looking at the theoretical foundations of fairness.”</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Recipes for fair cake cutting</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Documented experiments in finding fair ways to split stuff up go way back, at least to Hesiod&#39;s poem <em>Theogony</em> , written some 2,700 years ago. In one story in the poem, gods and mortals clashed in Mecone, a mythical Greek city. As a sacrifice to appease the gods, Prometheus, who was both a god and humankind&#39;s greatest benefactor, divided a recently slaughtered ox into two piles, one containing unappealing bare bones covered with a layer of fat and the other containing the desirable meat concealed beneath an unappealing section of stomach. Prometheus invited Zeus to take his pick. Zeus, seduced by the shiny fat, chose the unappetizing bones.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> In this ancient story, Prometheus infuses the classic I-cut-you-choose strategy — the simplest version of cake cutting — with deception. But when I-cut-you-choose is executed in pursuit of fairness, it should guarantee the satisfaction of everyone involved.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The outcome is proportional, meaning that each player feels like their slice represents a fair share of the total. So for two players, a player would value their own slice at 1/2; for three, a fair share would be 1/3. (And for some arbitrary n number of cake eaters, a fair share would be 1/n.) If the cake is the same throughout, proportionality is equivalent to all the slices being the same size.</p><div class="wp-block-sciencenews-content-sidebar" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><h3 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> How to share cake between two people</h3><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> You probably already know how to fairly share cake between two people. It&#39;s the simplest approach to fairly cutting cake and is often called the “divider-chooser” method. </p><div
	class="container"
	data-component="slideshow"
 style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><div class="controls-wrapper" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"></div><ol class="slides" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><li class="wrapper item-1" role="list-item" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><figure class="figure"><img decoding="async" width="650" height="383" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_cake-cut-and-choose-1-650x383.jpg" class="attachment-medium size-medium" alt="All illustration shows an Alice&#039;s face next to a cake with two slices and a knife below." loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="3131012" data-permalink="https://www.sciencenews.org/090923_cake-cut-and-choose-1" data-orig-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_cake-cut-and-choose-1.jpg" data-orig-size="681,401" data-comments-opened="0" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="090923_cake-cut-and-choose-1" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="&lt;p>;First, one person, in this case Alice, cuts the cake into what she thinks are two fair slices.&lt;/p>;
" data-medium-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_cake-cut-and-choose-1-650x383.jpg" data-large-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_cake-cut-and-choose-1.jpg" /><figcaption class="gallery-caption"> <span class="caption">First, one person, in this case Alice, cuts the cake into what she thinks are two fair slices.</span> <span class="credit">OLENA SHMAHALO</span> </figcaption></figure></li><li class="wrapper item-2" role="list-item" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><figure class="figure"><img decoding="async" width="650" height="383" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_cake-cut-and-choose-2-650x383.jpg" class="attachment-medium size-medium" alt="An illustration shows Bob&#039;s face next to a slice of cake and Alice&#039;s face next to a slice of cake." loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="3131013" data-permalink="https://www.sciencenews.org/090923_cake-cut-and-choose-2" data-orig-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_cake-cut-and-choose-2.jpg" data-orig-size="681,401" data-comments-opened="0" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="090923_cake-cut-and-choose-2" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="&lt;p>;The second person, Bob, chooses his preferred slice. Alice gets the remaining slice. Alice is happy because she liked both pieces equally; Bob is happy because he chose his favorite piece.&lt;/p>;
" data-medium-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_cake-cut-and-choose-2-650x383.jpg" data-large-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_cake-cut-and-choose-2.jpg" /><figcaption class="gallery-caption"> <span class="caption">The second person, Bob, chooses his preferred slice. Alice gets the remaining slice. Alice is happy because she liked both pieces equally; Bob is happy because he chose his favorite piece.</span> <span class="credit">OLENA SHMAHALO</span></figcaption></figure></li></ol></div></div><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> But cake cutting isn&#39;t an interesting mathematical problem if the cake is all the same. Ordinary division and a kitchen scale could readily separate a slab of uniform chocolate sponge into any number of proportional pieces. The problem becomes more complicated if you assume that the cake is heterogeneous — if it&#39;s unevenly frosted, for example, or includes sections of varying flavors and toppings.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> A maraschino cherry–lover might choose the smallest slice and feel satisfied if they get the cake&#39;s only cherry. In this case, what mathematicians call the “serendipity of disagreement” gives rise to rich math. The most interesting math arises when there are differing opinions.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> A two-person I-cut-you-choose scenario still works here. The divider divides the cake into two pieces of equal value in their view and will be happy with either; the chooser chooses their preferred piece. But increase the number of cake eaters, each with particular preferences, and there&#39;s no easy solution.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Hugo Steinhaus of the University of Warsaw was one of the first mathematicians to dive into this complexity. During World War II, as questions of fair division of land were playing out on a large and violent scale, Steinhaus developed a <a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/1914289" target="_blank" rel="noopener">modified I-cut-you-choose strategy</a> for three players. It came to be called the lone-divider method.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> In this approach, one person, let&#39;s call her Alice, cuts the cake into three pieces that she values equally (each at 1/3 of the total). Then a second person, Bob, indicates which of the pieces would be acceptable to him. If he approves at least two pieces, then the third person, Carla, can take any piece she wants, followed by Bob (who has at least one acceptable piece available). Alice gets the one that&#39;s left.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> But if either Bob or Carla disapprove of the same piece, then that piece goes to Alice (who valued all pieces equally). The remaining two pieces (which Bob and Carla must value at 2/3 or more of the total) are recombined and shared between Bob and Carla using I-cut-you-choose.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Steinhaus described this algorithm in a short paper published in 1948 in <em>Econometrica</em> . It represented one of the first rigorous investigations in the field of cake cutting. “The rule for the first partner,” Steinhaus wrote, “allows him to cut the object — it may be a cake — as he pleases.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Steinhaus&#39; method worked for only three eaters, but in the same paper, he reported that two colleagues had developed an algorithm that could achieve proportionality for any number of cake eaters. The method is known as the last-diminisher method, and it goes like this: One person cuts off a piece of cake they deem to represent a fair share and passes that piece along to the next person. Each remaining player has a chance to either trim the cake (if they think it represents more than a proportional share) or pass (if they think it&#39;s proportionally fair or less than fair). Once everyone has had a chance to trim, or “diminish” the slice, the last person who trimmed gets the piece and exits the game.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The trim is then recombined with the remaining cake, and the process begins again with the remaining players. When only two players are left, they use I-cut-you-choose.</p><div class="wp-block-sciencenews-content-sidebar" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><h3 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> How the “last-diminisher” method works</h3><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Sharing cake among three people is harder. In the “last-diminisher” method, three people — Alice, Bob and Carla — each believe they are getting a piece that they value at 1/3 of the total. Mathematicians call that “proportionality,” but whoever exits the game first could still be envious of someone else&#39;s piece. </p><div
	class="container"
	data-component="slideshow"
 style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><div class="controls-wrapper" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"></div><ol class="slides" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><li class="wrapper item-1" role="list-item" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><figure class="figure"><img decoding="async" width="650" height="383" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_cake-last-diminisher-1-650x383.jpg" class="attachment-medium size-medium" alt="Illustration showing Alice&#039;s face beside a cake with a cut slice and a knife." loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="3131014" data-permalink="https://www.sciencenews.org/090923_cake-last-diminisher-1" data-orig-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_cake-last-diminisher-1.jpg" data-orig-size="681,401" data-comments-opened="0" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="090923_cake-last-diminisher-1" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="&lt;p>;In round 1, the first person, in this case Alice, cuts a piece that she thinks represents 1/3 the value of the cake and passes it to the second person, Bob.&lt;/p>;
" data-medium-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_cake-last-diminisher-1-650x383.jpg" data-large-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_cake-last-diminisher-1.jpg" /><figcaption class="gallery-caption"> <span class="caption">In round 1, the first person, in this case Alice, cuts a piece that she thinks represents 1/3 the value of the cake and passes it to the second person, Bob.</span> <span class="credit">OLENA SHMAHALO</span> </figcaption></figure></li><li class="wrapper item-2" role="list-item" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><figure class="figure"><img decoding="async" width="650" height="383" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_cake-last-diminisher-2-650x383.jpg" class="attachment-medium size-medium" alt="" loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="3131015" data-permalink="https://www.sciencenews.org/090923_cake-last-diminisher-2" data-orig-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_cake-last-diminisher-2.jpg" data-orig-size="681,401" data-comments-opened="0" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="090923_cake-last-diminisher-2" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="&lt;p>;Bob and the third person, Carla, each have a chance to trim the piece, if they think it is worth more than 1/3 the value, or pass. In this case, Bob passes and Carla trims. &lt;/p>;
" data-medium-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_cake-last-diminisher-2-650x383.jpg" data-large-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_cake-last-diminisher-2.jpg" /><figcaption class="gallery-caption"> <span class="caption">Bob and the third person, Carla, each have a chance to trim the piece, if they think it is worth more than 1/3 the value, or pass. In this case, Bob passes and Carla trims.</span> <span class="credit">OLENA SHMAHALO</span> </figcaption></figure></li><li class="wrapper item-3" role="list-item" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><figure class="figure"><img decoding="async" width="650" height="383" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_cake-last-diminisher-3-650x383.jpg" class="attachment-medium size-medium" alt="" loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="3131016" data-permalink="https://www.sciencenews.org/090923_cake-last-diminisher-3" data-orig-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_cake-last-diminisher-3.jpg" data-orig-size="681,401" data-comments-opened="0" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="090923_cake-last-diminisher-3" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="&lt;p>;The piece goes to whoever trimmed it last — in this case Carla. If both Bob and Carla had passed, Alice takes the piece.&lt;/p>;
" data-medium-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_cake-last-diminisher-3-650x383.jpg" data-large-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_cake-last-diminisher-3.jpg" /><figcaption class="gallery-caption"> <span class="caption">The piece goes to whoever trimmed it last — in this case Carla. If both Bob and Carla had passed, Alice takes the piece.</span> <span class="credit">OLENA SHMAHALO</span> </figcaption></figure></li><li class="wrapper item-4" role="list-item" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><figure class="figure"><img decoding="async" width="650" height="383" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_cake-last-diminisher-4-650x383.jpg" class="attachment-medium size-medium" alt="" loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="3131017" data-permalink="https://www.sciencenews.org/090923_cake-last-diminisher-4" data-orig-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_cake-last-diminisher-4.jpg" data-orig-size="681,401" data-comments-opened="0" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="090923_cake-last-diminisher-4" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="&lt;p>;In round 2, any trimmings are added back to the remaining cake, and then the “divider-chooser” method for two people is used. Alice cuts the cake into what she thinks are two fair slices.&lt;/p>;
" data-medium-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_cake-last-diminisher-4-650x383.jpg" data-large-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_cake-last-diminisher-4.jpg" /><figcaption class="gallery-caption"> <span class="caption">In round 2, any trimmings are added back to the remaining cake, and then the “divider-chooser” method for two people is used. Alice cuts the cake into what she thinks are two fair slices.</span> <span class="credit">OLENA SHMAHALO</span> </figcaption></figure></li><li class="wrapper item-5" role="list-item" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><figure class="figure"><img decoding="async" width="650" height="383" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_cake-last-diminisher-5-650x383.jpg" class="attachment-medium size-medium" alt="" loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="3131018" data-permalink="https://www.sciencenews.org/090923_cake-last-diminisher-5" data-orig-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_cake-last-diminisher-5.jpg" data-orig-size="681,401" data-comments-opened="0" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="090923_cake-last-diminisher-5" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="&lt;p>;Bob chooses his preferred slice. Alice gets the remaining slice. Everyone appears to be happy with their piece. But Carla, who exited the game early, could still think that Alice’s or Bob’s piece is better than hers.&lt;/p>;
" data-medium-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_cake-last-diminisher-5-650x383.jpg" data-large-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_cake-last-diminisher-5.jpg" /><figcaption class="gallery-caption"> <span class="caption">Bob chooses his preferred slice. Alice gets the remaining slice. Everyone appears to be happy with their piece. But Carla, who exited the game early, could still think that Alice&#39;s or Bob&#39;s piece is better than hers.</span> <span class="credit">OLENA SHMAHALO</span></figcaption></figure></li></ol></div></div><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Brams has called the last-diminisher method an elegant solution, and it guarantees that everyone judges their own piece to be at least as valuable as a fair share. But it&#39;s not perfect because it doesn&#39;t take envy into account. In both the lone-divider and last-diminisher approaches, a person who exits the game early may end up coveting a piece that is cut later in the game — even though they thought their piece was proportional. These algorithms are not what mathematicians call “envy-free,” which is another way to think about fairness.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> There is another practical limitation to the last-diminisher method: With enough players, the cake that remains in later rounds might end up broken apart by a lot of slicing — or even reduced to crumbs. It&#39;s easy to see how a partygoer might not value that as highly as a whole piece.</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Can cake cutting be free of envy?</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Since the debut of the last-diminisher method, cake cutting has fueled a small but mighty body of serious mathematics.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The 1960s brought a major step forward when mathematicians John Conway and John Selfridge, independently of each other, came up with a new cutting algorithm for three people. Unlike the work by Steinhaus and colleagues, the new recipe achieved both perceived proportionality and avoided any envy among the recipients.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> An envy-free solution, in which no one covets another person&#39;s piece, is easy to achieve, points out computer scientist Haris Aziz of the University of New South Wales in Sydney. Just throw the entire cake away. “If you don&#39;t give anything to anybody, that&#39;s envy-free,” he says.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> But if the cake lands in the rubbish bin, no one is happy. In Conway&#39;s and Selfridge&#39;s more pleasing scheme, Alice first divides the cake into three pieces she believes are of equal value. Then, Bob can trim one piece — at most — to create a two-way tie for the most valuable. (The trimmings are set aside.) Carla is left to choose among the three. Then the order reverses, and if Carla didn&#39;t choose the trimmed piece, Bob takes it. Alice gets the one that remains. The eaters then turn to the trimmings, following a similar iterative protocol of cutting, trimming and choosing.</p><div class="wp-block-sciencenews-content-sidebar" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><h3 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> How to divide cake with no envy</h3><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> In a version of cake cutting for three people, each person — Alice, Bob and Carla — are guaranteed to feel that their piece represents 1/3 the total value of the cake. The method, named for John Selfridge and John Conway, also ensures that none of the cake eaters will be envious of another person&#39;s piece. The Selfridge-Conway procedure has been extended for any number people, but the cutting can last a very long time. </p><div
	class="container"
	data-component="slideshow"
 style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><div class="controls-wrapper" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"></div><ol class="slides" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><li class="wrapper item-1" role="list-item" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><figure class="figure"><img decoding="async" width="650" height="383" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_cake-selfridge-conway-1-650x383.jpg" class="attachment-medium size-medium" alt="" loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="3131007" data-permalink="https://www.sciencenews.org/090923_cake-selfridge-conway-1" data-orig-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_cake-selfridge-conway-1.jpg" data-orig-size="681,401" data-comments-opened="0" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="090923_cake-selfridge-conway-1" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="&lt;p>;In round 1, the first person, Alice, cuts the cake into three pieces that she considers equal.&lt;/p>;
" data-medium-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_cake-selfridge-conway-1-650x383.jpg" data-large-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_cake-selfridge-conway-1.jpg" /><figcaption class="gallery-caption"> <span class="caption">In round 1, the first person, Alice, cuts the cake into three pieces that she considers equal.</span> <span class="credit">OLENA SHMAHALO</span> </figcaption></figure></li><li class="wrapper item-2" role="list-item" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><figure class="figure"><img decoding="async" width="650" height="383" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_cake-selfridge-conway-2-650x383.jpg" class="attachment-medium size-medium" alt="" loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="3131008" data-permalink="https://www.sciencenews.org/090923_cake-selfridge-conway-2" data-orig-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_cake-selfridge-conway-2.jpg" data-orig-size="681,401" data-comments-opened="0" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="090923_cake-selfridge-conway-2" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="&lt;p>;The second person, Bob, can either pass or trim one — and only one — of the pieces to make two pieces that are tied for the best. The trimmings are set aside.&lt;/p>;
" data-medium-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_cake-selfridge-conway-2-650x383.jpg" data-large-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_cake-selfridge-conway-2.jpg" /><figcaption class="gallery-caption"> <span class="caption">The second person, Bob, can either pass or trim one — and only one — of the pieces to make two pieces that are tied for the best. The trimmings are set aside.</span> <span class="credit">OLENA SHMAHALO</span> </figcaption></figure></li><li class="wrapper item-3" role="list-item" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><figure class="figure"><img decoding="async" width="650" height="383" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_cake-selfridge-conway-3-650x383.jpg" class="attachment-medium size-medium" alt="" loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="3131009" data-permalink="https://www.sciencenews.org/090923_cake-selfridge-conway-3" data-orig-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_cake-selfridge-conway-3.jpg" data-orig-size="681,401" data-comments-opened="0" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="090923_cake-selfridge-conway-3" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="&lt;p>;The third person, Carla, gets to pick first — getting her favorite piece. Bob goes next (taking the trimmed piece if Carla doesn’t, thus ensuring he gets one piece that he thought was tied for the best). Alice gets the remaining piece, one of her original pieces. &lt;/p>;
" data-medium-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_cake-selfridge-conway-3-650x383.jpg" data-large-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_cake-selfridge-conway-3.jpg" /><figcaption class="gallery-caption"> <span class="caption">The third person, Carla, gets to pick first — getting her favorite piece. Bob goes next (taking the trimmed piece if Carla doesn&#39;t, thus ensuring he gets one piece that he thought was tied for the best). Alice gets the remaining piece, one of her original pieces.</span> <span class="credit">OLENA SHMAHALO</span> </figcaption></figure></li><li class="wrapper item-4" role="list-item" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><figure class="figure"><img decoding="async" width="650" height="383" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_cake-selfridge-conway-4-650x383.jpg" class="attachment-medium size-medium" alt="" loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="3131010" data-permalink="https://www.sciencenews.org/090923_cake-selfridge-conway-4" data-orig-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_cake-selfridge-conway-4.jpg" data-orig-size="681,401" data-comments-opened="0" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="090923_cake-selfridge-conway-4" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="&lt;p>;In round 2, the trimmings are divided. Whoever between Bob and Carla got the untrimmed piece (in this case Carla) cuts the trim into three equally valuable pieces.&lt;/p>;
" data-medium-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_cake-selfridge-conway-4-650x383.jpg" data-large-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_cake-selfridge-conway-4.jpg" /><figcaption class="gallery-caption"> <span class="caption">In round 2, the trimmings are divided. Whoever between Bob and Carla got the untrimmed piece (in this case Carla) cuts the trim into three equally valuable pieces.</span> <span class="credit">OLENA SHMAHALO</span> </figcaption></figure></li><li class="wrapper item-5" role="list-item" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><figure class="figure"><img decoding="async" width="650" height="383" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_cake-selfridge-conway-5-650x383.jpg" class="attachment-medium size-medium" alt="" loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="3131011" data-permalink="https://www.sciencenews.org/090923_cake-selfridge-conway-5" data-orig-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_cake-selfridge-conway-5.jpg" data-orig-size="681,401" data-comments-opened="0" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="090923_cake-selfridge-conway-5" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="&lt;p>;Bob chooses first, getting his favorite piece. Alice, who thought her piece was preferable to the trimmed piece in the previous round, goes next. Carla ends up with one of the pieces she trimmed. This approach is free of envy because Bob got to pick first, Carla valued all the trims equally and Alice feels like any trim is a bonus, since she would have been happy with her original piece alone.&lt;/p>;
" data-medium-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_cake-selfridge-conway-5-650x383.jpg" data-large-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_cake-selfridge-conway-5.jpg" /><figcaption class="gallery-caption"> <span class="caption">Bob chooses first, getting his favorite piece. Alice, who thought her piece was preferable to the trimmed piece in the previous round, goes next. Carla ends up with one of the pieces she trimmed. This approach is free of envy because Bob got to pick first, Carla valued all the trims equally and Alice feels like any trim is a bonus, since she would have been happy with her original piece alone.</span> <span class="credit">OLENA SHMAHALO</span></figcaption></figure></li></ol></div></div><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Yet for decades more, an envy-free cake-cutting solution for any arbitrary number of eaters remained elusive. In the late 1980s, on his PBS television show <em>For All Practical Purposes: Introduction to Contemporary Mathematics</em> , mathematician Sol Garfunkel <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dS73L5YMZ_E&amp;list=PL9n195Q8MdMgGACoKTurcoXhB7xh7rbss&amp;index=12" target="_blank" rel="noopener">featured the unsolved cake-cutting problem</a> and related questions of fair division.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> But the problem wouldn&#39;t go unsolved for much longer. In 1995, Brams at NYU and Alan D. Taylor of Union College in Schenectady, NY, devised <a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/2974850" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a new procedure that cuts cake for four people</a> with <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/archive/formulas-fairness">no one envying anyone else</a> . “That was considered a breakthrough of sorts,” Brams says. It built on the “trimming” approach of Conway and Selfridge, running a similar procedure on all possible pairs of cake eaters. Brams and Taylor described how the procedure could be extended to any number of people.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The approach still had limitations. There was no guarantee of how many cuts it might take. “We showed in general that you could require three cuts or 3 million cuts,” Brams says. Or many, many more.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> A few years later, mathematicians Jack Robertson and William Webb of Washington State University in Pullman described a useful computation model that could be used to analyze how many steps, including cuts and evaluations, are required by an algorithm. Its calculations confirmed, for example, that no maximum number of cuts could be predicted for any algorithm known at that time that divided cake proportionally and without envy for any arbitrary number of players.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Over the next few decades, many mathematicians came to wonder whether an upper bound for envy-free cake cutting even existed. If not, in theory, cake cutting could go on forever. What&#39;s more, Procaccia says, no one had figured out the minimum, either.</p><figure class="wp-block-pullquote alignright"><blockquote style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> What mathematicians call the “serendipity of disagreement” gives rise to rich math.</p></blockquote></figure><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Is cake cutting infinite?</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Procaccia never actually set out to study cake cutting. In 2008, he was teaching a course on the mathematical foundations of artificial intelligence. One day, walking home after delivering a lecture on resource allocation and the Robertson-Webb model, he realized how he could find a lower bound — a minimum number of steps, including cuts — for envy-free cake cutting for any number of people. The lower bound he found was somewhere around n² steps, where n is the number of cake eaters.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> That would lead to his first paper on cake. Procaccia has a knack for giving mathematical papers catchy titles. The lower-bound paper, published in 2009, was titled “ <a href="https://dl.acm.org/doi/10.5555/1661445.1661484" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Thou shalt covet thy neighbor&#39;s cake</a> .” In 2010, he coauthored one called “ <a href="https://www.cs.huji.ac.il/~jeff/aaai10/02/AAAI10-137.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Truth, justice, and cake cutting</a> ,” which introduced the question of truthfulness — in addition to guaranteeing proportionality and removing envy. If a person hides their preferences during the cutting, someone may end up with an unequal share. It&#39;s “mathematically fascinating,” Procaccia says.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> As Procaccia continued in the field, he began thinking more about useful algorithms that could put insights from cake cutting — and the theory of fair division in general — to good use. One example: dividing rent.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The easiest way, of course, is to divide the total due by the number of inhabitants. But that ignores the “serendipity of disagreement.” One person might want a window, another might prefer the bigger closet. In 2014, Procaccia and colleagues designed a web-based tool called Spliddit that collected users&#39; preferences and produced mathematically fair ways to divide anything, from rent among roommates to possessions among divorcees.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The biggest recent breakthrough in cake cutting, Procaccia says, came from Aziz and computer scientist Simon Mackenzie, based in Sydney, who determined an upper bound on envy-free, proportional cake cutting. First, in 2015, the pair tackled the problem of how to share cake among four people. By borrowing ideas from Conway and Selfridge and from Brams and Taylor, the team devised an algorithm that produced an upper bound of 203 steps, which could include almost as many cuts. That&#39;s a lot but not too unreasonable.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> A year later, the team extended the approach to an arbitrary number of people, <a href="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/abstract/document/7782956" target="_blank" rel="noopener">reporting an algorithm with a finite number of cuts</a> for envy-free, proportional cake cutting. It was a potentially astronomical number of cuts, but it was finite — answering a long-standing question in the field.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Cake cutting for n people, Aziz and Mackenzie reported, could require as many as n^n^n^n^n^n operations. That&#39;s a totally unreasonable number. The maximum number of steps for five people would be around 2 x 10 <sup>2,180</sup> . That means five people cutting the cake billions of times per second for 100 trillion years might barely be getting started.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> However, Aziz says the algorithm can be adapted to a more reasonable, though still really big upper bound if the partygoers, for example, allow for a little cake to be left over. And it&#39;s still possible that mathematicians could bring that upper bound lower in the future. </p><figure class="wp-block-image alignwide size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1440" height="810" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_cake_cover.jpg" alt="Cartoon illustration shows four people around a cake with lots of dashed lines to indicate where one might cut. One person holds a knife and looks perplexed. Two people point to different sections, and one person holds frosting on their finger." class="wp-image-3131020" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_cake_cover.jpg 1440w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_cake_cover-680x383.jpg 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_cake_cover-800x450.jpg 800w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_cake_cover-330x186.jpg 330w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_cake_cover-768x432.jpg 768w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_cake_cover-1030x580.jpg 1030w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_cake_cover-1380x776.jpg 1380w" sizes="(max-width: 1440px) 100vw, 1440px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3131020"><p class="Default" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl">The cake-cutting problem asks: What methods for cutting a cake guarantee that everyone is happy with what they get?</p></span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3131020">MADELINE MCMAHON</span></figcaption></figure><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The cake-cutting problem endures</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Explorations into the question of how to fairly cut a cake aren&#39;t over. Inspired by Procaccia&#39;s 2010 paper on truthfulness, computer scientist Biaoshuai Tao of Shanghai Jiao Tong University investigated what happens <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2104.07387.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">when you try to account for dishonest cake eaters</a> . “If everyone knows how the cake is allocated, then I should get more if I tell the truth,” he says.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> But in some cases, dishonesty can yield an advantage. If Alice and Bob were to divide a cake, and Alice knew that Bob always preferred chocolate, she might knowingly divide the cake unequally so the smaller piece contained more chocolate. Then Bob would choose according to his preference, and Alice would get the larger piece.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> In his work, presented in July 2022 at the Association for Computing Machinery Conference on Economics and Computation, in Boulder, Colo., Tao found that truthfulness and proportionality are incompatible, making it impossible to construct a cake-cutting algorithm that strictly guarantees truthfulness, proportionality and no envy.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Practical applications for cake cutting also continue to abound. Klaus, in Lausanne, points to school choice as an example.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> A district with limited seats in certain schools has to balance the school board priorities — scores on entrance exams or geographic distribution, for example — with the preferences of parents to try to find a proportional solution with a fair value. “In the past, schools were just assigned … without asking people what they want,” Klaus says. “The school choice comes from the fact that the preferences of the parents or the kids would be taken into account.”</p><figure class="wp-block-pullquote alignleft"><blockquote style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Over time, cake cutting has evolved into a kind of mathematical sandbox, a constructive playground that brings together abstract proofs and intuitive applications.</p></blockquote></figure><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> And there are plenty of other real-world applications for questions of fair division. Brams has used ideas from cake cutting to study fair voting procedures. (To elect their leaders, at least four scientific societies, including the Mathematical Association of America, adopted an algorithm developed by him.)</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Procaccia has applied fair division algorithms to model food allocation. Aziz is exploring applications ranging from <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.00879.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">how to divvy up chores</a> or other tasks that can&#39;t be divided to how to best schedule doctors&#39; shifts in hospitals.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Others are studying fair allocation of goods that can&#39;t be cleanly divided. After a divorce, for instance, former partners might come to agreement on a fair split only if some items are taken out of consideration. These investigations include approaches that are close to envy-free if not mathematically perfect.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Even after decades of investigation, cake cutting isn&#39;t like a simple jigsaw puzzle with a well-defined solution. Instead, over time, it has evolved into a kind of mathematical sandbox, a constructive playground that brings together abstract proofs and intuitive applications. The more researchers explore it, the more there is to explore.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “I&#39;m interested in it now not only because it&#39;s beautiful in math,” Tao says, “but I still believe there&#39;s a lot to be done.”</p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_cake_opener-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="249140" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_cake_opener-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item></channel></rss>