<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/" xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/" xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"><channel><title> חדשות המדע </title><atom:link href="https://www.sciencenews.org/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org<description> עיתונאות עצמאית מאז 1921</description><lastbuilddate> שבת, 15 ביולי 2023 19:54:03 +0000</lastbuilddate><language> en-US</language><sy:updateperiod> מדי שעה</sy:updateperiod><sy:updatefrequency> 1</sy:updatefrequency><generator> https://wordpress.org/?v=6.2.2</generator><item><title> דגימות אסטרואידים ריוגו מפוזרים באבק כוכבים עתיק ממערכת השמש</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/ryugu-asteroid-stardust-old-space<dc:creator><![CDATA[Lisa Grossman]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Fri, 14 Jul 2023 18:00:00 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Astronomy]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3129687 </guid><description><![CDATA[Slivers of the asteroid appear to be from the fringes of the solar system and could reveal bits of the history of the sun and its planets.]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<p>דוגמאות של האסטרואיד Ryugu מכילות פיסות אבק כוכבים שקדמו להולדת מערכת השמש שלנו.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> נראה ששבבי חומר ריוגו, שנתפסו על ידי חללית Hayabusa2 היפנית, <a href="http://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/sciadv.adh1003" target="_blank" rel="noopener">מגיעים מהשוליים הקפואים של מערכת השמש</a> , ולא מהאסטרואיד עצמו, מדווחים מדענים ב-14 ביולי ב- <em>Science Advances</em> . שברים זרים אלה יכולים להאיר פרטים על ההיסטוריה של מערכת השמש.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> מציאת השברים הללו &quot;הוא באמת ייחודי&quot;, אומרת הקוסמוכימאית אן נגוין ממרכז החלל ג&#39;ונסון של נאס&quot;א ביוסטון. &quot;זה מראה לנו סוג חדש של חומר, אבל גם מספר לנו על הדינמיקה של חומר ממערכת השמש החיצונית.&quot;</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> החללית Hayabusa2 ביקרה באסטרואיד ב-2018 וב-2019, ואז <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/japan-hayabusa2-asteroid-dirt-sample-clues-early-solar-system">חזרה לכדור הארץ עם 5.4 גרם מסלע החלל ב-2020</a> ( <em>SN: 12/7/20</em> ). מדענים בחנו את הדגימות הללו במעבדה בדרכים שלא ניתן לעשות עם טלסקופים או אפילו חלליות, כמו לקבל מדידות מפורטות של הרכב כימי.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> עד כה, בדיקות אלו הראו כי ריוגו עשיר בפחמן, שהוא עשוי מאותו חומר כמו כמה מהמטאוריטים הנדירים ביותר שנמצאו על פני כדור הארץ, ושהוא <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/asteroid-ryugu-ryugu-hayabusa2-meteorite-sample-carbonaceous-chondrite">השתנה על ידי מים</a> בשלב מסוים בעברו ( <em>SN: 6/9 /22</em> ). מדענים חושבים ש-Ryugu נוצר מהפסולת של אסטרואיד גדול יותר, שהתפרק בהתנגשות והיווצר מחדש לערימת <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/ryugu-came-two-other-asteroids">הריסות רופפת</a> ( <em>SN: 3/20/19</em> ).</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> נגוין, לעומת זאת, חיפש משהו אחר. &quot;המיקוד שלי במחקר הוא גרגירים פרה-סולריים&quot;, כתמי חומר זעירים <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/ancient-meteorite-stardust-oldest-ever-examined-lab">שנוצרו מאפר של כוכבים גוססים</a> , היא אומרת ( <em>SN: 1/13/20</em> ). &quot;חיפשתי אחריהם.&quot; הגרגרים העדינים האלה מכילים איזוטופים שונים - אטומים של יסוד שיש להם מספר שונה של נויטרונים - מאלה שנוצרו על ידי השמש, מסגירים את מקורותיהם החייזריים.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Nguyen ועמיתיה בחנו שתי דגימות של Ryugu, כל אחת בגודל של פחות ממילימטר. לאחר מכן הם בחרו רסיסים זעירים של סלע, ​​ברוחב 50 עד 200 מיקרומטר, הנקראים קלסטים, שבלטו משאר מדגם ריוגו.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> באמצעות מיקרוסקופים סורקים של אלקטרונים וטכניקות הדמיה אחרות, Nguyen ועמיתיו מצאו כי שניים מהסוגים שונים מבחינה כימית משאר ריוגו, עם תכולת חמצן, מגנזיום וסיליקון נמוכה יותר, וכמויות גדולות יותר של ברזל וגופרית. </p><figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" width="680" height="766" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071423_LG_ryugu_inline-1-mobile.jpg" alt="תמונות מיקרוסקופ אלקטרוני של רסיס של חומר מערכת השמש (מתואר בלבן) בדגימה של האסטרואיד Ryugu מראות שהחומר שונה משאר האסטרואיד. הצבעים השונים מבליטים אלמנטים שונים בדגימה: חמצן (מגנטה), מגנזיום (ירוק), סיליקון (תכלת), ברזל (כחול כהה) וגופרית (צהוב). הרסיסים מכילים גם גרגרי סיליקטים (חצים לבנים) המגיעים מחוץ למערכת השמש." class="wp-image-3129690" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071423_LG_ryugu_inline-1-mobile.jpg 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071423_LG_ryugu_inline-1-mobile-340x383.jpg 340w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071423_LG_ryugu_inline-1-mobile-399x450.jpg 399w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071423_LG_ryugu_inline-1-mobile-165x186.jpg 165w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071423_LG_ryugu_inline-1-mobile-515x580.jpg 515w" sizes="(max-width: 680px) 100vw, 680px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3129690">תמונות מיקרוסקופ אלקטרוני של רסיס של חומר מערכת השמש (מתואר בלבן) בדגימה של האסטרואיד Ryugu מראות שהחומר שונה משאר האסטרואיד. הצבעים השונים מבליטים אלמנטים שונים בדגימה: חמצן (מגנטה), מגנזיום (ירוק), סיליקון (תכלת), ברזל (כחול כהה) וגופרית (צהוב). הרסיסים מכילים גם גרגרי סיליקטים (חצים לבנים) המגיעים מחוץ למערכת השמש.</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3129690">A. Nguyen <em>et al</em> / <em>Science Advances</em> 2023</span></figcaption></figure><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> כמו כן יש בקלאס ריכוזים גבוהים בהרבה של גרגירים פרה-סולריים מאשר שאר החומר ריוגו. הדגנים מכילים סיליקון קרביד, אשר נהרס בקלות על ידי מים, בתוספת שפע נוסף של חומרים אורגניים.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> זה אומר שהגרגרים לא יכלו להיות חלק מגוף האם של ריוגו, אשר השתנה בהרחבה על ידי מים. החוקרים חושבים שהגרגרים היו חתיכות של שביט שנוצרו בחגורת קויפר של מערכת השמש החיצונית, שם התנאים היו קרירים ויבשים. ואז התפזרו הגרגירים על ההריסות שיצרו ריוגו מתישהו בין הרס האסטרואיד המקורי להיווצרות ערימת ההריסות.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> &quot;בין האירועים האלה, זה קצת אסף כמה חברים אחרים שהגיעו מגופים אחרים, מחלקים שונים של מערכת השמש&quot;, אומר נגוין. עדיין לא ברור כיצד חומר ממערכת השמש החיצונית מצא את דרכו ל-Ryugu. אולי האסטרואיד נוצר רחוק יותר מהשמש - ומכאן, קרוב יותר לחגורת קויפר - ממה שהוא היום. &quot;מעניין לדמיין איך האסטרואיד הזה נוצר ומה הוא אסף לאורך הדרך.&quot;</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> התגלית &quot;מרגשת מאוד&quot;, אומר הקוסמוכימאי פיליפ הק ממוזיאון פילד לתולדות הטבע בשיקגו, שלא היה מעורב בעבודה החדשה. &quot;המעמדות האלה ששולבו ב-Ryugu לאחר היווצרותם, הם בעלי ערך רב. אני חושב שהם אפילו יותר יקרים מדגימת ריוגו עצמה.&quot;</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> המחזורים יכולים לחשוף ממה עשויים המרכיבים ללא שינוי שיצרו את מערכת השמש. חשבו על הדיסק שיצר את כוכבי הלכת כבצק לחם, אומר Heck. לאחר שהבצק מעורבב היטב, קשה לדעת מה נכנס לתוכו. קלסטים כמו אלה שבדגימת ריוגו הם כמו חתיכות קמח לא מעורבבות ששרדו בשלמותן בכיכר האחרונה, הוא אומר - לא טעים, אבל מאוד אינפורמטיבי.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> &quot;אם אנחנו רוצים להבין את המרכיבים שמהם נוצרה מערכת השמש, המרכיבים המקוריים, אנחנו צריכים למצוא את ההרכבים הנדירים מאוד, ללא שינוי&quot;, אומר הק. &quot;זה אחד מהם.&quot;</p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071423_LG_ryugu_feat-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="240586" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071423_LG_ryugu_feat-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title> המוח של אליזה ג&#39;י מדהים. חסר לו גם נתח גדול</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/brain-missing-chunk-neuroplasticity<dc:creator><![CDATA[Meghan Rosen]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Fri, 14 Jul 2023 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Neuroscience]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3129520 </guid><description><![CDATA[A new project explores interesting brains to better understand neural flexibility.]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<p><em><strong>הערת העורך</strong> : רוב משתתפי פרויקט המוח המעניין המופיעים בסיפור זה משתמשים בצורות מקוצרות של שמם ו/או שמות בדויים כדי להגן על פרטיותם.</em></p><hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity is-style-default" /><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> לעולם לא תנחשו שלאליזה ג&#39;י יש חור שחור במוח.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> תפגשו אותה ברחוב, ואי אפשר יהיה לדעת שחסר לה גוש של רקמה עצבית בערך בגודל של אגרוף קטן.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> להסתכל על סריקות המוח שלה זה סיפור אחר. זה כאילו מישהו הפיל בקבוק דיו. החושך בריכה בתוך הגולגולת שלה ליד אוזנה השמאלית, שלולית של שחור מפלצתי. בתוך הכתם, אין חומר לבן או חומר אפור, אין כלי דם או רקמה כלל.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> אליזה אומרת שלא צריך להיות נוירוכירורג כדי לזהות מה שונה במוח שלה: &quot;חסרה קטע צופר גדול!&quot; </p><div class="wp-block-image  has-alignleft" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><figure class="alignleft size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="438" height="636" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_interesting-brains_REV-2.gif" alt="גיף המראה את סריקת ה-MRI של אליזה ג&#39;י ואת החלק הגדול של מוחה חסר בצד שמאל." class="wp-image-3129547" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3129547">בהשקפה זו של מוחה של אליזה ג&#39;י, מדענים ערמו פרוסות MRI שהולכות מהחלק התחתון של המוח לחלק העליון. בצד שמאל, האונה הטמפורלית החסרה מופיעה כחור שחור גדול שמופיע ולאחר מכן נעלם כשהסריקות נעות למעלה דרך המוח.</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3129547">באדיבות מעבדת פדורנקו</span></figcaption></figure></div><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> מדענים לא יכולים לומר בדיוק איך זה קרה. ייתכן שלפני זמן מה, אולי בגלל שבץ מוחי לפני או זמן קצר לאחר הלידה, חלק מהמוח של אליזה מת ואז נעלם בסופו של דבר, והותיר אחריו רק נוזל - רקמת מוח שהוחלפה לריק מלא נוזלים. גם לאחותה יש כזה.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> אליזה ואחותה, מרתה מ&#39;, שאינן משתמשות בשמם המלא כדי לשמור על האנונימיות שלהן, נראות ומתנהגות רגילות לחלוטין. אבל לכל אחד חסרה רוב האונה הטמפורלית, וכל אחד בחצי כדור אחר. לאליס חסר גם חלק מגזע המוח שלה. הנשים הן שתיים מהן יודעות כמה אנשים חיים את חייהם ללא מבני מוח בדרך כלל נחשבים חיוניים.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> מרתה, כיום בת 59, לא ידעה שהמוח שלה שונה עד שהיתה נערה. אליזה, שתמלא השנה 61, גילתה את זה בבית הספר לתארים מתקדמים. שתי אחיות. שני מוחות. שני חורים שחורים. כשהצוות של מדען המוח הקוגניטיבי של MIT, אוולינה פדורנקו, למד לראשונה על הצמד, &quot;כולנו די מפוצצים&quot;, היא אומרת.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> אליזה שלחה לפדורנקו בדוא&quot;ל את תמונות המוח שלה ב-2016, עשרות שנים לאחר גילוי החלל. היא קראה מאמר על מחקר מדעי המוח ב-MIT והיתה סקרנית אם מדענים יהיו מעוניינים. &quot;היא אמרה, &#39;חסרה לי האונה הטמפורלית השמאלית שלי. אתה רוצה ללמוד אותי?&#39; &quot;נזכרת פדורנקו.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> האונה הטמפורלית השמאלית נחשבת בדרך כלל חיונית לדיבור ולשפה, ופדורנקו, שהוכשר כחוקר שפה, הסתקרן. המעבדה שלה לא חקרה אנשים כמו אליזה לפני כן, אבל &quot;אני מדענית מאוד הרפתקנית&quot;, היא אומרת. אז הצוות שלה הביא את אליזה למעבדה לבדיקות.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> פדורנקו לא ידעה זאת בזמנו, אבל המחקרים הראשונים הללו יזינו מערבולת שתשנה את מהלך המחקר שלה. הממצאים של הצוות שלה יציתו את תשומת הלב התקשורתית, ויגררו עוד יותר אנשים לשלוח סריקות מוח שלהם. מה שהתחיל כמקרה בודד הגיע כעת לכדור שלג <a href="https://web.mit.edu/~interestingbrains/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">לפרויקט המוח המעניין</a> .</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> עד סוף הסתיו הזה, הפרויקט יסרוק ככל הנראה יותר מ-40 אנשים עם מוח לא טיפוסי. במקרים רבים חסרים למשתתפים אזורים שלמים במוח, וכמו אליזה, הם לא גילו את זה עד שהם היו בוגרים.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> זה עשוי להיות מחווה לגמישות המוח - יכולתו לשנות ולהסתגל - כולל היתירות שלו, אומר פדורנקו. כמו מחוללי גיבוי, אזורים מסוימים במוח יכולים להיכנס להילוך אם אחרים נפצעים. מבט מקרוב על מקרים כמו של אליזה יכול לעזור למדענים להבין טוב יותר כיצד המוח שלנו מתמודד עם נזק ומדוע סוגים מסוימים גרועים יותר מאחרים.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> לעת עתה, הצוות של פדורנקו מתמקד בשפה ובהיבטים של קוגניציה ברמה גבוהה, כמו יכולתו של אדם להגיב כללי. אבל המאמץ יכול גם להציע תובנות לגבי פעולת המוח בצורה רחבה יותר ואולי יום אחד ייתן לרופאים תחושה טובה יותר לאילו תוצאות עשוי לצפות אדם עם פגיעה מוחית.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> זה מה שאליס ופדורנקו מקווים, בכל מקרה. לפני שהתחילה לעבוד עם צוות MIT, אליזה אומרת, &quot;הרגשתי שהמוח שלי הוא משהו שצריך &#39;לרפא&#39; ולא לחגוג אותו&quot;. לא עוד. בימים אלה, יש מילה אחרת שעולה במוחה של אליזה כשהיא חושבת על המוח שלה. &quot;זה מדהים,&quot; היא אומרת.</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> MRI מעלה מוחות לא טיפוסיים</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> אליזה למדה לראשונה על המוח הלא טיפוסי שלה לאחר סריקת MRI בסתיו 1987. היא הייתה בת 25 ובשנה הראשונה ללימודי תואר ראשון בוושינגטון די.סי., קוראת נלהבת ומזדמנת עם מחט וחוט.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> בפגישה עם נוירולוג בבית החולים האוניברסיטאי ג&#39;ורג&#39; וושינגטון, אליזה - שאובחנה בעבר עם אפילפסיה למרות שמעולם לא קיבלה התקף - חשה בעיקר שעמום מהרופא ומהדייר המלווה. לא הודיעו לה הרבה, היא אומרת.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> התחושה הזו התנדפה כשאליזה חזרה על התוצאות שלה. עכשיו היא קיבלה את מלוא תשומת הלב של הרופאים. הם רכנו קדימה בכיסאותיהם, מרפקים על הברכיים, סנטרים בידיים, עיניים ממוקדות בלייזר על אליזה. &quot;איך אתה מרגיש?&quot; היא זוכרת שהם שואלים. היא הרגישה כמו דגימת מעבדה - כמו צפרדע הם מזנקים עם אלקטרודות, היא אומרת.</p><figure class="wp-block-pullquote alignright"><blockquote style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> &quot;הרגשתי שהמוח שלי הוא משהו שצריך &#39;לרפא&#39; במקום לחגוג אותו&quot;.</p> <cite>אליזה ג.</cite></blockquote></figure><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> מה שהרופאים ראו בסריקת המוח שלה, כמובן, היה החור השחור הבוטה הזה. כאשר מתגלה אצל תינוקות, זה סוג הנגע שגורם להורים לפחד מהגרוע מכל. אצל מבוגרים, שבץ בהמיספרה השמאלית יכול לגנוב את היכולת של אנשים לקרוא ולכתוב ולערבב את הדיבור שלהם. המשמעות של מילים יכולה לחמוק פתאום מהמוח, כאילו מחק קרצף את המילון המנטלי של אדם. הרופאים של אליזה, היא זוכרת, הופתעו שיש לה יותר מאוצר מילים של כיתה ה&#39;.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> באותו זמן, אליזה הרגישה בחילה ומפוחדת. היא לא ידעה אם הנגע גדל, אם הוא מבשר על מחלת אלצהיימר מוקדמת או שהוא עומד &quot;להתפוצץ לי בראש&quot;, היא אומרת. סריקת מעקב שישה חודשים לאחר מכן הפיגה את חששותיה. הסריקה נראתה זהה לזו הראשונה. החור השחור של המוח שלה לא התרחב.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> אליזה מעולם לא חזרה לרופאים האלה, אבל היא כן קיבלה חוות דעת שנייה באותו קיץ מהנוירוכירורג של אחותה. הוא ניתח את מרתה כשהייתה בת 17, לאחר שהבחינה בבעיות ראייה. עיקר האונה הטמפורלית הימנית שלה נעלמה, אולי בגלל שבץ ברחם. הצטברות נוזלים במוח נלחצה על עצבי עיניה, והפריעה לראייתה. &quot;הם רוקנו את זה, ואני המשכתי בדרכי העליזה&quot;, אומרת מרתה. מאז לא ניקזה את האזור.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> הרופאה של מרתה הסתכלה בסריקה של אליזה ואמרה לה שככל שבדיקות ה-MRI הופכות נפוצות יותר, הרופאים מוצאים אנשים אחרים עם מוח שחורג מהנורמה. &quot;הוא אמר, &#39;אנחנו רואים יותר ויותר סטיות, ויש לך אחת&#39;&quot;, היא נזכרת. </p><figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="680" height="450" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_interesting-brains_inline-1-MM.jpg" alt="סריקת MRI של המוח של מרתה מ&#39; עם קטע כהה גדול בצד ימין." class="wp-image-3129526" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_interesting-brains_inline-1-MM.jpg 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_interesting-brains_inline-1-MM-579x383.jpg 579w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_interesting-brains_inline-1-MM-281x186.jpg 281w" sizes="(max-width: 680px) 100vw, 680px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3129526">למרתה מ&#39;, אחותה הצעירה של אליזה ג&#39;, חסרה גם רוב האונה הטמפורלית, אבל בצד ימין של המוח - תמונת מראה כמעט של הנגע של אליזה. ייתכן שמארתה עברה שבץ בזמן שהייתה ברחם. מאוחר יותר, הצטברות נוזלים במוח נלחצה על עצבי עיניה, והפריעה לראייתה. כמו כל משתתפי פרויקט המוחות המעניינים שנבדקו עד כה, מרתה משיגה ציונים בממוצע או מעל הממוצע במשימות שפה ומשימות קוגניטיביות.</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3129526">באדיבות מעבדת פדורנקו</span></figcaption></figure><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> פרויקט המוחות המעניינים נולד</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> כשאליזה ופדורנקו נפגשו לראשונה, פדורנקו התעניין כיצד אזורי שפה מתחברים כאשר חלק מרקמה חיונית חסר. התוכנית שלה הייתה להציץ לתוך ראשה של אליזה באמצעות MRI פונקציונלי, טכניקה שעוקבת אחר זרימת הדם במוח. MRI פונקציונלי מאפשר למדענים לראות אילו חלקים במוח פעילים בזמן שאדם מבצע משימה מסוימת.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> עבור אליזה, זה אומר לשכב פסל בשקט בתוך הצינור הענק של מכונת MRI בזמן שציוד מסתובב סביבה. בהתאם למשימה, אליזה עשויה להסתכל או להקשיב למילים, משפטים וסיפורים או לראות בעיות מתמטיות או חידות מרחביות. מדי פעם, היא תלחץ על כפתור כדי שהצוות ידע שהיא נשארת ערנית.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> מחוץ לצינור, החוקרים בדקו גם את אוצר המילים, את כישורי הקריאה והכתיבה ואת האינטליגנציה של אליזה. היא השיגה ציון קרוב לפסגה של כל מבחן שפה שעשתה. &quot;יכולתי כנראה להשתלט על העולם אם היה לי את כל המוח שלי&quot;, מתבדחת אליזה.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> הסריקה הראשונה של אליזה עם הצוות של פדורנקו חשפה פעילות שפה בצד ימין של המוח, <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0028393222000434?via%3Dihub" target="_blank" rel="noopener">כך דיווח הצוות ב-2022 ב- <em>Neuropsychologia</em></a> . הסטת פונקציות ימינה היא טריק אחד שהמוח שלנו משתמש בו כדי להתמודד עם נזק בצד שמאל, משהו שמדענים אחרים דיווחו בעבר, אומר פדורנקו.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> הצוות תהה אם האונה הקדמית השמאלית של אליזה עשויה להידבק גם היא. כן, לאליס חסרה האונה הטמפורלית השמאלית שלה, אומר פדורנקו, אבל האונה הקדמית השמאלית שלה - שם שוכנת בדרך כלל השפה - שלמה לחלוטין. &quot;יש שם שפה כלשהי?&quot; שאל פדורנקו.</p><figure class="wp-block-pullquote alignleft"><blockquote style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> &quot;יכולתי כנראה להשתלט על העולם אם היה לי את כל המוח שלי.&quot;</p> <cite>אליזה ג.</cite></blockquote></figure><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> אבל האונה הזו לא הראתה אזורים המגיבים לשפה בכלל. הממצאים מרמזים על סדר פעולות עצבי להתפתחות השפה: ללא האונה הטמפורלית השמאלית של אליזה, אזורי השפה באונה הקדמית השמאלית שלה לא יכלו להתחבר.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> הצוות של פדורנקו גם חשף שלאליזה חסר לחלוטין אזור טיפוסי לקריאת מילים. הצוות חשב שאזור כזה עשוי להופיע באונה הטמפורלית הימנית של אליזה. במקום זאת, נראה שהיא נכנסת לרשת של נוירונים ברחבי קליפת המוח החזותית, <a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/02643294.2023.2164923" target="_blank" rel="noopener">כך דיווח הצוות השנה ב- <em>Cognitive Neuropsychology</em></a> .</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> &quot;מסתבר שאתה יכול להיות בעל מכונות קריאה חזותיות פונקציונליות במוח שלך שמיושמות בצורה אחרת&quot;, אומר פדורנקו. אליזה עשויה להיות הדוגמה הראשונה שדווחה לכך.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> הממצאים ממוחה של אליזה משכו את תשומת ליבו של כתב ב- <em>Wired</em> שכתב מאמר בשנה שעברה עם כותרת תופסת עין: &quot; <a href="https://www.wired.com/story/she-was-missing-a-chunk-of-her-brain-it-didnt-matter/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">היא חסרה חלק מהמוח שלה. זה לא היה משנה</a> .&quot; ואז המיילים התחילו לזרום.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> בבוקר שלאחר פרסום הסיפור <em>Wired</em> , תיבת הדואר הנכנס של פדורנקו &quot;התמלאה בתמונות מוח מגניבות - מוחות חסרים כל מיני חלקים גדולים&quot;, היא אומרת. במקרים רבים, אנשים גילו על המוח הלא טיפוסי שלהם בטעות. פדורנקו שמע סיפורים על אנשים עם מתח צוואר שנכנסים לבדיקת MRI ומגלים שחסר להם רוב האונה הקדמית הימנית שלהם. אחרים, כמו הלן סנטורו, ידעו על נגעי המוח שלהם מאז שהיו קטנים.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> סנטורו, עיתונאית מדע שהגיעה אל פדורנקו לאחר שקראה את הסיפור <em>Wired</em> , עברה שבץ לפני הלידה וחסרה לה את האונה הטמפורלית השמאלית, כמו אליזה. הרופאים אמרו שסנטורו לעולם לא ידבר ויהיה צורך למסד אותו. &quot;אבל חודש אחרי חודש הפתעתי את המומחים, כשפגשתי את כל אבני הדרך האופייניות לילדים בגילי&quot;, היא כתבה בספטמבר האחרון <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/09/04/science/brain-language-research.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">במאמר על הניסיון שלה</a> עבור <em>הניו יורק טיימס</em> .</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> עדיין לא ברור מדוע פציעות מוח מסוימות גולשות מבלי לשים לב, בעוד שאחרות דורשות תשומת לב, אומרת מדענית הדמיית המוח הלן קרלסון. הצוות שלה באוניברסיטת קלגרי בקנדה עבד עם ילדים שעברו שבץ מוקדם בקליפת המוח המוטורית, אזור המוח שאחראי לתנועה.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> לחלק מהילדים עם פציעות מוח גדולות יש חולשה קלה בלבד בצד אחד של הגוף. לאחרים עם רק &quot;לחישה קטנה של כתם ב-MRI שלהם... יש מוגבלויות די עמוקות במשך כל חייהם&quot;, אומר קרלסון.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> חוסר ההתאמה הזה יכול להיות נכון גם לגבי קשיים אחרים, כולל בעיות בשפה ובנימוקים כלליים - וזו אחת מכמה תעלומות שפרויקט המוח המעניין רודף אחריו.</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> איך המוח מסתגל</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> נכון ל-30 במאי, פרויקט המוח המעניין סרק את מוחותיהם של 30 אנשים. לחלקם יש חורים באונות הקדמיות או הטמפורליות; אחרים חסרים חלקים מהמוח הקטן שלהם, מבנה מוחי המעורב באיזון ובתנועה. למשתתפים אחרים יש חומר מוחי שנדחס לצידי הגולגולת שלהם; סריקות מראות חללים שנראים כאילו התפוצצו ממרכז המוח.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> הסדרים לא טיפוסיים אלה יכולים לנבוע מציסטות, ניתוח, שבץ או הצטברות נוזלים עודפת במוח. חלקם יכולים לגרום למוח עם הרבה פחות רקמה עצבית מהרגיל - ולפעמים השינוי יכול להיות פתאומי. מה קורה כשהמוח צריך לבצע את אותן עבודות אבל בחלל קטן בהרבה, שואל פדורנקו. &quot;מהם הפתרונות שהמוח שלנו מציג כשפתאום יש הרבה פחות דשא לעבוד איתו?&quot;</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> קהילה של מדענים כבר חפרה כמה תשובות על ידי מחקר של ילדים שעברו שבץ לידה. בחלק מהמקרים הללו, במהלך לידת התינוק, או בשבועות שלפני ואחרי, זרימת הדם במוח עלולה לנתק לחלוטין, רקמות מורעבות של חמצן.</p><figure class="wp-block-pullquote alignright"><blockquote style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> &quot;המוח שלי מיוחד, ייחודי ומעניין&quot;.</p> <cite>אליזה ג.</cite></blockquote></figure><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> המוח יכול להסתגל לפציעה הזו, אבל זה לא גוש חימר עם פוטנציאל אינסופי. &quot;כולם חושבים, &#39;הו, המוח הוא פלסטיק אינסופי&#39;&quot;, אומרת אליסה ניופורט, מדעית מוח קוגניטיבית מאוניברסיטת ג&#39;ורג&#39;טאון בוושינגטון, אבל הוא נוטה להתמודד עם נזק בדרכים מוגדרות.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> ניופורט עבדה לאחרונה עם קבוצה של 15 ילדים ומבוגרים צעירים שכולם סבלו מאירוע מוחי סביב הלידה שגרם לנזק להמיספרה השמאלית באזור שמעבד מילים ומשפטים. כמעט בכל מקרה, מוחותיהם של המשתתפים העבירו את השפה לאותם נקודות בהמיספרה הימנית, כך דיווחו ניופורט ועמיתיו <a href="https://www.pnas.org/doi/10.1073/pnas.2207293119" target="_blank" rel="noopener">בשנת 2022 ב- <em>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</em></a> .</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> זה כאילו אזור השפה התהפך משמאל לימין, &quot;בדיוק תמונת המראה של איך נראים מוחות רגילים טיפוסיים&quot;, היא אומרת. דפוס זה מצביע על כך שאזורים מסוימים במוח יכולים לשמש כחותרים לתפקוד השפה. </p><div
	class="container"
	data-component="slideshow"
 style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><div class="controls-wrapper" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"></div><ol class="slides" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><li class="wrapper item-1" role="list-item" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><figure class="figure"><img decoding="async" width="579" height="383" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_interesting-brains_inline-2-ES-579x383.jpg" class="attachment-medium size-medium" alt="סריקת MRI של מוחו של E.S. עם כתמים כהים אחד גדול ושני קטן יותר באמצע המוח." loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="3129527" data-permalink="https://www.sciencenews.org/071523_interesting-brains_inline-2-es" data-orig-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_interesting-brains_inline-2-ES.jpg" data-orig-size="680,450" data-comments-opened="0" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="071523_interesting-brains_inline-2-ES" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="&lt;p>;E.S.’s atypical brain may stem from an assortment of issues, including an arachnoid cyst, a fluid-filled sac that forms between the brain and one of its membranes. Hydrocephalus, when excess fluid collects in the middle parts of the brain, may also have compressed E.S.’s brain tissues. On top of that, E.S. is missing most of the tissue that connects the left and right hemispheres, a condition called agenesis of the corpus callosum. In their daily life, E.S. is a professor and researcher in the field of speech-language pathology.&lt;/p>;
" data-medium-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_interesting-brains_inline-2-ES-579x383.jpg" data-large-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_interesting-brains_inline-2-ES.jpg" /><figcaption class="gallery-caption"> <span class="caption">המוח הלא טיפוסי של ES עשוי לנבוע ממגוון בעיות, כולל ציסטה ארכנואידית, שק מלא נוזל שנוצר בין המוח לאחד מהקרומים שלו. הידרוצפלוס, כאשר נוזל עודף נאסף בחלקים האמצעיים של המוח, עשוי גם לדחוס את רקמות המוח של ES. נוסף על כך, ל-ES חסרה רוב הרקמה המחברת בין ההמיספרה השמאלית והימנית, מצב הנקרא אגנזיס של הקורפוס קלוסום. בחיי היומיום שלהם, ES הוא פרופסור וחוקר בתחום פתולוגיית שפת הדיבור.</span> <span class="credit">באדיבות מעבדת פדורנקו</span> </figcaption></figure></li><li class="wrapper item-2" role="list-item" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><figure class="figure"><img decoding="async" width="579" height="383" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_interesting-brains_inline-3-KV-579x383.jpg" class="attachment-medium size-medium" alt="תמונה של סריקת MRI עם אזור שחור גדול באמצע מוחו של K.V. בצורת לב." loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="3129528" data-permalink="https://www.sciencenews.org/071523_interesting-brains_inline-3-kv" data-orig-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_interesting-brains_inline-3-KV.jpg" data-orig-size="680,450" data-comments-opened="0" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="071523_interesting-brains_inline-3-KV" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="&lt;p>;Hydrocephalus has left its mark in K.V.’s brain, pushing neural tissue toward the sides of their skull and pressing the cortex thin. K.V.’s ventricles, cavities filled with cerebrospinal fluid (center), are larger than most people’s and form a fluid-filled void in the center of the brain. K.V. makes their living as a writer.&lt;/p>;
" data-medium-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_interesting-brains_inline-3-KV-579x383.jpg" data-large-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_interesting-brains_inline-3-KV.jpg" /><figcaption class="gallery-caption"> <span class="caption">הידרוצפלוס הותיר את חותמו במוחו של KV, דוחף רקמה עצבית לצידי הגולגולת שלהם ודוחף את קליפת המוח דק. החדרים של KV, חללים מלאים בנוזל השדרה (מרכז), גדולים יותר משל רוב האנשים ויוצרים חלל מלא בנוזל במרכז המוח. KV מתפרנסים כסופרים.</span> <span class="credit">באדיבות מעבדת פדורנקו</span> </figcaption></figure></li><li class="wrapper item-3" role="list-item" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><figure class="figure"><img decoding="async" width="579" height="383" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_interesting-brains_inline-4-GC-579x383.jpg" class="attachment-medium size-medium" alt="תמונה של סריקת MRI של מוחו של G.C מראה קטע כהה גדול מאוד בצד שמאל והמוח נדחף ימינה." loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="3129529" data-permalink="https://www.sciencenews.org/071523_interesting-brains_inline-4-gc" data-orig-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_interesting-brains_inline-4-GC.jpg" data-orig-size="680,450" data-comments-opened="0" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="071523_interesting-brains_inline-4-GC" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="&lt;p>;Scientists think that G.C. may have developed a cyst in their left hemisphere early in life. That could have compressed their left frontal, temporal and parietal lobes. Though G.C.’s language areas are squished, the cyst does not seem to have affected their daily life. G.C. is a speech-language pathologist.&lt;/p>;
" data-medium-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_interesting-brains_inline-4-GC-579x383.jpg" data-large-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_interesting-brains_inline-4-GC.jpg" /><figcaption class="gallery-caption"> <span class="caption">מדענים חושבים שייתכן ש-GC פיתחה ציסטה בהמיספרה השמאלית שלהם בשלב מוקדם בחיים. זה יכול היה לדחוס את האונות הקדמיות, הטמפורליות והפריאטליות השמאלית שלהם. למרות שאזורי השפה של GC מעוכים, נראה שהציסטה לא השפיעה על חיי היומיום שלהם. GC הוא פתולוג בדיבור.</span> <span class="credit">באדיבות מעבדת פדורנקו</span></figcaption></figure></li></ol></div><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> אבל עדיין יש יקום של שאלות נוספות, אומר פדורנקו. היא סקרנית אם תפקודי המוח יכולים לחפוף, ולחלוק את אותה מכונות קליפת המוח במוח לא טיפוסי, כאשר אחרת אולי היו מקימים חנות במקומות שונים. והמיספרה שמאלית פגומה לא תמיד אומרת שהשפה זזה ימינה. לפעמים תפקוד השפה נשאר מאחור, שורד בשולי האזור הפגוע, אומר פדורנקו. &quot;אף אחד לא יודע למה זה קורה.&quot;</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> קרלסון ועמיתיו דיווחו על סוג זה של הסתגלות בשנת <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0887899420302770" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2020 ב- <em>Pediatric Neurology</em></a> . הצוות חקר חולי שבץ צעירים שעברו אירוע מוחי סביב הלידה שפגע בקורטקס המוטורי. קרלסון אומר שפרויקט המוחות המעניינים הוא בעל ערך מכיוון שהוא יכול לספר למדענים יותר על פלסטיות במוח ברמה האישית - כיצד המוח של אדם ספציפי הסתגל לפציעה.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> לא המוח של כל אדם מסוגל לחזור אחורה. מה שמדענים לומדים מהפרויקט, יחד עם הדמיה עצבית פרטנית, יכול לעזור בפרוגנוזה, ואולי גם בשיקום. &quot;אולי אם נוכל להתאים אפשרויות התערבות למוח אינדיבידואלי, הן עשויות להיות יעילות יותר&quot;, אומר קרלסון.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> השגת תוצאות תיקח זמן. הצוות של פדורנקו מלהטט כעת בלוגיסטיקה ניסיוני, כולל סריקת משתתף חדש כל שבוע עד שבועיים, ביצוע בדיקות התנהגותיות וניתוח נתונים. ובכל זאת, הם רואים כמה תוצאות מעניינות, אומר פדורנקו, ומקווים להגיש מאמר בקיץ הקרוב.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> היא מקווה שהפרויקט יוכל להציג את מגוון הפתרונות שהמוח שלנו יכול להשתמש, במקרים מסוימים, כדי להתמודד עם אובדן איטי או פתאומי של נכסים עצביים. אולי, היא אומרת, ממצאי הפרויקט יעזרו ליותר אנשים להבין &quot;עד כמה אתה יכול להיות שונה ועדיין לגדול ולעשות דברים מדהימים&quot;.</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> מהו בכלל מוח תקין?</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> בהערת פתיחה <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0028393222000434?via%3Dihub" target="_blank" rel="noopener">במאמרו של פדורנקו מ-2022 ב- <em>Neuropsychologia</em></a> , כתבה אליזה על כך שמבנה המוח שלה לא מגדיר אותה. &quot;בבקשה אל תקרא למוח שלי לא נורמלי, זה מפחיד אותי&quot;, כתבה. &quot;המוח שלי לא טיפוסי. אלמלא מצאתי בטעות את ההבדלים האלה, אף אחד לא היה בוחר אותי מהקהל בסבירות שיש לי כאלה, או כל הבדלים אחרים שעושים אותי ייחודי&quot;.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> אליזה מקווה שהמסר מגיע לרופאים ולמדעני מחקר. &quot;אני רוצה שהם יבינו שזה אדם שהם קוראים עליו מאמר, לא מוח חסר גוף בצנצנת&quot;, היא אומרת.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> דבר אחד שאליזה אוהבת בעבודה עם הצוות של פדורנקו הוא שהמחקר מרגיש שיתופי. מדענים מסתמכים על שותפויות קרובות כמו זה כדי להבין כיצד המוח פועל במצבים טיפוסיים וכיצד הוא עשוי להתאושש מפציעה, אומר לסלי עמיתים, נוירולוג מאוניברסיטת מקגיל במונטריאול, החוקר כיצד נזק מוחי משפיע על קבלת החלטות. אנשים עם מוח לא טיפוסי &quot;יכולים לתת לנו כל מיני רעיונות נהדרים שאולי לא חשבנו עליהם&quot;, היא אומרת. &quot;יש להם נקודת תצפית ייחודית&quot;.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> אליזה, למשל, חווה הזיות ריח. היא קולטת ניחוחות של שריפות חשמל בכל פעם שהיא במתח רב. &quot;כשהייתי בתיכון, הייתי מריחה שריפות חשמל שלוש פעמים בשבוע&quot;, היא אומרת. אליזה עדיין לא חקרה את המוזרות המוחית הזו עם פדורנקו ועמיתיה, אבל היא פתוחה לרעיונות שלהם לחקירות עתידיות.</p><figure class="wp-block-pullquote alignright"><blockquote style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> &quot;אני רוצה שהם יבינו שזה אדם שהם קוראים עליו מאמר, לא מוח חסר גוף בצנצנת.&quot;</p> <cite>אליזה ג.</cite></blockquote></figure><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> למחקר האחרון של הצוות, שדווח בהדפסה מוקדמת השנה, השתתפו אליזה, מרתה ואחות נוספת (אחת עם מוח &quot;רגיל&quot;) במשימות שמיעה בתוך צינור ה-MRI. הצוות של פדורנקו רצה לברר <a href="https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2023.01.18.523979v1" target="_blank" rel="noopener">כיצד פועלת קליפת השמיעה השמאלית או הימנית כאשר הצד השני חסר</a> .</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> אפשר לחשוב שצריך לשפר איכשהו את קליפת המוח השמיעתית הנותרת כדי לבצע עבודה כפולה, אולי לתפוס מקום נוסף, אומרת תמר רגב, מדענית מוח קוגניטיבית במעבדה של פדורנקו. אבל זה לא מה שהצוות מצא.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> גם במוחה של אליזה וגם של מרתה, &quot;הפעילות נראית נוירוטיפית לחלוטין&quot;, אומרת רגב. זה מרמז על יתירות מסוימת למערכת השמיעה של המוח, ושהתפתחות קליפת שמע אחת אינה תלויה בקיומו של האחר.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> אליזה סקרנית אילו תובנות נוספות ילמד הצוות של פדורנקו מהמוח שלה ומהמוח של משתתפי פרויקט מוחות מעניינים אחרים. &quot;המוח שלי מיוחד, ייחודי ומעניין&quot;, כתבה במאמר משנת 2022, &quot;ואני נרגשת שהוא יכול לעזור למדעני מוח להבין את הפלסטיות של המוח האנושי&quot;.</p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_interesting-brains_feat-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="302857" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071523_interesting-brains_feat-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title> למסה יש הגדרות שונות. מסלול הירח מאשר שניים שווים</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/mass-moon-orbit-gravity-space<dc:creator><![CDATA[Emily Conover]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Thu, 13 Jul 2023 16:20:02 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Physics]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3129654 </guid><description><![CDATA[Laser measurements of the moon’s orbit square with Newton’s third law of motion and Einstein’s theory of gravity.]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<p>מסה היא מסה היא מסה.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> לפיסיקאים יש שלוש הגדרות שונות של מסה, שכולן נחשבות שוות ערך. מדידות של המרחק בין כדור הארץ לירח מאשרות <a href="https://journals.aps.org/prl/abstract/10.1103/PhysRevLett.131.021401" target="_blank" rel="noopener">ששתיים מאותן מסות הן זהות בדיוק</a> גבוה מאי פעם, פיסיקאים מדווחים על 13 ביולי ב- <em>Physical Review Letters</em> . תוצאה זו מאשרת את אחד היסודות הבסיסיים ביותר של הפיזיקה: חוק התנועה השלישי של ניוטון.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> מסה אינרציאלית קובעת באיזו קלות עצם מאיץ בתגובה לכוח. ואז יש מסה כבידה פעילה, שקובעת את חוזק שדה הכבידה של עצם. מסה כבידה פסיבית משלימה את השלישייה, המכתיבה את הכוח על עצם בשדה כבידה נתון.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> &quot;זו שאלה גדולה בפיזיקה מדוע המסות האלה זהות&quot;, אומר הפיזיקאי התיאורטי קלאוס למרזהל מאוניברסיטת ברמן בגרמניה. אז מדענים רוצים להיות בטוחים שהם לא מעט שונים.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> בעבר, <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/einstein-general-relativity-gravity-microscope-experiment">ניסוי ה-MICROSCOPE</a> אישר את השקילות של מסה אינרציאלית ומסת כבידה פסיבית בבדיקות על סיפון לוויין ( <em>SN: 9/14/22</em> ).</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> במחקר החדש, מדענים השוו מסות כבידה אקטיביות ופסיביות לשני יסודות שנמצאים בחלקים שונים של הירח: ברזל בליבה ואלומיניום בקרום.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> החוק השלישי של ניוטון, שנאמר לעתים קרובות כ&quot;לכל פעולה, יש תגובה שווה והפוכה&quot;, מציע שהמשיכה של הברזל על האלומיניום צריכה להיות זהה למשיכה של האלומיניום על הברזל.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> אם המסות האקטיביות והפאסיביות היו שונות, זה היה מפר את הכלל והמשיכה הלא אחידה תשנה את מסלול הירח. בהתבסס על עשרות שנים של מדידות לייזר של מרחק הירח מכדור הארץ ומיקומו במסלולו, היחס בין מסות כבידה אקטיביות ופסיביות לשני החומרים היה זהה לכארבעה טריליון האחוז, כך מדווחים לאמרזאהל ועמיתיו.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> מציאת הבדל תתנגש גם עם תורת הכבידה של איינשטיין, תורת היחסות הכללית. אז הירח משרת ניצחון לא רק לניוטון, אלא גם לאיינשטיין.</p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071223_EV_moon-mass_feat-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="49013" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071223_EV_moon-mass_feat-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title> השבוע שעבר היה החם ביותר שהוקלט אי פעם - זו הסיבה שאנחנו ממשיכים לשבור שיאים</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/heat-record-june-july-water-climate<dc:creator><![CDATA[Nikk Ogasa]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Thu, 13 Jul 2023 13:29:26 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Climate]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3129622 </guid><description><![CDATA[Global temperature records are being shattered as El Niño and climate change combine to push the Earth into uncharted territory, researchers say.]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<p>הטמפרטורות העולמיות מנפצות שיאים כאשר אל ניניו ושינויי האקלים מתחברים.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> ב-3 ביולי, כוכב הלכת התנפח כשהטמפרטורה הגלובלית הממוצעת הגיעה ל-17.01 מעלות צלזיוס (62.62 מעלות פרנהייט), הגבוהה ביותר שנרשמה אי פעם, על פי נתונים מהמרכזים הלאומיים של ארה&quot;ב לחיזוי סביבתי. זה עבר את השיא הקודם של 16.92 מעלות צלזיוס (62.46 מעלות פרנהייט) מאוגוסט 2016.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> עד סוף השבוע, השיא החדש הושווה או נשבר שלוש פעמים נוספות, והגיע לשיא ב-6 ביולי עם 17.23 מעלות צלזיוס (63.01 מעלות פרנהייט). וכדור הארץ בדיוק חווה את יוני החם ביותר שלו שנרשם אי פעם.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> תקופה זו של השנה היא בדרך כלל כאשר הטמפרטורה הגלובלית הממוצעת מגיעה לשיא. אבל האופי יוצא הדופן של יוני ויולי השנה נובע כנראה ממה שקורה בכחול הגדול. האוקיינוסים ברחבי העולם התחממו בצורה מדאיגה, לא מעט הודות לשינויי אקלים שנגרמו על ידי אדם, אומרים חוקרים. ואל ניניו, דפוס האקלים החוזר הידוע כמחמם את כדור הארץ באופן זמני, חזר סוף סוף.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> &quot;באמת מעולם לא היו לנו נסיבות כאלה בעבר&quot;, אומרת מדענית האטמוספירה ג&#39;ניפר פרנסיס מהמרכז לחקר האקלים וודוול בפאלמות&#39;, מסה. &quot;אנחנו נכנסים לטריטוריה לא ידועה&quot;.</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> אוקיינוסים חמים הם בעיה</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> חלק גדול מהחום הקיצוני שאנו רואים חוזר למצב האוקיינוסים שלנו, אומר מדען האקלים תומס די ליברטו ממינהל האוקיינוסים והאטמוספירה הלאומי של ארה&quot;ב בוושינגטון הבירה &quot;האוקיינוס ​​העולמי פשוט היה כל כך, כל כך חם.&quot;</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> הים של הפלנטה שלנו מתחממים כבר עשרות שנים. העשור האחרון היה החם ביותר של פני הים מאז שנות ה-1800 לפחות. באפריל הגיעה טמפרטורת פני השטח הממוצעת של האוקיינוסים בעולם ל-21.1 מעלות צלזיוס, הגבוהה ביותר שנרשמה אי פעם.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> היה חם במיוחד בצפון האוקיינוס ​​האטלנטי, שם נשברים שיאים בהפרשים גדולים. באפריל, טמפרטורות פני הים שם עלו על <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/north-atlantic-heat-record-sea-surface-temperature">4 מעלות צלזיוס מעל הרגיל</a> לתקופה זו של השנה ( <em>SN: 15/6/23</em> ). ובמפרץ מקסיקו, טמפרטורת פני השטח הממוצעת היא יותר מ-30 מעלות צלזיוס, נכון ל-12 ביולי, הגבוהה ביותר שנרשמה בתקופה זו של השנה מאז שהחלו לוויינים לנטר שם ב-1981. שניהם דוגמאות לגלי חום ימיים, תקופות מתמשכות של טמפרטורות אוקיינוס ​​חמות בצורה חריגה.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> גלי חום כאלה פוקדים כיום כ-40% מהאוקיינוסים בעולם. תחזיות NOAA מצביעות על כך שעד ספטמבר, <a href="https://psl.noaa.gov/marine-heatwaves/#report" target="_blank" rel="noopener">גלי חום ימיים עלולים להשתלט על פני חצי מהאוקיינוס ​​העולמי</a> , אומר די ליברטו. אירועי קיצון אלו הפכו לשכיחים בכ-50 אחוז במהלך העשור האחרון. הרבה מההתחממות הזו קשורה לשינויי אקלים, הוא אומר. &quot;ענקנו את המערכת.&quot;</p><div class="wp-block-sciencenews-content-sidebar" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> גלי חום ימיים 13 ביוני עד 12 ביולי 2023</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> כ-40 אחוז מהאוקיינוסים בעולם מושפעים כיום מגלי חום ימיים - תקופות מתמשכות של טמפרטורות אוקיינוסים חמות בצורה חריגה. ניתן לראות את התפוצה שלהם במפה זו, המציגה חריגות ממוצעות של טמפרטורת פני הים ברחבי האוקיינוסים מ-13 ביוני עד 12 ביולי 2023. חריגות טמפרטורה עזות יותר הן גוונים כהים יותר של אדום. </p><figure class="wp-block-image "><picture class="sn-responsive-image"><source srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071223_no_heat-records_inline1_desktop.jpg 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071223_no_heat-records_inline1_desktop-613x383.jpg 613w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071223_no_heat-records_inline1_desktop-298x186.jpg 298w" width="680" height="425" media="(min-width: 600px)" sizes="(max-width: 1023px) 100vw, 680px"></source><source srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071223_no_heat-records_inline1_mobile.jpg 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071223_no_heat-records_inline1_mobile-579x383.jpg 579w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071223_no_heat-records_inline1_mobile-281x186.jpg 281w" width="680" height="450"></source><img src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071223_no_heat-records_inline1_mobile.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large" alt="מפת העולם המציגה כתמי חום באוקיינוסים בגווני אדום." decoding="async" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071223_no_heat-records_inline1_mobile.jpg 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071223_no_heat-records_inline1_mobile-579x383.jpg 579w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071223_no_heat-records_inline1_mobile-281x186.jpg 281w" sizes="(max-width: 1023px) 100vw, 680px" data-attachment-id="3129627" data-permalink="https://www.sciencenews.org/071223_no_heat-records_inline1_mobile" data-orig-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071223_no_heat-records_inline1_mobile.jpg" data-orig-size="680,450" data-comments-opened="0" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="071223_no_heat-records_inline1_mobile" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071223_no_heat-records_inline1_mobile-579x383.jpg" data-large-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071223_no_heat-records_inline1_mobile.jpg" /></picture><figcaption> <span class="credit mobile-credit wp-credit-3129627">NOAA</span> <span class="credit desktop-credit wp-credit-3129626">NOAA</span></figcaption></figure></div><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Hotter seas are a huge problem, says atmospheric scientist Marybeth Arcodia of Colorado State University in Fort Collins.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “The ocean is currently taking [in] about 93 percent of the heat associated with global warming,” Arcodia says. As the oceans warm, they become less capable of absorbing heat from the atmosphere, so that&#39;s where it remains, raising the global temperature.</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> El Niño has arrived</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Operating on top of this background of ocean warming is a natural climate cycle called the El Niño-Southern Oscillation, or ENSO. The phenomenon entails yearslong fluctuations in sea surface temperatures in the central and eastern tropical Pacific Ocean. These water temperature changes are controlled by equatorial air currents known as the trade winds.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> During neutral ENSO conditions, the trade winds blow westward against the surface of the Pacific Ocean, pushing warm water toward Indonesia and triggering the upwelling of cold water from the ocean&#39;s depths along the South American coast. When the trade winds blow especially strong, more warm water is pushed east. This part of the cycle is called La Niña. In March, the Earth exited three years of La Niña conditions, a relatively long-lived phase.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Then in June, La Niña&#39;s counterpart, El Niño, got underway. Many scientists think that El Niño can be triggered by westerly wind bursts — anomalous winds that sometimes appear in the western Pacific, says physical oceanographer Regina Rodrigues of the Federal University of Santa Catarina in Florianópolis, Brazil. These bursts blow opposite to the trade winds and weaken them, she says, setting the stage for El Niño.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Unbidden by the westbound winds, warm water in the western Pacific sloshes back toward the Americas. Ocean upwelling along the tropical South American coast is stifled, and much of the tropical Pacific — which at the equator wraps halfway around the planet — becomes swaddled in a warm duvet of water, which can be hundreds of meters deep. That balmy layer exudes heat into the atmosphere, where much of it is trapped by the greenhouse gases that humans have emitted, raising the global temperature.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> El Niño is typically associated with warmer global temperatures, while La Niña is often correlated with cooler temperatures, Arcodia says. “2016 is currently the hottest year on record,” she says. “That lines up with the strongest El Niño event on record.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> But El Niño and La Niña don&#39;t always have predictable outcomes. For instance, <a href="https://www.noaa.gov/news/2020-was-earth-s-2nd-hottest-year-just-behind-2016" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2020 was the second hottest year</a> on record, and it was during La Niña conditions, Arcodia says. That underscores the influence of climate warming on these record-breaking temperatures, she says.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> While it&#39;s probably safe to say that El Niño is exacerbating climate warming, it&#39;s hard to say exactly how much the phenomenon&#39;s return contributed to the recent unprecedented heat, Di Liberto, Rodrigues and Arcodia agree.</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> We&#39;re just getting started</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> This El Niño is still in its infancy. The climate pattern typically peaks during the Northern Hemisphere&#39;s winter, so Earth has probably not yet felt the full brunt of the impact. That means the planet may be in store for even higher global temperatures later in July, Di Liberto says. Even later in the year, Earth will probably see more anomalously warm months as El Niño continues to strengthen.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Since the climate pattern hasn&#39;t reached full force, it&#39;s hard to draw comparisons with its past manifestations. But forecast models do suggest that there is a <a href="https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/analysis_monitoring/enso_advisory/ensodisc.shtml" target="_blank" rel="noopener">better than 50 percent chance</a> of this El Niño developing into a relatively strong one, Arcodia says. In such a scenario, the average temperature of the east-central tropical Pacific would temporarily reach or exceed 1.5 degrees C above normal. In early June, temperatures in that part of the Pacific were already 0.7 degrees C above normal.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> It&#39;s possible that the relatively long La Niña period we just exited might have set the stage for a strong El Niño, Rodrigues speculates. That La Niña spent three years packing the western Pacific with warm water, loading it like a spring, she says. Now, that spring has been released.</p><div class="wp-block-sciencenews-content-sidebar alignwide" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Global temperatures during El Niño and La Niña </h4><figure class="wp-block-image alignwide"><picture class="sn-responsive-image"><source srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071223_no_heat-records_inline2_desktop_1030_REV-800x281.jpg 800w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071223_no_heat-records_inline2_desktop_1030_REV-680x239.jpg 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071223_no_heat-records_inline2_desktop_1030_REV-330x116.jpg 330w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071223_no_heat-records_inline2_desktop_1030_REV-768x270.jpg 768w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071223_no_heat-records_inline2_desktop_1030_REV.jpg 1030w" width="800" height="281" media="(min-width: 600px)" sizes="(max-width: 1023px) 100vw, (max-width: 1439px) 60vw, 894px"></source><source srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071223_no_heat-records_inline2_mobile.jpg 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071223_no_heat-records_inline2_mobile-330x150.jpg 330w" width="680" height="310"></source><img src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071223_no_heat-records_inline2_mobile.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large" alt="A graph showing the number of El Nino months in red, ENSO neutral months in gray and La Nina months in blue from 1950 through 2023." decoding="async" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071223_no_heat-records_inline2_mobile.jpg 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071223_no_heat-records_inline2_mobile-330x150.jpg 330w" sizes="(max-width: 1023px) 100vw, (max-width: 1439px) 60vw, 894px" data-attachment-id="3129629" data-permalink="https://www.sciencenews.org/071223_no_heat-records_inline2_mobile" data-orig-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071223_no_heat-records_inline2_mobile.jpg" data-orig-size="680,310" data-comments-opened="0" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="071223_no_heat-records_inline2_mobile" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="&lt;p>;Periods of El Niño (shown in red) are typically associated with warmer than normal global temperatures, while La Niña (shown in blue) usually correlate with cooler temperatures. The previous hottest year on record, 2016, coincided with a strong El Niño that lasted from 2015 to 2016.&lt;/p>;
" data-medium-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071223_no_heat-records_inline2_mobile.jpg" data-large-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071223_no_heat-records_inline2_mobile.jpg" /></picture><figcaption> <span class="caption mobile-caption wp-caption-3129629">Periods of El Niño (shown in red) are typically associated with warmer than normal global temperatures, while La Niña (shown in blue) usually correlate with cooler temperatures. The previous hottest year on record, 2016, coincided with a strong El Niño that lasted from 2015 to 2016.</span> <span class="credit mobile-credit wp-credit-3129629">c</span> <span class="caption desktop-caption wp-caption-3129660">Periods of El Niño (shown in red) are typically associated with warmer than normal global temperatures, while La Niña (shown in blue) usually correlate with cooler temperatures. The previous hottest year on record, 2016, coincided with a strong El Niño that lasted from 2015 to 2016.</span> <span class="credit desktop-credit wp-credit-3129660">National Centers for Environmental Information/NOAA</span></figcaption></figure></div><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> With El Niño exacerbating things, this year could become the hottest year on record. There&#39;s about <a href="https://www.ncei.noaa.gov/access/monitoring/monthly-report/global/202305/supplemental/page-2" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a 13 percent chance</a> that 2023 takes the title, and a nearly 90 percent chance that it&#39;s among the top five on record, according to the US National Centers for Environmental Information.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> What&#39;s more, some scientists are concerned that the El Niño could temporarily push global warming more than 1.5 degrees C above preindustrial levels for the first time, Rodrigues says.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Many experts have warned that <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/global-warming-limit-degrees-ipcc-climate-change">crossing that benchmark</a> could trigger irreversible changes in some parts of the planet ( <em>SN: 10/7/18</em> ). That could include the transformation of the <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/amazon-tipping-trouble-climate-cerrado">Amazon rainforest</a> and more widespread melting of the <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/greenland-hinterlands-leaking-ice">Greenland</a> and <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/melting-eroding-thwaites-glacier">Antarctic ice sheets</a> ( <em>SN: 6/16/23</em> ; <em>SN: 11/9/22</em> ; <em>SN: 2/15/23</em> ). But because El Niño is a temporary phenomenon, it&#39;s hard to say if, or how, the climate pattern might impact these elements, Rodrigues says.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> It&#39;s a momentous experiment, she says. One with us, and the rest of life on Earth, stuck in the middle.</p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071223_no_heat-records_feat-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="114732" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071223_no_heat-records_feat-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title> Explore the past, present and future of &#39;Eight Bears&#39;</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/eight-bears-book-conservation<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jake Buehler]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Thu, 13 Jul 2023 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Animals]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3129345 </guid><description><![CDATA[The book invites readers to meet the eight species of bears left on Earth and looks at how humans are shaping their future, for better or for worse. ]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[



<div class="wp-block-image  has-alignleft"><figure class="alignleft size-medium is-resized"><a href="https://bookshop.org/a/21798/9781324005087" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/071523_reviews_inline-254x383.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-3129348" width="191" height="287" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/071523_reviews_inline-254x383.jpg 254w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/071523_reviews_inline-298x450.jpg 298w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/071523_reviews_inline-123x186.jpg 123w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/071523_reviews_inline-384x580.jpg 384w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/071523_reviews_inline-514x776.jpg 514w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/071523_reviews_inline.jpg 680w" sizes="(max-width: 191px) 100vw, 191px" /></a></figure></div><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <a href="https://bookshop.org/a/21798/9781324005087" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Eight Bears</a><br> <em>Gloria Dickie<br> WW Norton &amp; Co., $30</em></p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Bears have long been considered family. “Stories of a familial bear exist in almost every human culture that shares territory with the animal,” writes journalist Gloria Dickie in her new book, <em>Eight Bears</em> .</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The Yakut people of eastern Siberia call brown bears “grandfather” and “uncle.” Shepherds in the French Pyrenees call the brown bear <em>la va-nu-pieds</em> , the “barefooted one,” a reference to its humanlike footprints. In Peru, the Ukuku is an Andes-traipsing man-bear hybrid in Quechua lore that steals away young women.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The ancient and recurrent history of humans recognizing bears as either spiritual or biological brethren sets the tone for the book, which provides rich lessons for understanding our ursine neighbors and how their lives have intertwined with our own.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> That bears have had such a cultural grip on our species is impressive given their dearth of global diversity. As you might have guessed, there are only eight bear species: brown, black, sun, moon, polar, spectacled, sloth and giant panda. Dickie explores each in vivid detail, traveling across three continents to some of the places where they amble.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The settings Dickie presents — some remote, some urban — are marvelously rendered. She transports readers to the perilously steep ridgelines of the Andes, perpetually misty and buzzing with hummingbirds, and to Churchill, Canada, a subarctic town on an icy seashore sitting square in the path of migrating <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/polar-bear-paws-traction-snow-microstructures-friction">polar bears</a> ( <em>SN: 11/1/22</em> ). Through these travels, Dickie weaves in each species&#39;s unique stories — of decline, recovery and an uncertain future — and how humans have roped their own desires and ambitions to the bears, for better or worse.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Dickie expertly peppers her “ursine odyssey” with dry humor, augmenting the experience of encountering the bears, which oscillates from dopey to truly dangerous. One moment that stands out is when Dickie is preparing to visit the forest homes of Indian sloth bears and describes digesting jarringly matter-of-fact stories and photos of the aftereffects of maulings. But not to worry, a local biologist assures her “in a way that was meant to be comforting,” she will see more injuries like this where she is set to travel.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Such engaging insights into Dickie&#39;s experiences elevate <em>Eight Bears</em> well above a patchwork of bear facts.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Though, there are facts aplenty. Dickie provides ample context on each species&#39;s biology, ecology and historical (and sometimes prehistorical) relationship with humans. The robust accounting of so much about these animals is fascinating, though some forays into the evolutionary history of each branch of the bear family tree and the taxonomic identity of Paddington Bear and Baloo from <em><a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/disneys-jungle-book-resurrects-giant-extinct-ape">The Jungle Book</a></em> can feel meandering ( <em>SN: 4/3/16</em> ). Still, Dickie excels in crafting a captivating and carefully considered mosaic of stories that will engross any reader interested in wildlife and wilderness.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> One primary theme in <em>Eight Bears</em> is that many species inhabit woefully shrinking natural spaces. In the Andes, spectacled bears&#39; cloud forests risk ascending upslope into oblivion due to a warming climate. Polar bears are caught between <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/climate-change-bering-sea-ice-winter-melt-lowest-level">rapidly dwindling sea ice</a> and a genetic tidal wave from hybridizing with brown bears that have started wandering poleward ( <em>SN: 9/3/20</em> ). Sloth bears are squeezed into smaller and smaller pockets of forest as human populations expand, leading to violent, tragic conflicts with people.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> These eight bear species, Dickie shows, manage to capture the full range of people&#39;s attitudes toward wilderness, from awe to exploitation, neglect to reverence. She illuminates radically varied consequences of humans placing political, social or economic value on bears. For instance, circumstances aligned for giant pandas to be useful in “panda diplomacy” as a political bargaining chip for China, thus feeding a cultural status and conservation investment the seven other bear species lack. Dickie&#39;s honest and bleak accounts of moon and sun bears languishing on farms in Vietnam that collect bear bile to treat inflammation and high cholesterol present a far darker reality for some species.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> There are relative success stories in which bears have bounced back into abundance, but that can present ongoing tension. In the United States, humans and black bears navigate coexistence at the wildland-urban interface (and national park trash cans). On the eastern flanks of the Rockies, brown bears lollop into territories gone bearless for decades due to intentional extermination, now saturated with farms and people.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> In the end, Dickie warns that only three species — black, brown and panda bears — seem well-positioned to persist in the wild in the future. Losing animals whose lives have so closely paralleled our own would be like losing family, she writes. “And in some ways, we would lose a part of our own wildness. Without bears, the woods, and our stories, would be empty.”</p><hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" /><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <em>Buy</em> <a href="https://bookshop.org/a/21798/9781324005087" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Eight Bears</a> <em>from Bookshop.org.</em> Science News <em>is a Bookshop.org affiliate and will earn a commission on purchases made from links in this article.</em></p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/071523_reviews_feat-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="255827" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/071523_reviews_feat-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title> How Kenya is helping its neighbors develop geothermal energy</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/geothermal-energy-africa-kenya-renewable-electricity<dc:creator><![CDATA[Geoffrey Kamadi]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Wed, 12 Jul 2023 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Earth]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3129332 </guid><description><![CDATA[Renewable energy is crucial to halting climate change. In East Africa, the region’s geology makes geothermal energy a viable option. ]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<p class="has-drop-cap">The dusty town of Naivasha sits within the Great Rift Valley, where the African continent is being divided into two. About 90 kilometers northwest of Kenya&#39;s capital city of Nairobi, Naivasha welcomes gaggles of tourists each year trekking to Hell&#39;s Gate National Park. The forces that are splitting apart the African tectonic plate have sculpted the area&#39;s steep cliffs, plummeting valleys and undulating hills — a rugged landscape that inspired the backdrop of Disney&#39;s <em>The Lion King</em> .</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Those forces have also made Naivasha the frontier of Kenya&#39;s geothermal power industry.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The country&#39;s first geothermal well was drilled there in the 1950s. By 1981, Kenya had its first geothermal power plant, harnessing a renewable resource that taps into heat generated deep within the Earth. Today, Naivasha&#39;s Olkaria geothermal power project plus a small facility at another site are capable of generating 963 megawatts of electricity when running at full power.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> At the end of last year, Kenya ranked seventh on the list of top geothermal energy countries in the world. Geothermal accounts for 47 percent of the country&#39;s total energy production — a percentage that&#39;s growing. The only other geothermal energy producer in Africa, Ethiopia, started production in 1998 and has an installed capacity of just 7.5 megawatts.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> But regional interest is growing, especially as Africa works toward universal energy access by 2030, in accordance with the United Nations&#39; Sustainable Development Goals. Roughly 43 percent of the continent&#39;s population, equaling about 600 million people, lacks access to electricity. A 2021 analysis by the Dalberg consulting firm in partnership with the UN showed that there&#39;s enough renewable energy potential to power Africa&#39;s energy needs well into the future, though the up-front costs would be higher than if fossil fuels were used to meet those energy demands.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> If African countries pursue renewable energy to meet their electricity goals, the up-front cost would be $1.5 trillion, about 50 percent more than the $1 trillion that fossils fuels would require, says James Mwangi, formerly of Dalberg and founder of the group Climate Action Platform for Africa. But thanks to lower operating and maintenance costs, renewables eventually pay off. In one scenario in the Dalberg analysis, a renewable-heavy future would take 13 years or so to break even with one where fossil fuels are still heavily used.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> With the renewables route, Mwangi says, “Africa could reach universal energy access much faster and ultimately have the lowest energy costs in the world.” The localized nature of renewable sources, compared with often-imported fossil fuels, could also enhance energy security and independence.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> In East Africa, geothermal energy is an attractive option. It&#39;s abundant thanks to the East African Rift System, which brings heat toward the surface. Like other renewable energies such as wind and solar, geothermal doesn&#39;t emit carbon dioxide. And it comes with extra benefits. “Geothermal power is reliable,” says Anna Mwangi, senior geophysicist at the Kenya Electricity Generating Company, or KenGen, the government entity that operates Olkaria (and no relation to James Mwangi). Geothermal sources are available night and day, and don&#39;t depend on the sun, wind or rain. So geothermal energy may be more resilient to climate change than some other renewables.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> But setting up geothermal power plants requires more money and specialized expertise than other renewable energies. And like any development project, it can come with social costs, such as displacing people from their land.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Given its long-standing experience, Kenya is now assisting its neighbors. “We are offering technical support to the countries in the region, as a way to help them develop their geothermal potential,” says Anna Mwangi. KenGen has already drilled multiple geothermal wells in Ethiopia and Djibouti. </p><div class="wp-block-image  has-alignleft" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><figure class="alignleft size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="680" height="454" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/070123_geothermal_inline-1.jpg" alt="photo of Anna Mwangi sitting at a table" class="wp-image-3129427" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/070123_geothermal_inline-1.jpg 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/070123_geothermal_inline-1-574x383.jpg 574w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/070123_geothermal_inline-1-674x450.jpg 674w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/070123_geothermal_inline-1-279x186.jpg 279w" sizes="(max-width: 680px) 100vw, 680px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3129427">“Geothermal power is reliable,” says Anna Mwangi, a geophysicist at KenGen.</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3129427">G. Kamadi</span></figcaption></figure></div><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Why East Africa is a geothermal energy hot spot</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Globally, geothermal resources are often found along the boundaries of tectonic plates, such as around the Pacific Ocean&#39;s Ring of Fire. In Africa, a bounty of geothermal resources exist where a new boundary is forming: the East African Rift System. The exact start of the system is not clearly defined; it originates on the Arabian Peninsula before running south along the Red Sea and into Djibouti. As it runs southward in Africa, the rift zone branches into two arms: The eastern arm ends at the border between Kenya and Tanzania while the western arm goes farther south, running 6,400 kilometers through more than 10 countries before ending in Mozambique.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> For millions of years, the African Plate has been pulled in opposite directions, at a rate of a few centimeters per year. Eventually, this stretching will split Africa into two separate continents and create two tectonic plates, the Nubian Plate to the west and the Somalian Plate to the east.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The stretching also causes magma to dome up in various points along the rift system. One such place is Olkaria in Naivasha. Beneath the surface, the molten rock heats groundwater. Wells bring that hot water and steam to the surface. When harnessed at high pressure and used to turn turbines, the steam generates electricity. The hot water is then injected back into the ground to recharge the subterranean water supply.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> There&#39;s no comprehensive estimate for how much total energy East Africa could harvest from geothermal sources. But experts estimate that Kenya and Ethiopia could each generate 10,000 megawatts. That&#39;s roughly triple Kenya&#39;s total installed electricity capacity and double Ethiopia&#39;s.</p><div class="wp-block-sciencenews-content-sidebar alignleft" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><h3 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Where&#39;s the heat?</h3><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The total worldwide installed capacity for generating electricity from geothermal energy is 16,000 megawatts. In 2022, Kenya ranked seventh on the list of top geothermal countries.<br> Source: ThinkGeoEnergy Research 2023</p><h5 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Top 10 geothermal countries (megawatts of installed capacity)</h5><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> United States: 3,794<br> Indonesia: 2,356<br> Philippines: 1,935<br> Turkey: 1,682<br> New Zealand: 1,037<br> Mexico: 963<br> Kenya: 944*<br> Italy: 944<br> Iceland: 754<br> Japan: 621</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> *ThinkGeoEnergy&#39;s tally of Kenya&#39;s installed capacity, as of January 2023, differs slightly from KenGen&#39;s.</p></div><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> For now, it&#39;s mostly Kenya — one of the world&#39;s fastest-growing geothermal power players — that has plumbed this deep heat. In addition to Olkaria, there&#39;s a small site at the nearby Eburru geothermal field that can generate 2.4 megawatts of electricity. Farther to the north, a 35-megawatt power plant is expected to open this year at the Menengai geothermal field, with another one in development.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> A push toward geothermal energy in recent years has come as droughts have dwindled some of Kenya&#39;s hydropower sources. With rainfall and temperatures projected to become more erratic and extreme with climate change, geothermal energy may be the more dependable option, Anna Mwangi says.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Geothermal power plants can run at maximum power output up to 90 percent of the time, when taking downtime due to maintenance into account, says François Le Scornet, president and senior market intelligence consultant at Carbonexit Consulting in France. That&#39;s comparable to a nuclear power plant and about twice as reliable as a fossil fuel plant or wind farm (and four times as good as solar). Indeed, with the rise of geothermal energy, <a href="https://www.irena.org/Publications/2023/Feb/Global-geothermal-market-and-technology-assessment" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Kenya&#39;s power outages have declined</a> , according to a report released in February by the International Renewable Energy Agency and the International Geothermal Association.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The scalding-hot water and steam that flow up a geothermal well can do more than generate electricity; they can also be a direct source of heating. The <a href="https://www.geothermal-energy.org/pdf/IGAstandard/WGC/2020/01055.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Oserian flower farm near Naivasha</a> , for instance, pipes the water in to warm a greenhouse at night. The warmth dries out the air to prevent fungus from spoiling the roses, carnations and other flowers destined for bouquets around the world. At Olkaria, tourists in need of relaxation after a long day of exploring Hell&#39;s Gate can soak in the geothermal spa near the power plant. </p><figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1030" height="550" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/070123_geothermal_inline-2.jpg" alt="people in a spa pool with steam rising in the background near the Olkaria geothermal power project" class="wp-image-3129428" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/070123_geothermal_inline-2.jpg 1030w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/070123_geothermal_inline-2-680x363.jpg 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/070123_geothermal_inline-2-800x427.jpg 800w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/070123_geothermal_inline-2-330x176.jpg 330w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/070123_geothermal_inline-2-768x410.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1030px) 100vw, 1030px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3129428">Geothermal energy doesn&#39;t just generate electricity. It can also be used as a direct source of heating, like at this spa next to the Olkaria geothermal power project.</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3129428">G. Kamadi</span></figcaption></figure><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> How to find geothermal resources</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> It takes a team of specialists to determine a site&#39;s suitability for geothermal resource exploration. At minimum, what&#39;s needed are the presence of groundwater, high temperatures — often around or above 150° Celsius — and permeable rock that will enable heated water and steam to flow into production wells, says Mohamed Abdel Zaher, a geophysicist at the National Research Institute of Astronomy and Geophysics in Cairo.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Certain visual characteristics on the surface may give an initial hint. Hot springs, hot mud puddles, geysers and even steam rising from the ground are signs of geothermal activity. Another clue is the presence of certain rocks, such as travertine, or mineral veins like quartz that indicate rock has been altered during interactions with hot water.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> At Olkaria, a tip-off was the fact that the surrounding area is ring-shaped like a caldera, a collapsed volcano. A series of younger volcanic domes appear to have intruded into the caldera.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> If the surface characteristics look promising, geochemists will step in to analyze fluid and gas samples to estimate how deep and hot the heat source might be and where the fluids flow. Seismometers might be deployed to infer the brittleness of the subsurface rock. It&#39;s important that rock be permeable, but it needs to be strong enough to withstand the interaction of cool water being heated from the magma below.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> If all those data look promising, exploration drilling will commence and if all goes well, a production well and eventually a full-blown power plant will follow.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Zaher and his colleagues recently completed a project that might help experts across the continent zero in on potential geothermal targets before starting costly on-the-ground exploration. “It is quite difficult to predict the precise power or electricity that can be produced for all of Africa,” he says. But his group incorporated a range of geologic, seismic and other geophysical data into a geographic information system to predict the most promising spots for geothermal exploration. The resulting map identifies <a href="https://geothermal-energy-journal.springeropen.com/articles/10.1186/s40517-022-00219-1" target="_blank" rel="noopener">14 areas that have high geothermal potential</a> , the team reported last year in <em>Geothermal Energy</em> .</p><div class="wp-block-sciencenews-content-sidebar alignwide" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><h3 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Good prospects</h3><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> A recent analysis pinpointed 14 areas in Africa with high potential for developing geothermal energy. Most of these locations are within the East African Rift System. </p><div class="wp-block-columns is-layout-flex wp-container-3" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><div class="wp-block-column is-layout-flow" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><h5 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Locations in Africa with high potential for geothermal energy </h5><figure class="wp-block-image size-full" data-component="lightbox"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="680" height="615" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/070123_geothermal_inline-3.jpg" alt="map of 14 geothermal hotspots in Africa" class="wp-image-3129429" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/070123_geothermal_inline-3.jpg 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/070123_geothermal_inline-3-423x383.jpg 423w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/070123_geothermal_inline-3-498x450.jpg 498w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/070123_geothermal_inline-3-206x186.jpg 206w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/070123_geothermal_inline-3-641x580.jpg 641w" sizes="(max-width: 680px) 100vw, 680px" /><figcaption> <span class="credit wp-credit-3129429">T. Tibbitts</span> </figcaption></figure></div><div class="wp-block-column is-layout-flow" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><h5 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Areas with high potential</h5><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> 1. Northernmost Africa<br> 2. Gulf of Suez, Gulf of Aqaba (Egypt)<br> 3. Red Sea access<br> 4. Liberia and Ivory Coast<br> 5. Djibouti<br> 6. Main Ethiopian Rift<br> 7. Kenyan Rift<br> 8. Lake Albert Rift (DRC and Uganda)<br> 9. Lake Kivu Rift<br> 10. Tanzanian Rift<br> 11. Northern Malawi<br> 12. Central Zambia<br> 13. Botswana/South Africa border<br> 14. Namibia </p></div></div><div style="text-transform: uppercase;line-height: 12px;font-size: 10px;letter-spacing: 0.75px;text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Source: S. Elbarbary <em>et al</em> / <em>Geothermal Energy</em> 2022</div></div><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Not surprisingly, many of these locations are within the East African Rift System, though high potential also exists in northern Africa in Morocco, Algeria and Tunisia, as well as in Liberia, Namibia, Zambia and South Africa. In many of those countries, the tectonics are such that using geothermal energy for direct heating — as is done at the Oserian flower farm and could be applied in a variety of settings, including industrial processing — may be more feasible than for electricity generation, Zaher says.</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Work beyond Kenya</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> KenGen has led on-the-ground geothermal exploration in a number of nearby countries. In addition to the drilling done in Ethiopia and Djibouti, surface studies to identify potential geothermal resources have been done in Sudan, Uganda, Rwanda, Tanzania, Zambia and the Comoros islands off the coast of Mozambique, Anna Mwangi says.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> In addition, KenGen — in collaboration with the Icelandic-based GRÓ Geothermal Training Programme and Kenya&#39;s Geothermal Development Company — has been training university students, energy professionals and government officials within East Africa on geothermal resource exploration and development, as well as power plant financing and management. With help from the World Bank, Kenya is also setting up the Geothermal Centre of Excellence, which will train professionals in the region once it opens in a couple years, Mwangi says.</p><div class="wp-block-sciencenews-content-sidebar" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><h3 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Deep-seated power</h3><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Comprehensive estimates of geothermal energy potential are not available for all East African countries. But the estimates that do exist suggest there&#39;s room for growth.</p><h5 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Geothermal energy potential versus installed capacity in select East African countries</h5><figure class="wp-block-table" style="font-size:14px"><table style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><tbody><tr><td> Country</td><td> Estimated potential (megawatts)</td><td> Installed capacity (megawatts)</td></tr><tr><td> קניה</td><td> 10,000</td><td> 963</td></tr><tr><td> Ethiopia</td><td> 10,000</td><td> 7.5</td></tr><tr><td> Tanzania</td><td> 5,000</td><td> 0</td></tr><tr><td> Uganda</td><td> 1,500</td><td> 0</td></tr><tr><td> Djibouti</td><td> 1,000</td><td> 0</td></tr><tr><td> Comoros</td><td> 30–50</td><td> 0 </td></tr></tbody></table></figure><div style="text-transform: uppercase;line-height: 12px;font-size: 10px;letter-spacing: 0.75px;text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Sources: KenGen, ThinkGeoEnergy</div></div><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Even with the right technical knowledge, though, it can take several years to go from exploration to geothermal energy production. In fact, even once a well has been drilled, it could still take up to a decade or more before a power plant is up and running. Funding constraints can be one barrier.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> This is what Kenyan engineers were faced with in 2012, Mwangi says. Wells had already been drilled, yet funding for putting up power plants to generate electricity at full capacity was still unavailable.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> This opened an avenue for experimentation. Typically, a power plant is supplied with water and steam from multiple wells at varying distances away. But a new wellhead approach, which hadn&#39;t been implemented anywhere in the world, allowed for the generation of power directly and quickly from a single well, at low cost, in the meantime.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Once a permanent power plant is ready to be built, the wellhead installation can be disassembled and taken to another well for the same purpose. About 85 megawatts of power have been produced this way in Kenya. “Such well-based power plants give us the early generation benefit, and generate revenue in the meantime,” Mwangi says. “Otherwise, these production wells would have remained capped awaiting construction and commissioning of a new power plant.” </p><figure class="wp-block-image alignwide size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1030" height="580" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/070123_geothermal_inline-5.jpg" alt="Photo of six zebras grazing near a pipe outside Olkaria. The air appears hazy around the pipe." class="wp-image-3129431" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/070123_geothermal_inline-5.jpg 1030w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/070123_geothermal_inline-5-680x383.jpg 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/070123_geothermal_inline-5-800x450.jpg 800w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/070123_geothermal_inline-5-330x186.jpg 330w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/070123_geothermal_inline-5-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1030px) 100vw, 1030px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3129431">Zebras gather near a tube carrying water that will be injected back into geothermal wells near Olkaria.</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3129431">ROBERTO SCHMIDT/AFP via Getty Images</span></figcaption></figure><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The costs of geothermal energy</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Even as interest and expertise in geothermal energy grow in East Africa, financial constraints remain an impediment. In Kenya, a single geothermal well can cost about $6 million to drill, and it can be another $300 million to build a roughly 165-megawatt plant.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “Up-front capital cost is high in geothermal, but running costs are limited,” says Le Scornet, the energy consultant.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The worldwide levelized cost of electricity, or LCOE, for a new geothermal installation in 2021 averaged $0.068 per kilowatt-hour, according to the International Renewable Energy Agency. The LCOE is the lowest price at which electricity can be sold for an energy project to break even. The figure takes into account lifetime costs, from building a plant to operating and maintaining it.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Geothermal&#39;s LCOE is about 40 percent higher than a new hydropower project or solar photovoltaic array, which have an LCOE of $0.048 per kilowatt-hour. An onshore wind farm is about half as expensive, at $0.033 per kilowatt-hour, but geothermal energy is slightly less costly than an offshore wind farm&#39;s $0.075 per kilowatt-hour. (For context, Kenya&#39;s per capita energy consumption in 2019 was about 168 kilowatt-hours, according to the UN) </p><figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="680" height="453" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/070123_geothermal_inline-4.jpg" alt="photo of a group of a people in yellow vests and hard hats standing next to a well in Olkaria" class="wp-image-3129430" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/070123_geothermal_inline-4.jpg 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/070123_geothermal_inline-4-575x383.jpg 575w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/070123_geothermal_inline-4-675x450.jpg 675w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/070123_geothermal_inline-4-279x186.jpg 279w" sizes="(max-width: 680px) 100vw, 680px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3129430">Journalists stand next to a geothermal well while on a tour of Olkaria.</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3129430">G. Kamadi</span></figcaption></figure><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Le Scornet says that stable financing mechanisms are needed to provide stability and reduce actual and perceived project risks. To tackle this challenge, the <a href="https://grmf-eastafrica.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Geothermal Risk Mitigation Facility</a> , funded by the European Union and the African Union, was set up in 2012 to cofinance surface studies and drilling programs.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “Support from project partners like the EU, for instance, and the African Development Bank can be instrumental, especially in countries with high debt levels and where competition with alternative projects presents obvious challenges for the development of new geothermal projects,” Le Scornet says.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> But not all costs are purely financial. Kenya&#39;s Olkaria project demonstrates one of the social costs. In developing and expanding the project over time, some members of the local Maasai community, a seminomadic pastoralist group, have been removed from their land, says Ben Ole Koissaba, lead consultant for Rarin Consulting Services, which champions for the land rights of Indigenous communities. Relocated people “have been cut off from the rest of the community,” says Koissaba, who is a member of the Maasai. And some of the housing built for them has not been culturally appropriate, he says.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> While some of the Maasai consider the displacement an outstanding issue, Kenya&#39;s geothermal exploration isn&#39;t slowing down. By 2025, the country aims to more than double its current production capacity to 2,500 megawatts.</p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/070123_geothermal_feat-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="197121" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/070123_geothermal_feat-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title> Coronal rain has been seen splashing on the sun</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/coronal-rain-sun-space<dc:creator><![CDATA[Lisa Grossman]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Wed, 12 Jul 2023 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Astronomy]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3129516 </guid><description><![CDATA[New images of the solar corona, taken by the Solar Orbiter probe, reveal bright fireball effects and upwelling induced by falling plasma droplets.]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<p>Plasma rain in the sun&#39;s atmosphere makes a splash when it lands. New observations from the European Space Agency&#39;s Solar Orbiter have revealed <a href="https://nam2023.org/press-releases/279-solar-astronomers-discover-shooting-stars-on-the-sun-s-corona" target="_blank" rel="noopener">previously unseen details</a> of how this coronal rain falls, including bright fireball effects and sudden upward surges in plasma.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “These are the highest resolution images we have ever obtained from the solar corona,” says solar physicist Patrick Antolin of Northumbria University in Newcastle upon Tyne, England. He presented the results at the National Astronomy Meeting in Cardiff, Wales, the week of July 3 and in a paper <a href="https://www.aanda.org/component/article?access=doi&amp;doi=10.1051/0004-6361/202346016" target="_blank" rel="noopener">to be published in <em>Astronomy &amp; Astrophysics</em></a> .</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The corona is the sun&#39;s wispy upper atmosphere, the sizzling tangle of plasma and magnetism that is visible during a <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/2019-total-solar-eclipse-south-america">total eclipse</a> ( <em>SN: 6/30/19</em> ). When clumps of scorching-hot plasma in the corona suddenly cool, they condense and fall toward the solar surface, just like water droplets in Earth&#39;s atmosphere. This <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/plasma-rain-sun-atmosphere-falls-surprising-places">coronal rain</a> has been observed before, but details of its formation and falling were fuzzy ( <em>SN: 5/24/18</em> ).</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/esas-solar-orbiter-will-be-the-first-spacecraft-to-study-the-suns-polar-zones">2020 launch of Solar Orbiter</a> promised to change that ( <em>SN: 2/9/20</em> ). The probe is making passes over the sun&#39;s unexplored polar regions, carrying high resolution cameras and other instruments to investigate solar mysteries. In late March 2022, Solar Orbiter made its closest approach to the sun to date, swooping within 49 million kilometers of our star — about a third of the distance between the sun and Earth.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> In images from the spacecraft taken during that close encounter, Antolin and colleagues discovered a new feature in the coronal rain. As the plasma raindrops fell, the region immediately below them brightened. The researchers think the brightening came from other plasma below the falling rain getting compressed and heated, similar to the way meteors in Earth&#39;s atmosphere can <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/meteor-explodes-over-russia">create fireballs</a> just ahead of the falling rocks ( <em>SN: 2/15/13</em> ).</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “This is the first time we&#39;ve seen that kind of compression from the rain falling this clearly,” says Emily Mason, a solar physicist at Predictive Science, a research company based in San Diego, who was not involved in the study. “The resolution just wasn&#39;t there before.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Antolin and colleagues also saw a rebound and upward flow of material after coronal raindrops smacked onto the chromosphere, the thin layer of plasma that lies between the sun&#39;s visible surface and the corona.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “This rain is as dense as the chromosphere,” Antolin says. “It can fall to the chromosphere and then make a splash.” This sort of splash was predicted in computer simulations but had never been observed on the actual sun before.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> On their own, the observations won&#39;t directly solve the biggest solar mysteries, like why the <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/2017-solar-eclipse-hot-corona">diffuse corona sizzles at millions of degrees</a> Celsius higher than the surface of the sun ( <em>SN: 8/20/17</em> ). But more observations of the same phenomena can help figure out details of the coronal environment, like how easily its gas compresses, or what its chemical composition is.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “We are not able to send a probe to the inner part of the corona because it&#39;s so hot,” Antolin says. “So we can use these observations as indirect probes of the local environment.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The observations are “an important litmus test for Solar Orbiter itself,” Mason says. “It&#39;s good to see what Solar Orbiter is capable of.”</p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/070723_lg_coronal_rain_feat-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="843965" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/070723_lg_coronal_rain_feat-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title> Wildfires aren&#39;t going away. Here&#39;s how smoke can affect your health</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/wildfire-smoke-health-air-quality-pollution<dc:creator><![CDATA[Meghan Rosen]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Wed, 12 Jul 2023 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Earth]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3129553 </guid><description><![CDATA[How does repeat exposure to wildfire smoke affect our health? Three experts weigh in on the massive air pollution fueled by Canada’s ongoing fires. ]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<p>North America&#39;s summer of smoke may well be a harbinger of what&#39;s to come. As record-breaking wildfires in Canada continue to sweep across the land, smoke has been suffusing the skies for more and more people. Frequent fires like these can mean more smoke inhaled, and over longer periods of time.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> What are the health consequences of breathing in this fumy miasma? I asked three experts.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Air pollution exposure scientist Jeffrey Brook&#39;s office at the University of Toronto is roughly 500 kilometers from some of the raging blazes that have engulfed more than 8 million hectares in Canada this year. Even at that distance, the air has been bad, he says, shrouding the city in noxious gasses and tiny particles of burned biomass. “It&#39;s the worst particulate matter air quality I&#39;ve seen in 30 years or more,” Brook says.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> When I reach him, he&#39;s on a boat on the eastern end of Lake Ontario. All around, the air is hazy from wildfire smoke; he can just make out the shoreline. Driving there from Toronto, Brook felt like he was moving through a curtain, he says.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Some 800 kilometers south, where atmospheric scientist Katelyn O&#39;Dell works at George Washington University in Washington, DC, the scene has been less apocalyptic, but it can change abruptly. Some days, you can see and smell smoke in the air, and “the sky doesn&#39;t even look blue,” she says.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> From across the continent, at the British Columbia Centre for Disease Control in Vancouver, environmental epidemiologist Sarah Henderson says those smoky scenes look all too familiar. “We&#39;re no strangers to wildfire smoke,” she says. In previous years, the region has seen extreme episodes driven by fires in the Pacific Northwest.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> These three scientists have been studying the health effects of wildfire smoke for years. They talked with me about <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/wildfire-smoke-health-risks-air-quality-pollution">how smoke impacts our health, what questions remain</a> and what researchers might be able to learn from the current fires <em>(SN: 9/18/20)</em> . Our conversations have been edited for brevity and clarity.</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Why are scientists focusing on wildfire smoke?</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <strong>O&#39;Dell:</strong> The wildfire season has been expanding, so it&#39;s impacting us more throughout the year. [And] wildfire smoke is different than the typical urban smog that has been studied historically.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> [That smog], emissions from traffic and industry, has been decreasing due to successful emissions control policies — and those are projected to continue to decrease. Because those are going down and wildfire smoke is going up, it&#39;s really important for us to study wildfire smoke and its impacts on health. </p><figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><iframe loading="lazy" title="Wildfire smoke forecast July 10-13, 2023 | חדשות המדע" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/8bNHfi2rNiU?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe></div><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> In the coming days, wildfire smoke may continue to sweep across Canada and the northeastern and midwestern United States. The forecast shown predicts when and where particulate matter 2.5 microns and smaller may occur, with darker colors indicating more air pollution. Credit: <a href="https://firesmoke.ca/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">BlueSky Canada</a></figcaption></figure><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> How can wildfire smoke affect people&#39;s health?</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <strong>Henderson:</strong> Wildfire smoke is a really complex form of air pollution. And we have decades of research that tells us exposure to air pollution isn&#39;t good for us.<strong></strong></p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> What we know at this point is that when smoke is occurring, <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/wildfire-health-risks-air-smoke-west-east-united-states">there are measurable effects</a> in the population almost immediately <em>(SN: 6/17/22)</em> . Respiratory effects, especially for people with preexisting respiratory conditions, such as asthma and COPD [chronic obstructive pulmonary disease], are the first things to happen. We generally see that these people need more of their rescue medications, meaning that their airways are closing up.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The magnitude of that impact in those populations seems to be larger for wildfire smoke than for other types of air pollution. We [also] see small detriments to cognitive performance.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> And then [there&#39;s] quite a bit of evidence around impacts to the developing fetus. There&#39;s risk of preterm birth and reductions in birth weight for infants who are exposed in utero.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <strong>Brook:</strong> People will say, “Oh, it&#39;s natural. It&#39;s campfire smoke, it&#39;s OK.” No, it&#39;s not. [Wildfire smoke] contains some of the same toxicants that we think about all the time as bad ones in air pollution.</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> What&#39;s in wildfire smoke?</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <strong>O&#39;Dell:</strong> There are multiple pollutants in wildfire smoke that can impact health, but the one that we&#39;re typically most concerned with is the fine particulate matter, or PM 2.5. PM 2.5 is a particle in the air that is less than 2.5 micrometers in diameter.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <strong>Henderson:</strong> Those [are] particles that can travel deep into the lungs.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <strong>O&#39;Dell:</strong> Wildfire smoke has a lot of gases in it too. Things like formaldehyde, benzene and sometimes ozone.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/covid19-coronavirus-pandemic-air-pollution-ozone-shutdown">Ozone negatively impacts respiratory health</a> <em>(SN: 1/4/21)</em> . It&#39;s unclear right now if benzene and formaldehyde are often at [dangerous] levels in smoke plumes, but we do know these pollutants at certain levels can negatively impact health from both short-term and long-term exposure.</p><div class="wp-block-sciencenews-content-sidebar" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><h3 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Gauging air quality<strong></strong></h3><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The Air Quality Index, or AQI, ranges from 0 to 500, based on the amount of pollution in the air at a given time. Ground-level ozone, particulate matter (both PM <sub>10</sub> and PM <sub>2.5</sub> ), carbon monoxide, sulfur dioxide and nitrogen dioxide are the primary parameters considered in the index. Code orange (above a score of 100) is unhealthy for people in sensitive groups. Code red and above (151–500) is unhealthy for everyone. </p><figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="680" height="90" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071023_mr_wildfire-smoke-healtheffects_inline2.jpg" alt="a color scale showing the air quality index: Good (green 0-5); Moderate (yellow 51-100); Unhealthy for sensitive groups (Orange 101-150); Unhealthy (Red 151-200); Very unhealthy (Purple 201-300); Hazardous (Brown 301-500)" class="wp-image-3129556" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071023_mr_wildfire-smoke-healtheffects_inline2.jpg 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071023_mr_wildfire-smoke-healtheffects_inline2-330x44.jpg 330w" sizes="(max-width: 680px) 100vw, 680px" /><figcaption> <span class="credit wp-credit-3129556">T. Tibbitts</span> </figcaption></figure><div style="text-transform: uppercase;line-height: 12px;font-size: 10px;letter-spacing: 0.75px;text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Source: <a href="https://www.airnow.gov/aqi/aqi-basics/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Airnow.gov</a></div></div><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> What questions do researchers still have about the health effects of wildfire smoke?</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <strong>O&#39;Dell:</strong> If you have a wave of wildfire smoke multiple times every summer, how does that affect your health in the long term? It&#39;s a very important question [and] an open area of research right now.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <strong>Henderson:</strong> It&#39;s a slightly more challenging question to address because you might have a population that&#39;s exposed for a couple of weeks, at a really high magnitude for one summer, and then for the next three summers, there&#39;s no smoke and everything&#39;s fine.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> That intermittent episodic nature of exposure might mean that [the longer-term effects of wildfire smoke] are quite different from the more steady types of air pollution that affect our air quality, day in and day out.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> We&#39;re still learning about what that means. We might be seeing kids, if they are exposed very early in life, [with] a lifelong detriment to their lung function.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <strong>Brook:</strong> What if you happen to be pregnant and the fetus is at a particularly important part of development? If it&#39;s getting really high [smoke] exposure coupled with stress because the mom&#39;s worried about the high exposure, [could] that alter how certain organs – lungs, brain, heart – develop? אנחנו לא יודעים.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <strong>O&#39;Dell:</strong> [Another] open question is how the health impacts of fresh smoke differ from old smoke [ <a href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/full/10.1021/acs.est.0c04497" target="_blank" rel="noopener">more than three days old</a> ]. There are a few reasons [the impacts] might be different, one being chemical changes in the smoke itself — smoke changes as it travels through the atmosphere. Another major factor is the public&#39;s awareness of smoke. If you live close to where the fire is burning, you&#39;re very aware that there is likely smoke. But [people] farther away, might be less aware and maybe take less action to protect their own health.</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> What can we learn from the current wildfires?</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <strong>O&#39;Dell:</strong> These fires are impacting a different population than have historically been predominantly studied. A lot of the wildfire and health studies have occurred in the western United States. This event that we&#39;re experiencing right now [will] hopefully allow us to have a greater understanding of how wildfire smoke might impact people in the eastern states.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> There are many factors that may lead to a different health response for those out east compared with those out west, including different baseline disease rates or levels of pre-existing conditions, different responses to smoke, level of outdoor activity, et cetera.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <strong>Henderson:</strong> What we need [are] populations that are resilient to these exposures, populations that know how to take protective measures, and policies that look at how we keep smoke out of the indoor environment to ensure that people are protected when they&#39;re indoors. All of those types of things are going to allow us to be resilient to the smoke exposures in the decades ahead.</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> What can people do to protect themselves from wildfire smoke?</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <strong>Henderson:</strong> [In our current lifestyle], the vast majority of us spend the vast majority of our time inside. If we are effectively reducing smoke in the indoor environment, we are effectively protecting our health for about 90 percent of the time.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> We highly recommend that you have some sort of air cleaning device running in at least one room of the home so that you have kind of a smoke-free haven — especially the bedroom because you&#39;re probably going to be there for at least eight hours of the day.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Then we can look to what happens when you&#39;re outdoors. <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/double-mask-fit-reduce-coronavirus-exposure-covid-19-pandemic">A well-fitted respirator type mask like an N95 or KN95</a> will effectively filter the particles of wildfire smoke out and probably some of the gases as well <em>(SN: 2/12/21)</em> .</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <strong>O&#39;Dell:</strong> It&#39;s always a good idea to check the local air quality before you undergo any outdoor activity, and then adjust your behavior accordingly. If you really need to be outside, maybe go for a walk instead of a run, and wear a mask if it&#39;s really bad. And if you&#39;re in an extra-sensitive group — children, the elderly, people with preexisting conditions — you might choose to stay indoors on days that are especially smoky.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> At the local government level, it&#39;s good to have plans in place for when there is smoke. Do schools cancel recess? Do we open clean-air shelters for people who aren&#39;t able to have clean air in their homes — or maybe don&#39;t have a home — to protect that vulnerable set of the population?</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <strong>Brook:</strong> A key principle we always follow in environmental protection is to set our policies to protect the most vulnerable. It&#39;s always good to be cautious. If you&#39;re healthy, smoke is a little piece of many things in your life that impact your health. But if you&#39;re compromised, maybe you&#39;ve got a respiratory infection or just had a heart attack or some other condition, smoke could really hinder [your] recovery. <strong>&nbsp;</strong></p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> How worried should we be about wildfire smoke?</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <strong>Brook:</strong> We should be more worried about climate change. When you look at Canada, we&#39;ve had fire impacts from coast to coast this year. I&#39;ve never seen that. It&#39;s just unprecedented. It&#39;s a wake-up call. Like, hey folks, you&#39;ve been hearing that these things are going to happen. And look, they&#39;re happening sooner, they&#39;re happening faster. Look at your air. This is not just bad luck.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <strong>O&#39;Dell:</strong> In the western United States and even in parts of Canada, [wildfires] have been increasing over the past several decades due to several factors. In the United States, one [factor is] historical fire suppression tactics, but another [is] anthropogenic <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/wildfire-smoke-us-east-coast-climate">climate change</a> <em>(SN: 6/9/23).</em> And those increases in fires, and the smoke that they emit, is expected to continue to increase across the coming century.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <strong>Henderson:</strong> There are people who live their daily lives in cities that are about as polluted as some of the cities we&#39;ve seen in eastern North America over the past month. On one hand, humans are quite resilient to air pollution exposure, and on the other hand, air pollution exposure is not good for people. We need to find a balance somewhere in the middle that doesn&#39;t make people feel panicked, [and] makes them feel empowered to make the best possible decisions for themselves in their health.</p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071023_mr_wildfire-smoke-healtheffects_feat-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="303247" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071023_mr_wildfire-smoke-healtheffects_feat-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title> Canada&#39;s Crawford Lake could mark the beginning of the Anthropocene</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/canada-crawford-lake-beginning-anthropocene<dc:creator><![CDATA[McKenzie Prillaman]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Tue, 11 Jul 2023 17:00:00 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Climate]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3129548 </guid><description><![CDATA[The mud of a Canadian lake holds an extremely precise record of humans’ influence on Earth. But the Anthropocene isn’t an official geologic epoch yet.]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<p>Scientists are one step closer to defining a new chapter in geology, one in which humans have become the dominant driver of Earth&#39;s climate and environment.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Out of 12 locations around the world, Crawford Lake in Ontario, Canada, has been selected as the site that would mark the official beginning of the Anthropocene, a proposed geologic epoch starting in the 1950s, researchers announced at a July 11 news conference during the <a href="https://climate-conference.mpg.de/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Max Planck Society Conference for a Sustainable Anthropocene</a> in Berlin.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The lake bottom&#39;s sediments hold one of the most precise records of humans&#39; alteration of Earth, including upticks in plutonium from nuclear weapons testing, ash from burning fossil fuels as well as heavy metals and microplastics.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> But the Anthropocene isn&#39;t an official geologic epoch yet. Now, several more committees must approve of the proposed epoch before it can be added to the geologic time scale. Doing so would end the nearly 12,000-year-old Holocene Epoch, which encompasses the rise of humankind since the last ice age.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Scientists first started using the term <em>Anthropocene</em> in the early 2000s to refer to the ongoing time of humans altering the planet on a global scale. Although framed in terms of geology, the Anthropocene lacked a formal geologic definition.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Still, the idea spread. “It exploded so quickly into other disciplines without it being defined,” says earth scientist Simon Turner of University College London. So “that&#39;s what we&#39;ve been trying to do ever since.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> In 2009, the International Commission on Stratigraphy, the scientific group responsible for defining geologic time, convened a committee to characterize the Anthropocene and see whether it deserved a spot on the geologic time scale. Over a decade later, that committee has now chosen Crawford Lake out of the 12 candidate sites as the Anthropocene&#39;s “Global Boundary Stratotype Section and Point,” a reference site that shows a change in its rock, ice or other layers to mark the beginning of a new geologic time.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> From coral to ice to peat, each of the candidate sites holds a remarkable record of human activity in its layers. Selecting Crawford Lake was “like choosing a favorite child,” says Turner, secretary and a voting member of the committee.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Among the locations, Crawford Lake&#39;s muddy layers have trapped one of the most precise histories of human activity. Each summer, the water&#39;s <a href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/full/10.1177/20530196221149281" target="_blank" rel="noopener">pH and warm temperatures cause mineral crystals to form near the top of the water</a> . The crystals fall to the lake&#39;s bottom like snow, where they lay undisturbed. “You get these lovely stripes,” Turner says. “And you can resolve what year [they&#39;re from] pretty much by counting backwards from the surface layer, like a tree ring.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The layers capture a sharp rise in <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/nuclear-blasts-other-human-activity-signal-new-epoch-anthropocene">radioactivity and other evidence of human activity starting in the early 1950s</a> ( <em>SN: 9/25/16</em> ).</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> But not all scientists agree that the Anthropocene began merely 70 years ago, or that it should be defined as a geologic term at all. “Any time you draw a hard line in the geologic record or in any other system, you&#39;re creating a binary — there&#39;s a before and there&#39;s an after,” says paleoecologist Jacquelyn Gill of the University of Maine in Orono. “We know human impacts began well before 1950.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Retaining an informal and flexible concept, like what&#39;s used now in disciplines beyond geology, might be more beneficial, she adds. “It&#39;s more powerful as a tool in that way,” Gill says, “than it is to try to confine it or constrain it to a narrow definition that then creates confusion about everything that came before.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Still, attempting to define the Anthropocene in geologic terms underscores humanity&#39;s rapid and intense impact on the planet, Turner says. “We&#39;ve become a geological force.”</p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071123_MP_geology-new-chapter_feat-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="281340" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071123_MP_geology-new-chapter_feat-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title> This &#39;thermal cloak&#39; keeps spaces from getting either too hot or cold</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/thermal-cloak-material-temperature<dc:creator><![CDATA[Skyler Ware]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Tue, 11 Jul 2023 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Materials Science]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3129532 </guid><description><![CDATA[A new thermal fabric prototype could help keep cars, buildings and other spaces a comfortable temperature during heat waves while reducing CO₂ emissions. ]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<p>If you&#39;ve ever burned your hands on a car steering wheel, you know how hot the inside of a car can get on a summer day. But a new fabric could one day help cars and other objects stay cool in the summer and warm in the winter.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Researchers created a prototype of the fabric, which <a href="https://cell.com/device/fulltext/S2666-9986(23)00008-X" target="_blank" rel="noopener">acts as a “thermal cloak”</a> that keeps the space underneath it from getting too hot or too cold. The cloak, described in the July 11 <em>Device</em> , doesn&#39;t require an external power source, which could <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/reflective-paint-could-keep-sunbaked-buildings-cool">reduce energy consumption</a> associated with heating and cooling ( <em>SN: 9/28/18)</em> .</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Globally, heating and cooling make up <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S235248472101427X#:~:text=In%20summary%2C%20HVAC%20consumption%20represents,as%20the%20UE%20or%20Russia." target="_blank" rel="noopener">38 percent of energy use in buildings and 12 percent of total energy consumption</a> . Materials like this thermal cloak could help keep us comfortable during heat waves while reducing carbon dioxide emissions associated with electricity used in temperature control, says Aaswath Raman, an applied physicist at UCLA who was not involved in the study.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> In the new study, Kehang Cui, an engineer at Shanghai Jiao Tong University, and colleagues built the cloak using two layers. The outer layer is made of white silica fibers that reflect visible light, coated with hexagonal boron nitride, a ceramic material that reflects ultraviolet light and helps dissipate heat. Together, the silica fibers and boron nitride reflect 96 percent of the sunlight that hits the fabric. At the same time, the outer layer absorbs heat from the surrounding area and emits that energy as infrared light, which also lowers the temperature under the cloak through a process called radiative cooling.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Though the outer layer keeps the space under the cloak cooler for longer than an uncovered area, the cloaked space slowly warms up throughout the day. The inner layer, made of aluminum foil, keeps the space warm at night by trapping some of that heat inside, similar to an insulating survival blanket.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The researchers tested the cloak material&#39;s durability under several extreme conditions. They baked the fabric at 800° Celsius, just about hot enough to melt table salt. They also exposed it to extreme cold by dunking it in liquid nitrogen, subjected it to the same amount of vibration as a rocket launch, doused it in acid and blasted it with fire from a butane torch — all with virtually no changes to the material&#39;s structure or performance. This extreme durability might lend itself to use in spacecraft or extraterrestrial environments, the team says.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> To see the fabric in action, Cui and colleagues built a full-size prototype cloak and tested it on an electric car. On a summer day in Shanghai, the cloak kept the car at about 23° C — up to 8 degrees C lower than the outside temperature and 28 degrees C lower than the inside of an uncloaked car. The cloak also kept the car about 5 degrees C warmer than the outside air on a winter night.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The cloak “definitely shows the capability of saving energy, but the next step is that we want to demonstrate it in even larger-scale field tests [such as rooftops] to see the impact on our daily lives,” Cui says.</p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071023_sw_thermal-cloak_feat-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="322097" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/071023_sw_thermal-cloak_feat-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title> Lauren Schroeder looks beyond natural selection to rethink human evolution</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/human-evolution-lauren-schroeder-scientists-to-watch<dc:creator><![CDATA[Anna Gibbs]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Tue, 11 Jul 2023 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Humans]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3129177 </guid><description><![CDATA[Paleoanthropologists studying the fossil record have long focused on natural selection, but other processes play a big role too. ]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<p>Lauren Schroeder has loved dinosaurs since age 3 and bones since she was 10. In her second year of university, she started studying the early evolution of the <em>Homo</em> genus and it turned into her Ph.D. Many fossils have taken her breath away, she says, but a 2-million-year-old <em>Homo habilis</em> skull holds such a special place in her heart that it&#39;s tattooed on her forearm.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “I think I can safely say that I&#39;m doing what I wanted to do,” she says. </p><div class="wp-block-image  has-alignleft" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><figure class="alignleft size-thumbnail"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="186" height="186" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/2023-SN10-bug_REV-186x186.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-3124149" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/2023-SN10-bug_REV-186x186.jpg 186w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/2023-SN10-bug_REV-214x214.jpg 214w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/2023-SN10-bug_REV.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 186px) 100vw, 186px" /></figure></div><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> As a paleoanthropologist at the University of Toronto, Schroeder works to untangle the various processes by which humans have evolved. One such process, natural selection, is adaptive: Changes in an organism&#39;s features make it more suited to its environment. But some changes are not selected for, or even totally random. Despite the existence of “nonadaptive” processes, paleoanthropology <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0047248422001567?via%3Dihub" target="_blank" rel="noopener">has often attributed</a> evolutionary changes in hominids to adaptation alone.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> While a Ph.D. student at the University of Cape Town in South Africa, Schroeder questioned the emphasis on natural selection to explain changes seen in the fossil record. “It was very clear that something was missing,” she says. Not much research had considered the role played by nonadaptive processes, such as genetic drift and gene flow. “That was really the big moment for me … these are important questions that haven&#39;t really been asked. I should try to answer them.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Since then, her research has suggested that nonadaptive processes play a much bigger role in evolution than previously realized.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “All aspects of Lauren&#39;s research have been consequential for the discipline,” says Benjamin Auerbach, a biological anthropologist at the University of Tennessee, Knoxville. “We&#39;re witnessing maybe a change in the way we talk about human evolution.”</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The importance of chance</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Schroeder&#39;s research centers around questions of how and why body features in humans (or other animals) — called “morphology” — came to be.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> They are hard questions to answer, in part because fossils often don&#39;t contain usable DNA. Paleoanthropologists rely on patterns in the morphology, established theory and statistical analyses to try to understand the evolutionary processes at play. It&#39;s math “all the way through,” Schroeder says — which is good, because she adores math.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Before the math, Schroeder measures the features of the fossils. During her Ph.D. research, she traveled across Africa to scan and analyze fossil <em>Homo</em> skulls dating from 2.8 million years ago until just tens of thousands of years ago. Some features of the skulls showed a strong adaptive signal, including the jaw; that means that early <em>Homo</em> jaw shape probably evolved via natural selection, driven by a changing diet.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> But surprisingly, when Schroeder looked at the results for the <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S004724841630152X?casa_token=sK6RMWS3q8UAAAAA:8FlfRoRlTg_7tEoFdQ63zifQXHv_JpzFHDW90IYcBrjVB8_ptd8pA2iEHNTZovoFgwTWbMoJ4Q" target="_blank" rel="noopener">shape of braincases</a> across the <em>Homo</em> genus, genetic drift appeared to be at play, she reported in 2017 in the <em>Journal of Human Evolution.</em> A nonadaptive process, genetic drift is the loss of genetic variation in a population due to the chance disappearance of certain genes. In other words, the braincase shape evolved just because. </p><figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="680" height="496" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Lauren-Schroeder_inline.jpg" alt="A photo of a Homo habilis skull on a black background." class="wp-image-3129182" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Lauren-Schroeder_inline.jpg 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Lauren-Schroeder_inline-525x383.jpg 525w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Lauren-Schroeder_inline-617x450.jpg 617w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Lauren-Schroeder_inline-255x186.jpg 255w" sizes="(max-width: 680px) 100vw, 680px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3129182">During her Ph.D. work, Lauren Schroeder analyzed this <em>Homo habilis</em> skull and other fossils to better understand how the human skull evolved.</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3129182">Chip Clark, Smithsonian Institution</span></figcaption></figure><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Schroeder also turns to today&#39;s animals to better understand the evolution of our ancestors. Another nonadaptive process — gene flow — occurs when genes spread from one population to another through breeding, including when two species hybridize. Hybrids in the fossil record could thus offer clues to evolutionary processes. But there&#39;s currently no good way to determine whether a fossil represents a hybrid.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Schroeder aims to change that by developing a framework based on morphological patterns in living hybrids. So far she&#39;s focused on the <a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/jmor.21417" target="_blank" rel="noopener">skulls of coyote-wolf hybrids</a> (chosen in part because Schroeder loves dogs), and she&#39;s identified traits consistent with other hybrids, she and colleagues reported in 2021 in <em>Journal of Morphology</em> , including a higher incidence of dental and other anomalies.</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Rewriting narratives</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Schroeder, who grew up in South Africa, remembers noticing as early as her undergraduate years that most of the paleoanthropological research in her country was conducted by foreign researchers. In fact, <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0047248422001567?via%3Dihub#fig5" target="_blank" rel="noopener">less than 5 percent of papers</a> published in the <em>Journal of Human Evolution</em> from 2016 to 2021 were authored by African researchers, Schroeder reported in the journal this past January.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Additionally, “even though most of it is based in Africa, paleoanthropology is so white,” she says. As a Black African woman, “it was such a lonely place, actually, for a long time.” Schroeder has struggled to publish papers, received sexist reviews on papers and experienced instances of blatant racism.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Some things have improved. At American Association of Biological Anthropologists conferences, she used to be able to count the number of Black people on two hands, she says. When she attended this past May, she was one of many. But there is still a long way to go. She credits her mentors for helping her get through the tough early years and the <a href="https://www.blackinbioanth.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Black in BioAnth Collective</a> for working to transform the field.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “It&#39;s not an easy journey getting to where she is, but she&#39;s there,” says Rebecca Ackermann, Schroeder&#39;s Ph.D. adviser at the University of Cape Town. “And so now the world is her oyster.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Schroeder recently secured tenure at the University of Toronto. As the first in her family to attend university, it means a lot to her and her parents. “They don&#39;t necessarily get everything I do,” she laughs. But “we&#39;re in disbelief that I&#39;ve gotten here.”</p><hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" /><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <em>Lauren Schroeder is one of this year&#39;s</em> <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/collections/sn-10-scientists-to-watch"><em>SN 10: Scientists to Watch</em></a> <em>, our list of 10 early and mid-career scientists who are making extraordinary contributions to their field. We&#39;ll be rolling out the full list throughout 2023.</em></p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <em>Want to nominate someone for the SN 10? Send their name, affiliation and a few sentences about them and their work to</em> <a href="mailto:sn10@sciencenews.org"><em>sn10@sciencenews.org</em></a> <em>.</em></p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Lauren-Schroeder_feat-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="629681" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Lauren-Schroeder_feat-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item></channel></rss>