<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/" xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/" xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"><channel><title> חדשות המדע </title><atom:link href="https://www.sciencenews.org/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org<description> עיתונאות עצמאית מאז 1921</description><lastbuilddate> שני, 25 בספטמבר 2023 15:10:48 +0000</lastbuilddate><language> en-US</language><sy:updateperiod> מדי שעה</sy:updateperiod><sy:updatefrequency> 1</sy:updatefrequency><generator> https://wordpress.org/?v=6.2.2</generator><item><title> הנה כמה אנשים נגועים בנגיף הקורונה עשויים לנשוף</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/coronavirus-infected-covid-19-exhale<dc:creator><![CDATA[Saima S. Iqbal]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Mon, 25 Sep 2023 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Health & Medicine]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3131748 </guid><description><![CDATA[Just breathing naturally can lead people with COVID-19 to emit dozens of copies of viral RNA a minute and that can persist for eight days, a study finds.]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<p>הנגיף שגורם ל-COVID-19 מתפשט באוויר. אבל כמה אנשים נושמים וירוסים במהלך ההדבקה אינה מוגדרת היטב.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> כדי להצמיד את המספרים, חוקר הריח גרגורי ליין ועמיתיו ניתחו למעלה מ-300 דגימות נשימה מ-43 אנשים עם COVID-19, בעקבותיהם במשך כמעט שלושה שבועות. הרמות השתנו בין ובתוך אנשים, אבל חלק מהאנשים משילים הרבה, ומשחררים יותר מ-800 עותקים של RNA ויראלי בדקה לפעמים.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> בממוצע, <a href="https://www.medrxiv.org/content/10.1101/2023.09.06.23295138v1.full" target="_blank" rel="noopener">המשתתפים נשפו 80 עותקים לדקה</a> במשך שמונה ימים שלמים לאחר שהחלו הסימפטומים, כך מדווח הצוות ב-8 בספטמבר ב-preprint שפורסם ב-medRxiv.org. רק לאחר נקודה זו ירדו החלקיקים הנגיפים לרמות כמעט בלתי ניתנות לזיהוי.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> ליין, מבית הספר לרפואה של אוניברסיטת נורת&#39;ווסטרן פיינברג בשיקגו, ועמיתיו עדיין צריכים לאשר איזה אחוז מה-RNA הנגיפי הננשף הזה מגיע מוירוסים שעדיין יכולים להתרבות בגוף של אדם אחר. ומדענים עדיין לא יודעים כמה נגיף נדרש לזיהום.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> אבל, בהתבסס על הנתונים החדשים, הצוות מעריך ששפך גבוה עלול לנשוף מספיק וירוס כדי להדביק מישהו בחלל סגור תוך כ-20 שניות, מה שהופך אפילו נסיעה במעלית למסוכנת. עם נשירה ממוצעת, ההדבקה יכולה להימשך קצת פחות מארבע דקות.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> המחקר החדש, שיתפרסם ב- <em>eLife</em> , מספק מידע רב ערך שגם מחקרי משטח האף וגם <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/new-device-detect-coronavirus-air">ניסויי אירוסול חד-פעמיים</a> אינם יכולים, אומרת חוקרת מחלות זיהומיות קריסטן קולמן ( <em>SN: 7/16/23</em> ). ספוגיות מדגימות רק חלק אחד של דרכי הנשימה. וניסויי אירוסול רבים מודדים את כמות<a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/covid-coronavirus-aerosol-droplets-airborne-evolution">הווירוסים שאנשים פולטים בזמן דיבור, שירה או קריאה בקול</a> , כמו גם בזמן נשימה, בנקודה אחת בלבד במהלך ההדבקה <em>(SN: 08/17/21)</em> .</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> הצוות של ליין הגה כלי פשוט וזול - בעצם פיית פלסטיק המחוברת לצינור סגור - שהמשתתפים לקחו איתם הביתה ונשמו לתוכו במשך 10 דקות בכל פעם. זה אפשר לצוות לאסוף בקלות דגימות על פני תקופה ממושכת ולעקוב אחר האופן שבו הפליטות השתנו במהלך ההדבקה. אבל הכלי המאולתר חסר את הדיוק של מכונות מתקדמות במעבדות ובבתי חולים, אומר קולמן, מבית הספר לבריאות הציבור של אוניברסיטת מרילנד בקולג&#39; פארק. אפילו העלייה של 876 עותקי RNA ויראלי לדקה שנראתה במחקר החדש עשויה להיות הערכת חסר בכמה סדרי גודל, היא אומרת.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> במחקר החדש, אלו שדיווחו על תסמינים חמורים יותר נטו לפלוט יותר וירוסים. עם זאת, אפילו אנשים אסימפטומטיים או אנשים עם מקרים קלים נשפו החוצה כמויות ניכרות של RNA ויראלי. גם אנשים מחוסנים וגם לא מחוסנים נשפו רמות דומות.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> המרכז האמריקאי לבקרת מחלות ומניעתן ממליץ כעת לאנשים החולים באורח קל או א-סימפטומטי לבודד לפחות חמישה ימים ולאחר מכן להסתיר חמישה ימים נוספים. ליין היה מציע עצות שונות: &quot;אם החברים או המשפחה שלי היו שואלים אותי, הייתי אומר שאתה צריך לבודד עד היום השמיני.&quot;</p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/091923_si_covid-transmission_feat-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="48432" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/091923_si_covid-transmission_feat-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title> &#39;הרגע השביר שלנו&#39; מוצא שיעורים מודרניים בהיסטוריה של האקלים של כדור הארץ</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/fragile-moment-book-earth-history-climate<dc:creator><![CDATA[Luis Melecio-Zambrano]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Mon, 25 Sep 2023 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Climate]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3131400 </guid><description><![CDATA[Michael Mann’s latest book, Our Fragile Moment, looks through Earth’s history to understand the current climate crisis.]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[



<div class="wp-block-image  has-alignleft"><figure class="alignleft size-medium is-resized"><a href="https://bookshop.org/a/21798/9781541702899" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><img decoding="async" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_reviews_inline-247x383.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-3131402" width="185" height="287" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_reviews_inline-247x383.jpg 247w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_reviews_inline-290x450.jpg 290w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_reviews_inline-120x186.jpg 120w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_reviews_inline-374x580.jpg 374w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_reviews_inline-501x776.jpg 501w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_reviews_inline.jpg 680w" sizes="(max-width: 185px) 100vw, 185px" /></a></figure></div><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <a href="https://bookshop.org/a/21798/9781541702899" target="_blank" rel="noopener">הרגע השביר שלנו</a><br> <em>מייקל מאן</em><br> <em>Public Affairs, $30</em></p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> לפני יותר מארבעה אלפי שנים, בימיה האחרונים של האימפריה האכדית במסופוטמיה, בצורת שטפה את האזור, שפקדה אדמות רחוקות כמו יוון ומה שהיא כיום פקיסטן. ככל הנראה מונע על ידי התפרצות של הר געש מרוחק, האקלים המתייבש הרס את החקלאות המקומית. טקסט עכשווי, <em>&quot;קללת אכד&quot;</em> , ציין כי &quot;שטחי העיבוד הגדולים לא הניבו תבואה... המטעים המושקים לא הניבו סירופ או יין, עננים עבים לא ירדו גשם&quot;.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> כשאדמות חקלאיות ששגשגו פעם קרסו בחלק הצפוני של האימפריה, אנשים ברחו דרומה. תגובת האכדים הדרומיים? בנו חומה באורך של יותר מ-150 קילומטרים בין נהרות החידקל והפרת, חוסמת כניסה לכל מהגרים. זמן קצר לאחר מכן, האימפריה הראשונה של ההיסטוריה התפוררה, מתה מצמא בערש הציוויליזציה.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> מערכות אקלים ותרבויות יציבות רק עד נקודה מסוימת. ברגע <em>השביר שלנו</em> , מדען האקלים מייקל מאן מזכיר לנו שהיום אנחנו פורצים את הגבולות של שניהם.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> בספר, מאן מסתכל אחורה על פרקים של שינויי אקלים עולמיים ב-4.5 מיליארד השנים האחרונות, מתקופות של חום קטלני ועד שממה של קרח נרחב. בכל מקרה, הוא מפיק לקחים על מה שקורה לכדור הארץ בתקופות של שינוי אקלים. לפעמים, התוצאה היא <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/volcanic-activity-convicted-permian-extinction">הכחדות המוניות דרמטיות</a> או תהפוכות גיאולוגיות ( <em>SN: 28/8/15</em> ). פעמים אחרות, כמו אצל האכדים, זו קריסה חברתית.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> מערכת האקלים של כדור הארץ כוללת כוחות ויסות הנוטים לחצץ נגד שינויים קטנים באקלים; כיפות קרח ועננים נמוכים מחזירים את אור השמש ועוזרים לקרר את כדור הארץ, למשל. אבל אם נדחף רחוק מדי, כוחות הוויסות עלולים להיות מוצפים, ולגרום לאקלים לצאת משליטה.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> זה היה המקרה לפני 55 מיליון שנה. כאשר מערך קבוע של התפרצויות געשיות פלט פחמן דו חמצני לאוויר, כדור הארץ התחמם. ייתכן שהחום תרם לעננים דקים יותר ופחות מחזירי אור. זה בתורו היה עושה את כוכב הלכת חם עוד יותר. בסופו של דבר, העננים הנמוכים נעלמו, והטמפרטורות העולמיות הממוצעות זינקו ל-32° צלזיוס (90° פרנהייט) במה שמכונה <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/eocene-temperature-spike-caused-half-much-co2-once-thought">חממה כדור הארץ</a> ( <em>SN: 11/3/15</em> ).</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> כיום, עם פליטת גזי חממה בלתי מבוקרת, אנו עשויים להתמודד עם ספירלה דומה, אם כי פחות מחממת, עם <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/greenland-hinterlands-leaking-ice">היעלמות כיפות הקרח המשקפות שלנו</a> ( <em>SN: 11/9/22</em> ).</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> אבל מה שמייחד את שינוי האקלים הנוכחי הוא המקור שלו - המין האנושי - והיכולת שלנו לעצור אותם. זוהי תועלת ייחודית לאקלים המשתנה שלנו. זה בא עם האשמה, אבל זה בא גם עם סוכנות.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> הסוכנות הזו היא מקור חשוב לתקווה עבור מאן. כיפות קרח נמסות עלולה להעלות את פני הים ולעקור כ-40% מהאוכלוסייה העולמית. <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/climate-deadly-extreme-temperature-predictions-already-here">חום עולה עלול להפוך חלקי כדור הארץ לבלתי ראויים למגורים</a> ( <em>SN: 5/8/20</em> ). אבל אם נפעל, נוכל לשמר עולם שנראה מאוד כמו שלנו. הגבול אינו גיאולוגי או אפילו טכנולוגי, טוען מאן; זה פוליטי.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> למרות הנושאים מרחיקי הלכת מאן טווה לאורך הספר, אולי זה לא מתאים לכולם. יש נטייה אקדמית חזקה לכתיבה, שנשענת מאוד על ז&#39;רגון. הספר כולל גם מצעד מסחרר של חוקרים, ומאן מרבה להדגיש את הקשר שלו לחוקרי אקלים ולאירועים, ובשלב מסוים נזכר איך הוא &quot;נודע כקצת גורו סטטיסטיקה&quot;. המונחים הטכניים, ראשי התיבות, ראשי התיבות והמשיקים להתייחסות עצמית יכולים להסיח את הדעת מהטיעונים והמסר הרחבים יותר של הספר.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> למרות שההתמסרות של מאן לשפה אקדמית מדויקת באה על חשבון בהירות מסוימת, חובבי האקלים יעריכו את הצלילות העמוקות לתוך התהליך המדעי. רבים מהקטעים הצפופים מתגמלים את הקורא במידע מספק של מידע מרתק או תובנה מאירה. מדי פעם צחקתי בקול מהמשחקים, הבדיחות והדוקרנים של מאן. (התייחסות ל-ROUSs של <em>הכלה הנסיכה</em> - מכרסמים בגודל יוצא דופן - נחתה טוב במיוחד.)</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> לאחר מסע בעבר, מאן מביא אותנו להווה ומביט לעבר העתיד. למרות שאקלים בעבר עשוי להציע שיעורים, שיעורים אלה מגיעים רק עד כה. לא סביר שנביא חממה נוספת לכדור הארץ, אבל האקלים מתחמם מהר יותר ממה שהתחמם באלפי שנים, הודות לפעולות אנושיות. אם מדיניות האקלים הנוכחית תתקיים, התחזיות המדעיות הטובות ביותר מראות שהדברים יהיו כואבים, אבל הציוויליזציה לא תיגמר. אבל מדעני אקלים אינם אורקלים. הם לא יכולים להיות בטוחים.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> חוסר הוודאות הזה, במקום להיות סיבה לשאננות, צריך לדרבן אותנו לפעולה, טוען מאן. &quot;ההשפעות של שינויי האקלים, ללא ספק, מהוות איום קיומי אם לא נפעל&quot;, מסכם מאן. &quot;אבל אנחנו <em>יכולים</em> לפעול. הרגע השברירי שלנו עדיין יכול להישמר&quot;.</p><hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" /><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <em>קנה</em> <a href="//bookshop.org/a/21798/9781541702899">את הרגע השביר שלנו</a> <em>מ-Bookshop.org.</em> Science News <em>היא שותפה ל-Bookshop.org והיא תרוויח עמלה על רכישות שנעשו מקישורים במאמר זה.</em></p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_reviews_feat-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="287067" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_reviews_feat-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title> המדוזות חסרות המוח האלה משתמשות בעיניים ובצרורות העצבים שלהן כדי ללמוד</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/brainless-jellyfish-eyes-nerves-learn<dc:creator><![CDATA[Maria Temming]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Fri, 22 Sep 2023 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Animals]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3131739 </guid><description><![CDATA[No brain? No problem for Caribbean box jellyfish. Their seemingly simple nervous systems can learn to avoid obstacles on sight, a study suggests.]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<p>עבור מדוזות קופסא הקאריביות, למידה היא ממש לא מובן מאליו.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> בניסוי חדש, בעלי חיים אלו <a href="https://www.cell.com/current-biology/fulltext/S0960-9822(23)01136-3" target="_blank" rel="noopener">למדו לזהות מכשולים ולהימנע מהם</a> למרות שאין להם מוח מרכזי, מדווחים חוקרים ב-22 בספטמבר ב- <em>Current Biology</em> . זוהי העדות הראשונה לכך שמדוזות יכולות ליצור קשרים נפשיים בין אירועים - כמו לראות משהו ולהיתקל בו - ולשנות את התנהגותן בהתאם.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> &quot;אולי למידה אינה זקוקה למערכת עצבים מורכבת מאוד, אלא, למידה היא חלק בלתי נפרד מתאי עצב, או מעגלים מוגבלים מאוד&quot;, אומר יאן ביילצקי, נוירואתולוג מאוניברסיטת קיל בגרמניה. אם כן, הממצא החדש יכול לעזור לאתר כיצד התפתחה למידה בבעלי חיים.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> מערכת העצבים של מדוזה תיבה קריבית ( <em>Tripedalia cystophora</em> ) כוללת ארבע rhopalia דמויי כפתורים המשתלשלים מהפעמון של גופה. כל rhopalium מכיל שש עיניים וכ-1,000 נוירונים. המדוזות משתמשות בחזון שלהן כדי לעזור לנווט בין שורשי המנגרוב בלגונות הטרופיות שבהן הן צדות טרף סרטנים זעירים.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> אריגה בין שורשים אינה הישג פשוט. מדוזות קופסאות קריביות שופטות את מרחק השורש על סמך עד כמה הוא נראה כהה ביחס למים שמסביב - כלומר, הניגודיות שלו. במים צלולים, רק שורשים מרוחקים נמוגים ברקע, או בעלי ניגודיות נמוכה. אבל במים עכורים, אפילו שורשים סמוכים יכולים להשתלב בסביבתם.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> מים יכולים להפוך עכורים במהירות עקב גאות ושפל, אצות וגורמים אחרים. בילצקי ועמיתיו תהו אם מדוזות קופסא הקאריביות יכולות ללמוד שאובייקטים בעלי ניגודיות נמוכה, שאולי יראו בהתחלה רחוקים, באמת נמצאים בקרבת מקום.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> הצוות הכניס 12 מדוזות למיכל עגול מוקף בפסים אפורים ולבנים בעלי ניגודיות נמוכה. מצלמה צילמה את התנהגות החיות במשך כשבע דקות. בתחילה נראה היה שהמדוזה פירשה את הפסים האפורים כשורשים מרוחקים ושחה לתוך קיר המיכל.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> אבל נראה היה שההתנגשויות הללו הובילו את המדוזה להתייחס לפסים האפורים יותר כמו שורשים קרובים במים עכורים, והחיות החלו להימנע מהם. המרחק הממוצע של הג&#39;לי מקיר המיכל גדל מכ-2.5 ס&quot;מ בדקות הראשונות לכ-3.6 ס&quot;מ בדקות האחרונות. ממוצע החבטות שלהם בקיר ירד מ-1.8 לדקה ל-0.78 לדקה.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> &quot;מצאתי שזה באמת מדהים&quot;, אומר Nagayasu Nakanishi, ביולוג אבולוציוני מאוניברסיטת ארקנסו בפייטוויל, שחקר את מערכות העצבים של מדוזה אך לא היה מעורב בעבודה החדשה. &quot;מעולם לא חשבתי שמדוזה יכולה באמת ללמוד.&quot; </p><div class="wp-block-image  has-alignleft" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><figure class="alignleft size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="314" height="450" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092123_MT_jellyfish-learning_jellyfish-still_inline-314x450.jpg" alt="תצלום של מדוזה קופסה מהקריביים עם ארבע רופליה מוקפות בלבן." class="wp-image-3131741" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092123_MT_jellyfish-learning_jellyfish-still_inline-314x450.jpg 314w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092123_MT_jellyfish-learning_jellyfish-still_inline-267x383.jpg 267w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092123_MT_jellyfish-learning_jellyfish-still_inline-130x186.jpg 130w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092123_MT_jellyfish-learning_jellyfish-still_inline-405x580.jpg 405w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092123_MT_jellyfish-learning_jellyfish-still_inline-541x776.jpg 541w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092123_MT_jellyfish-learning_jellyfish-still_inline.jpg 680w" sizes="(max-width: 314px) 100vw, 314px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3131741">לארבע הרופאליות (מעוגלות) של מדוזה הקופסה הקאריבית יש שש עיניים וכ-1,000 נוירונים כדי לעבד את מה שהם רואים.</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3131741">איזבלה בייר, בוב ובר ויאן ביילצקי</span></figcaption></figure></div><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> הנוירוביולוג Björn Brembs רואה את התוצאות ביתר זהירות, ומציין את המספר הקטן של מדוזות שנבדקו ואת השונות בביצועיהן. &quot;אני רוצה שזה יהיה נכון, כי זה יהיה כל כך מגניב&quot;, אומר ברמבס, מאוניברסיטת רגנסבורג בגרמניה. ניסויים עם יותר מדוזה יכולים לשכנע אותו שהחיות באמת לומדים.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> בניסויים אחרים, בילצקי ועמיתיו חתכו rhopalia ממדוזות והניחו את צרורות העצבים נושאי העין מול מסך. בערך כמו הסצנה ההיא ב- <em>A Clockwork Orange</em> , אומר ביילצקי, חוץ מזה שלעיני מדוזה אין עפעפיים פתוחים. המסך הציג פסים אפורים בהירים בעלי ניגודיות נמוכה, בעוד שאלקטרודה העניקה לרופליה דופק חשמלי חלש, שחקה את התחושה של התנגשות במשהו.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> אימון זה גרם ל-rhopalia להתחיל להגיב לברים בעלי ניגודיות נמוכה מהם התעלמו בתחילה. הם התחילו לשלוח את סוגי האותות העצביים שהם כידוע פולטים כאשר מדוזה מתרחקת ממכשול. זה מצביע על כך ש-rhopalia לבדה יכולה ללמוד שמכשולים רחוקים לכאורה, בעלי ניגודיות נמוכה, הם למעשה קרובים מספיק כדי להימנע מהם - מה שבתורו מרמז שה-rhopalia הם מרכזי הלמידה של מדוזה הקופסה הקאריבית.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> &quot;זה החלק הכי מגניב במאמר&quot;, אומר קן צ&#39;נג, ביולוג התנהגותי באוניברסיטת מקווארי בסידני. &quot;זה מביא אותנו צעד אחד למטה לתוך, אתה יודע, החיווט של איך זה עובד.&quot;</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> עבור הנוירוביולוגית Gaëlle Botton-Amiot, התחקות אחר הלמידה ל-rhopalia מעלה שאלות חדשות. &quot;יש להם ארבעה דברים כאלה בגוף, אז איך זה עובד?&quot; היא שואלת. &quot;איך זה מתואם?&quot; ואם מדוזה מאבדת את אחת ה-rhopalia שלה, האם היא שוכחת את כל מה שהעיניים האלה ראו ונוירונים למדו? או שהרופליה האחרת זוכרת את זה?</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> המחקר של בוטון-אמיות באוניברסיטת פריבורג בשוויץ <a href="https://www.pnas.org/doi/10.1073/pnas.2220685120" target="_blank" rel="noopener">מרמז על יכולות למידה דומות אצל כלניות ים</a> . בדומה למדוזות, הן משתייכות לקבוצת בעלי חיים הנקראים קנידיארים. &quot;המראה שקנידיארים כל כך שונים [יכולים ללמוד שניהם] אומר שזה כנראה נפוץ בתוכם&quot;, היא אומרת, ושאולי גם האב הקדמון המשותף שלהם יכול ללמוד.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> &quot;אולי [למידה] למעשה התפתחה מספר פעמים באבולוציה של מערכות העצבים&quot;, אומר נאקנישי. חשיפת המנגנון הסלולרי והכימי שמאחורי למידה אצל מדוזות או חיות אחרות עשויה לשפוך אור על כך. &quot;אם יש הרבה קווי דמיון במנגנון של איך הם לומדים, אז זה יעיד על מוצא משותף&quot;, הוא אומר. &quot;אבל אם הם התפתחו באופן עצמאי, אז אולי היית מצפה למנגנונים שונים מאוד של למידה.&quot;</p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092123_MT_jellyfish-learning_box-jellyfish_feat-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="105226" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092123_MT_jellyfish-learning_box-jellyfish_feat-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title> OSIRIS-REx של נאס&quot;א החזיר חלקים מהאסטרואיד Bennu לכדור הארץ</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/nasa-osiris-rex-return-asteroid-bennu-earth<dc:creator><![CDATA[James R. Riordon]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Fri, 22 Sep 2023 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Space]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3131719 </guid><description><![CDATA[Asteroid dirt from Bennu could help reveal clues about the material that came together to make the solar system — and possibly where life comes from.]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<p>שבע שנים הן הרבה זמן לחכות לשירות הספק שלך כדי לספק חבילה. זה כמה זמן עבר מאז<a href="https://solarsystem.nasa.gov/missions/osiris-rex/in-depth/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">החללית OSIRIS-REx של נאס&quot;א</a> יצאה לדרך לאסוף סלעים ואבק מהאסטרואיד בנו. אבל החבילה נמסרה כעת בבטחה.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> ב-24 בספטמבר, החללית טסה ליד כדור הארץ והפילה קפסולה המכילה חומר <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/nasa-osiris-rex-spacecraft-asteroid-bennu-sample-collection">שנאסף מבנו</a> באוקטובר 2020 ( <em>SN: 21/10/20</em> ).</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> זוהי המשימה השלישית לשלוף חלקים מאסטרואיד, והראשונה עבור נאס&quot;א וארה&quot;ב. כמות חומרי האסטרואידים על הסיפון הפעם עולה בהרבה על המיקרוגרם שחללית <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/blog/deleted-scenes/hayabusa-asteroid-sample-return-mission-lands-australia">Hayabusa של יפן החזירה ב-2005</a> , מהאסטרואיד איטוקאווה, וחמשת הגרם ש- <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/japan-hayabusa2-asteroid-dirt-sample-clues-early-solar-system">Hayabusa2 אסף ב-2018</a> מ-Ryugu ( <em>SN: 14/6/10; SN: 12/7 /20</em> ).</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> מדגם בנו הגיע בתזמון ובדיוק שיגרמו למרבית שירותי המשלוחים היבשתיים לקנא. לאחר מסע של שלוש שנים חזרה מהאסטרואיד וירידה מלכתחילה, הקפסולה שיחררה מצנח וירדה ליעדה בבסיס חיל האוויר היל ליד אוגדן, יוטה, ונגעה כמה דקות מוקדם מהמתוכנן בשעה 10:52 בבוקר EDT .</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> &quot;זו עסקת ענק&quot;, אמר המדען הראשי של מרכז טיסות החלל של נאס&quot;א גודארד, ג&#39;יימס גרווין, שהיה בבסיס חיל האוויר כדי לחזות בנחיתה של הקפסולה. &quot;זה החומר הכי נדיר שהיה לנו אי פעם על כדור הארץ.&quot;</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> הקפסולה תעבור למרכז טיסות החלל ג&#39;ונסון ביוסטון ב-25 בספטמבר לפני פתיחת מיכל המדגם.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> אם פיסות האסטרואידים שרדו את הירידה, הם יכולים לעזור לחשוף איזה סוג של חומרים חברו יחד לבניית מערכת השמש שלנו. התבוננות טובה בחומר שממנו בנוי עשויה לספק תובנות לגבי הסיכונים שהאסטרואידים הסמוכים מהווים לנו, במקרה שהם במסלול התנגשות עם כדור הארץ. מטען האסטרואיד עשוי אפילו להכיל רמזים שיעזרו לענות על אחת השאלות הגדולות ביותר במדע - איך התחילו החיים?</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> &quot;אני באמת מרוכז ב... לנסות להבין אם סוגים אלה של אסטרואידים עשירים בפחמן אולי סיפקו את זרעי החיים&quot;, אומר מדען הפלנטה דנטה לורטה מאוניברסיטת אריזונה בטוסון, שמוביל את משימת OSIRIS-REx. &quot;אז אנחנו מחפשים דברים כמו חומצות אמינו שנמצאות בחלבונים שלנו וחומצות גרעין&quot;, אבני הבניין של ההוראות הגנטיות שמאפשרות חיים על כדור הארץ.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> לורטה אומרת שבעצם אין סיכוי למצוא משהו חי על אסטרואידים כמו בנו. אבל בסלעים ובאבק שנאספו, &quot;יכולנו באמת לראות כיצד כימיה מולקולרית אורגנית יכולה להתפתח לפני שהחיים מופיעים.&quot; </p><figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="680" height="414" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092123_jr_bennu-return_inline.jpg" alt="איור של חללית OSIRIS-REx של נאס&quot;א נוגעת קלות באסטרואיד בנו." class="wp-image-3131722" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092123_jr_bennu-return_inline.jpg 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092123_jr_bennu-return_inline-629x383.jpg 629w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092123_jr_bennu-return_inline-306x186.jpg 306w" sizes="(max-width: 680px) 100vw, 680px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3131722">החללית OSIRIS-REx של נאס&quot;א (מתוארת נוגעת קלות באסטרואיד בנו) הורידה את דגימת האסטרואיד ביוטה לאחר מסע של שלוש שנים חזרה הביתה.</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3131722">נאס&quot;א</span></figcaption></figure><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> ב-250 גרם מוערך, דגימת האסטרואידים בקפסולת ההחזרה של OSIRIS-REx היא רק קצת יותר כבדה מכוס קפה. אבל זה מטמון עצום של חומר אסטרואיד, מבחינת מדעני המשימה. גודל המדגם עולה בהרבה על הכמות שציפתה לה בתחילה, אומרת לורטה.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> &quot;המצאנו 15 גרם&quot; כגודל מדגם סביר לניתוח, הוא אומר, &quot;שזו כמות עצומה של חומר בכימיה אנליטית בימינו&quot;. אבל נאס&quot;א מאפשרת ללורטה ולצוות שלו לשמור רק רבע מהמדגם לשימוש עצמי. חלק מהחלק הנותר יופץ למדענים ברחבי העולם, והשאר יישמר למחקרים עתידיים.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> זה אומר שאיסוף 60 גרם מבנו היה מספיק כדי להבטיח שלורטה ועמיתיו יש את הדגימה המקווה שלהם. &quot;העובדה שהתגברנו ארבע פעמים זה פשוט מוצלח בצורה פנומנלית&quot;, אומרת לורטה.</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> מתכון לאסטרואיד</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> החוקרים כבר מדמיינים את כל מה שהם יכולים ללמוד מבנו.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> הפיזיקאי Mikael Granvik מאוניברסיטת הלסינקי מקווה שניתוחים של החומר Bennu יסייעו לחשוף את הפוטנציאל לכריית אסטרואידים עבור מים וחומרי גלם שיכולים לספק משימות חלל עתידיות.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> פיסות האסטרואיד יכולות גם לסייע בחקירותיו לגבי עד כמה שברירי כמה סלעי חלל עשויים להיות. &quot;מה קורה לאסטרואידים מאותו סוג של בנו כשהם מתקרבים לשמש?&quot; אומר גרנוויק, שאינו חבר בצוות OSIRIS-REx. הוא ועמיתיו מציעים שהאינטראקציה עם השמש גורמת ל&quot;אסטרואידים של ערימת הריסות&quot; כאלה, העשויים מחומר קשור רופף, להתפרק. ההשערה יכולה להסביר מדוע יש פחות אסטרואידים של ערימות הריסות במסלולים ליד השמש מהצפוי.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> כדי לבדוק את הרעיון, גרנוויק חושף דגימות לתנאים קשים שמעריכים איך זה יהיה ליד השמש, ובעצם הורס את החומר. מסיבה זו, הוא לא מצפה להשתמש באף אחד מסלע בנו היקר. במקום זאת, Granvik מקווה ללמוד את מתכון האסטרואידים של Bennu ואז להזמין אנלוגים לאסטרואידים מספקים שימזגו יחד חומרים המחקים את תערובת Bennu. זו דוגמה לאופן שבו המדגם שהוחזר יכול להרחיב את הזדמנויות המחקר אפילו עבור מדענים שלא מקבלים חלק מהדבר האמיתי. </p><figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><iframe loading="lazy" title="כיצד OSIRIS-REx של נאס&quot;א יחזיר חלקים של אסטרואיד לכדור הארץ | חדשות המדע" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/SEJ-Ed1_UQ4?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe></div><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> לאחר מסע של שלוש שנים על סיפון החללית OSIRIS-REx, קפסולה המכילה אבק וסלעים מהאסטרואיד Bennu תבצע צלילה לוהטת לאטמוספירה של כדור הארץ ב-24 בספטמבר, כפי שניתן לראות בסימולציה זו. ברגע שהוא משחרר את הקפסולה, OSIRIS-REx יירה את המטוסים שלו כדי להסיט את עצמו הלאה לאסטרואיד אפופיס תחת השם החדש OSIRIS-APEX. בינתיים, הקפסולה תעוף לכיוון כדור הארץ כמו כדור אש. למרות שנדחף במהלך הירידה הגסה, הדגימה תהיה מוגנת מהטמפרטורות העזה של כניסה חוזרת על ידי מגן החום של הקפסולה. כשהקפסולה מתקרבת לקרקע, היא תקפיץ מצנח ותיסחף בעדינות את שארית הדרך למטה ביוטה, שם, אם הכל ילך כשורה, מדענים יכולים לאסוף את המשלוח המיוחל שלהם.</figcaption></figure><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> סיפורים שבנו יכול לספר</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> עבור המדענית הפלנטרית ג&#39;סיקה סנשיין מאוניברסיטת מרילנד בקולג&#39; פארק, חלק ניכר מהערך במשימות החזרה לדוגמה הוא בסיפורים שאסטרואידים יכולים לספר לנו על היווצרות כדור הארץ ומערכת השמש. &quot;אנחנו חושבים עליהם כעל סוג של סלעים מתים, והם לא. כלומר, הם עברו אבולוציה משמעותית, כימית ופיזית כאחד, ב-4.5 מיליארד השנים מאז היווצרותם&quot;, אומר סאנשיין.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> כמו לורטה, Sunshine מקווה ללמוד כיצד תהליכים אלה הובילו בסופו של דבר למקורות החיים, אך חקר אסטרואידים קרובים לכדור הארץ הוא חיוני להבנת האיומים שגם אסטרואידים מהווים. &quot;באופן עקרוני, הם יכלו לתת לנו חיים והם יכלו לקחת אותם&quot;, אומרת סאנשיין, &quot;כלומר, מנקודת המבט של הדינוזאור, הם כן לקחו אותם.&quot;</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Sunshine חבר בצוות ששלח את חללית ה-DART<a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/dart-mission-deflected-asteroid-for-planetary-defense">לדחוף את האסטרואיד דימורפוס</a> למסלול חדש כדי לראות אם אפשר לדחוף אסטרואידים ממסלולים המאיימים על כדור הארץ ( <em>SN: 10/11/22</em> ). &quot;אם אתה מודאג לגבי בעיית סכנת האסטרואידים, אנחנו די טוב יותר להבין מהי השונות הפיזית וההרכבה של כל הדברים האלה שעלולים לפגוע בנו&quot;, אומר Sunshine. &quot;כי תלוי ממה הם עשויים ואיך הם עשויים, זה ישנה את ההשפעה שלהם כשהם פוגעים בנו. אם אי פעם יפגעו בנו.&quot;</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> ייתכן שבקפסולת ההחזרה יהיו יותר מחלקים בלבד של בנו, אומר האסטרונום הומברטו קמפינס מאוניברסיטת מרכז פלורידה באורלנדו, שהוא חבר בצוות OSIRIS-REx. כמה סלעים מחזירי אור בבנו אינם תואמים את שאר האסטרואיד, שהוא חשוך מאוד. הסיבה הסבירה ביותר, אומר קמפינס, היא שהנתחים הבהירים מגיעים מהתנגשויות עם אסטרואידים אחרים.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> &quot;אין שום ערובה, אבל אני מקווה שבדגימה שלנו יהיו חלקים, חלקים, גרגרים שמקורם באסטרואידים האחרים האלה&quot;, אומר קמפינס. ניתוחים מרוחקים מצביעים על כך שחלק מהחלקים הבהירים בבנו מתאימים לאסטרואיד וסטה. &quot;אז תהיה לנו החזרה מדגם לא רק מבנו, אלא אולי מווסטה&quot;, אומר קמפינס, &quot;או מי יודע איזה עוד אסטרואיד.&quot;</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> למרות שזו תהיה החזרת הדגימה הראשונה של נאס&quot;א של אסטרואיד, <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/dust-nabbed-spacecraft-may-be-outside-solar-system">משימת אבק כוכבים</a> בשנת 2006 החזירה בהצלחה דגימות של השביט Wild-2, גם ליוטה ( <em>SN: 14/8/14</em> ).</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> התחנה הבאה: אסטרואיד אפופיס</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> המשימה של OSIRIS-REx לא מסתיימת במשלוח החבילות ביוטה. &quot;החללית עדיין בריאה&quot;, אומרת לורטה. לאחר ירי תמרון סטיה, &quot;זה במסלול לאסטרואיד אחר - אסטרואיד אפופיס&quot;, שנמצא בערך במרחק של בנו מכדור הארץ.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> עבור המשימה המורחבת, הלוויין מקבל שם חדש, OSIRIS-APEX, והוא אמור להקיף את אפופיס ברגע שהוא יגיע באפריל 2029, אם הכל ילך כמתוכנן. אבל זה לא יחזיר עוד דגימות לכדור הארץ. בניגוד למשאיות המשלוחים המקומיות שלך, OSIRIS-REx תוכנן לשאת רק חבילה אחת ולבצע משלוח בודד. לאחר יום ראשון מסתיימים ימי האספקה ​​של החללית.</p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092123_jr_bennu-return_feat-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="227398" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092123_jr_bennu-return_feat-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title> הקלטת פה היא אולי פריצת שינה טרנדית, אבל המדע מאחורי זה דק</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/mouth-taping-trend-sleep-science-slim<dc:creator><![CDATA[Meghan Rosen]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Fri, 22 Sep 2023 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Health & Medicine]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3131593 </guid><description><![CDATA[Mouth taping is big on social media, but few studies have evaluated it. Some evidence suggests that sealing the lips shut may help people with sleep apnea.]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<p>אולי TikTok הראה לכם אנשים שמים סרט קטן על השפתיים שלהם. או אולי אינסטגרם הגישה לכם מודעות לרצועות פה דביקות. ברשתות החברתיות ומחוצה לה, טרנד שנקרא הדבקת פה הוא לסתום את הפה של אנשים בלילה - לעזור להם לנשום דרך האף.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> זאק פורד, בן 38, ניסה לראשונה את הטרנד בחודש שעבר, לאחר שהחלים מניתוח למחיצה סטיה. הניתוח שיפר את נשימת האף שלו, אבל בלילה הוא עדיין שאב אוויר דרך שפתיו. בבקרים, אומר פורד, הוא היה מתעורר עם פה יבש וגרון שרוט.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> פורד העלה את הקלטת הפה במהלך פגישה עם הרופא שלו, שלא חשב שיש נזק בניסיון. באותו ערב, פורד הניח ריבוע קטן של סרט ניתוח על אמצע שפתיו והתיישב במיטה. זו הייתה שנת הלילה הטובה ביותר שהיה לו בזיכרון האחרון, הוא אומר. &quot;כשהתעוררתי, הייתי כמו, &#39;הולי, זה עובד!&#39;&quot;</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> היתרונות של הדבקת הפה הוכרזו עבור כל דבר, החל מרופא שיניים ועד לשינה. אנשים עשויים לסתום את הפה שלהם כדי למנוע חריקת שיניים, ריח רע מהפה, נחירות ודום נשימה בשינה - או אפילו כדי להגביר את הכושר או לקבל לסת חזקה יותר.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> אבל יש <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41415-023-6039-7" target="_blank" rel="noopener">עדיין מעט נתונים שתומכים בטענות כאלה</a> , כתב רופא השיניים ג&#39;ונתן קוויגלי במכתב ב-23 ביוני ב- <em>British Dental Journal.</em> לפני שייעץ למטופלים, קוויגלי, שעובדת במרפאת שיניים באנגליה, רוצה לראות מחקרים נוספים ולהבין טוב יותר את הסיכונים והיתרונות הפוטנציאליים.</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> האם הדבקת הפה יכולה לשפר את השינה של אנשים?</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> כמה ראיות מצביעות על כך שהדבקת הפה עשויה להועיל לסייע בטיפול במחלה אחת לפחות: דום נשימה בשינה. אפילו כאן, המדע דל, והשיטות מגוונות. מרצועה דקה על השפתיים ועד כתם שחור על פני הפה, סוגי הקלטת והטכניקות יכולים להיות שונים בין אנשים, מותגים ומחקרים, מה שמקשה על הסקת מסקנות רחבות.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> למרות שזכה לפופולריות לאחרונה באמצעות המדיה החברתית והספר <em>Breath</em> משנת 2020, הרעיון להשתמש במכשיר כדי לסתום את הפה בזמן השינה הוא לא כל כך חדש. במשך שנים, רופאים השתמשו ברצועות סנטר כדי לעזור לחלק מחולי דום נשימה בשינה לשמור על פיותיהם סגורים במהלך לחץ מתמשך בדרכי הנשימה, או טיפול CPAP, אומרת קרישנה סונדאר, רופאת ריאות ורופאת רפואת שינה המנהלת את מרכז השינה והתעוררות באוניברסיטת יוטה. בסולט לייק סיטי.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> אנשים הסובלים מהמצב עלולים להיתקל בבעיות נשימה בזמן שינה: השרירים נרגעים, הלשון נשמטת לאחור ורקמות רכות בגרון קורסות, וחוסמות את דרכי הנשימה. CPAP הוא הטיפול בסטנדרט הזהב. המכונה מספקת לחץ אוויר באמצעות מסכה המולבשת על הפנים. זה כמו לשאוב צמיג, אומר סונדאר. הפעל אותו, ודרכי הנשימה התקלות מתנפחות. עם זאת, אם מסכות מכסות רק את האף, אוויר יכול לדלוף מהפה. רצועות סנטר יכולות לשמור על הפה סגור ולמנוע דליפת אוויר. אבל הם לא עובדים כל כך טוב ויש אנשים שמוצאים אותם לא בנוח, אומר סונדאר. </p><figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="677" height="450" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/091523_MR_mouth-taping_chin-strap_inline-677x450.jpg" alt="תמונה של גבר לבן שוכב במיטה עם מכונת CPAP קשורה לראשו ומכסה את אפו." class="wp-image-3131598" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/091523_MR_mouth-taping_chin-strap_inline-677x450.jpg 677w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/091523_MR_mouth-taping_chin-strap_inline-576x383.jpg 576w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/091523_MR_mouth-taping_chin-strap_inline-280x186.jpg 280w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/091523_MR_mouth-taping_chin-strap_inline.jpg 680w" sizes="(max-width: 677px) 100vw, 677px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3131598">טיפול אחד לדום נשימה בשינה הוא מכונת CPAP, אשר שואבת אוויר לאף באמצעות מסיכת פנים. רופאים לפעמים משלבים אותו עם רצועת סנטר כדי למנוע מהאוויר לצאת מהפה.</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3131598">Alina555/E+/Getty Images Plus</span></figcaption></figure><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> במחקרי שינה במעבדה שלו, אם אדם שטופל ב-CPAP מוציא אוויר דרך הפה, הצוות של סונדאר ידביק פס זעיר של סרט על השפתיים כדי לשמור אותן סגורות. &quot;נראה שהקלטת העשרה הזו עושה את העבודה טוב יותר מרצועת סנטר גדולה&quot;, הוא אומר. זה הופך את ה-CPAP ליעיל יותר, מה שיכול לעזור לאנשים לישון טוב יותר בלילה. סונדאר מכנה את סרט הפה אחד הכלים בערכות הכלים של הרופאים, אם כי הוא היה רוצה לראות יותר נתונים על מידת היעילות שלו.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> אחת ההשפעות שמומחה לרפואת שינה אנדרו וולמן שם לב היא שעם השפתיים של אנשים צמודות זו לזו, אוויר שנשאב לתוך האף שלהם זורם לפעמים אל הפה ונופח את הלחיים. &quot;הם נראים כאילו הם נושפים לתוך סקסופון&quot;, אומר וולמן, מבית הספר לרפואה בהרווארד ובית החולים בריגהם אנד נשים בבוסטון. מדענים אחרים הבחינו גם<a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC9992075/#CR16" target="_blank" rel="noopener">בתופעת &quot;נפיחת הפה&quot;</a> הזו, אם כי הצוות של וולמן עדיין לא יודע כיצד היא משפיעה על דום נשימה בשינה. זה לא מסוכן, הוא אומר, אבל זה עלול להעיר אותך.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> הוא ועמיתיו שילבו את הקלטת הפה לא רק עם CPAP, אלא גם עם מכשיר לקידום הלסת התחתונה לטיפול בהפרעה. המכשיר מחליק לתוך הפה כמו מגן פה ודוחף את הלסת התחתונה קדימה, מושך את הלשון מהחלק האחורי של הגרון. אבל המכשיר יכול לגרום לאנשים לנשום דרך הפה, מה שעלול להפוך את הטיפול לפחות יעיל, אומר וולמן.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <a href="https://www.atsjournals.org/doi/10.1513/AnnalsATS.202109-1050OC?url_ver=Z39.88-2003&amp;rfr_id=ori:rid:crossref.org&amp;rfr_dat=cr_pub%20%200pubmed" target="_blank" rel="noopener">במחקר שנערך על 21 אנשים עם דום נשימה בשינה,</a> הצוות של וולמן כיסה את שפתי המשתתפים ברצועות דביקות שקופות מתוצרת SomniFix, חברת ייצור במרילנד שתמכה בעבודה. שילוב הרצועות עם המכשיר דמוי מגן הפה הציע שיפור לעומת המכשיר בלבד, והפחית את מספר הפעמים שאנשים הפסיקו לנשום בשעה, דיווח הצוות של וולמן בשנת 2022. זה היה &quot;שיפור קטן&quot;, הוא מציין. &quot;אנחנו צריכים מחקר גדול יותר.&quot;</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> יש צורך בניסויים גדולים יותר כדי לבדוק את יעילות הדבקת הפה</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> זה נראה כמכנה משותף של מחקר הקלטת הפה עד כה. הכל מחקרים ראשוניים קטנים, אומר וולמן. &quot;אין לנו את הניסויים הקליניים הגדולים... זה מה שחסר.&quot;</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> מחקר משנת 2015 מצא שרק <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/25450408/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">טלאי נקבובי על הפה לבדו עזר לטפל בדום נשימה קל בשינה ובנחירות</a> . <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC9498537/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">ומחקר בשנה שעברה על קלטת מסוג אחר</a> דיווח על משהו דומה. אבל המחקרים האלה היו זעירים, עם 30 משתתפים בלבד או פחות. היעדר נתונים מניסויים גדולים יותר פירושו שדעתם של מומחים על הקלטת הפה עשויה להיות על כל המפה, אומר וולמן. &quot;כשאתה שואל רופא על זה, אתה הולך לקבל כל תשובות שונות,&quot; הוא אומר.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> מומחה האוזניים, האף והגרון אריך וויגט, למשל, אינו משוכנע שהקלטת הפה מועילה - או אפילו בטוחה. הטרנד &quot;בהחלט מעלה כמה דגלים אדומים&quot;, אומר Voigt, מ-NYU Langone Health. הוא חושש שאנשים עלולים לעכב את הנשימה שלהם או לשאוף בטעות את הסרט ולהיחנק, אם כי עדיין לא מחקרים גדולים עקבו אחר זה.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> הדבקת פה עשויה להיות כדאית בתרחיש הנכון, אומר Voigt, אבל הוא ממליץ על גישה זהירה לכל מי שמנסה אופנה בריאותית חדשה מ-TikTok. &quot;זה כנראה רעיון טוב [לאנשים] לדבר על זה עם הרופא שלהם לפני שהם עושים את זה בעצמם.&quot;</p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/091523_MR_mouth-taping_man-sleeping_feature-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="99306" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/091523_MR_mouth-taping_man-sleeping_feature-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title> כיצד שתלי מוח מטפלים בדיכאון</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/brain-implant-depression-electrode-stimulation-surgery<dc:creator><![CDATA[Laura Sanders]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Thu, 21 Sep 2023 13:37:04 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Health & Medicine]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3131233 </guid><description><![CDATA[This six-part series follows people whose lives have been changed by an experimental treatment called deep brain stimulation.]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<div class="wp-block-sciencenews-content-sidebar"><div class="wp-block-image is-style-rounded has-alignleft" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><figure class="mobile-wrap alignleft size-thumbnail is-resized"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-186x186.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-3131518" width="93" height="93" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-186x186.jpg 186w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-383x383.jpg 383w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-450x450.jpg 450w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-768x768.jpg 768w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-580x580.jpg 580w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-776x776.jpg 776w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-214x214.jpg 214w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square.jpg 1080w" sizes="(max-width: 93px) 100vw, 93px" /></figure></div><h3 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> חשמל הציל את המוח שלי</h3><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <em>זהו החלק הראשון בסדרה על גירוי מוחי עמוק לדיכאון.</em></p></div><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <em>[אזהרת תוכן: הסיפור הזה מכיל דיון על התאבדות.]</em></p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> ביום ראשון חם ושטוף אחר הצהריים במנהטן, הזמן קפא לג&#39;ון נלסון. הוא עמד על המדרכה ונפרד משלושת ילדיו, שסבא שלהם הגיע לעיר מלונג איילנד כדי לאסוף אותם.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> כמו כל הורה, ג&#39;ון מכוון עמוקות למוזרויות של ילדיו. המבוגר שלו? לפעמים שקט אבל מצחיק עד ביס. הילד האמצעי שלו? מדרג את אבא ב-10 מתוך 10 בסולם המבוכה ואינו זקוק לחיבוק. בנו בן ה-10, תינוק המשפחה, הוא הרגשי. &quot;הבן הצעיר שלי היה מטפס בחזרה אל הרחם של אשתי אם היה יכול&quot;, אומר ג&#39;ון. &quot;הוא הילד הזה.&quot;</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> מצעד בלתי צפוי גרר את התנועה, אז ג&#39;ון חנה באופן לא חוקי לאורך שפת מדרכה צהובה ברחוב 36, ליד המקום שבו חיכה חמו. הגיע הזמן ללכת. הצעיר שלו נתן את החיבוק האחרון. &quot;הוא הרים את מבטו, מפוחד ועצוב,&quot; אומר ג&#39;ון, ושאל, &quot;אבא, אני הולך לראות אותך שוב?&quot;</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> השאלה הזאת עצרה את השעון. &quot;הייתי כמו, &#39;אוי גבר&#39;,&quot; אומר ג&#39;ון. &quot;זה היה אחד מהרגעים האלה שבהם חייתי את זה דרך העיניים שלו. ואני נבהלתי בפעם הראשונה&quot;.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Until that good-bye, Jon hadn&#39;t wanted to live. For years, he had a constant yearning to die — he talks about it like it was an addiction — as he fought deep, debilitating depression. But his son&#39;s question pierced through that heaviness and reached something inside him. “That was the first time I really thought about it. I was like, &#39;I kind of hope I don&#39;t die.&#39; I hadn&#39;t had that feeling in so long.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> That hug happened around 5 pm on August 21, 2022. Twelve hours later, Jon was wheeled into a surgical suite.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> There, at Mount Sinai&#39;s hospital just southwest of Central Park, surgery team members screwed Jon&#39;s head into a frame to hold it still. Then they numbed him and drilled two small holes through the top of his skull, one on each side. Through each hole, a surgeon plunged a long, thin wire dotted at the end with electrodes deep into his brain. The wiring, threaded under his skin, snaked around the outside of Jon&#39;s skull and sank down behind his ear. From there, a wire wrapped around to the front, meeting a battery-powered control box that surgeons implanted in his chest, just below his collarbone.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> During the surgery and in the days after, doctors sent small pulses of electricity into Jon&#39;s brain. In ways that are still unclear, this electrical tinkering changes the messages that move between different brain regions. The doctors and researchers had what seems like a bold goal: They wanted these pulses to pull Jon out of the darkness of depression.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Jon is one of dozens of people in the United States currently in clinical trials that aim to heal mental disorders with brain implants. The technique is called deep brain stimulation, and it&#39;s built on the scientific premise that electrical stimulation can reset brains that are in the grip of powerful and devastating psychiatric disorders <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/chemical-imbalance-explain-depression">such as depression</a> , obsessive-compulsive disorder and post-traumatic stress disorder. </p><figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><iframe loading="lazy" title="Jon Nelson wants you to know how electricity saved his brain | Science News" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/SwZWsi1-4eM?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe></div><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> Watch a video of Jon describing his depression, his experience with DBS and how his mental health affects his family.</figcaption></figure><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Introducing deep brain stimulation</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> I first heard about deep brain stimulation, or DBS, more than a decade ago, in 2010. As a science reporter, I was sitting in a cavernous conference room packed with neuroscientists in San Diego. We were listening to a presentation by <a href="https://profiles.mountsinai.org/helen-s-mayberg" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Helen Mayberg, a neurologist and neuroscientist</a> who was then at Emory University in Atlanta. As she spoke, Mayberg walked the audience through the scientific rationale for the idea that electrodes pushed down into the brain could alleviate severe depression.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Toward the end of her presentation, Mayberg showed a video of a woman who had severe depression. The day before the video was taken, doctors had implanted electrodes into the woman&#39;s brain. The researchers in the video turned on the stimulation, and within a minute, just like that, the woman wanted to smile and laugh. That transformation floored me, and judging by the audience reaction, a lot of other people too.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> In November of 2022, I caught up with Mayberg, again at a neuroscience meeting, again in San Diego. We talked about what had happened in the years since that presentation and where this research is going. It hasn&#39;t been an easy road, says Mayberg, who now directs the Nash Family Center for Advanced Circuit Therapeutics at the Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai. The science of DBS has taken lots of twists and turns.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> So have the journeys of people who have participated in this research. To hear one of those stories, Mayberg put me in touch with Jon.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> For this series, I talked with him and his wife, as well as three other people who had lived with severe depression and are now being treated with deep brain stimulation. These people&#39;s paths have been incredibly tough. And while they still face challenges, they have been crystal clear about what DBS has done for them: This experimental brain surgery has given them back their lives. </p><figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="680" height="475" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_1_inline.jpg" alt="CT scan of electrodes in a person's brain" class="wp-image-3131241" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_1_inline.jpg 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_1_inline-548x383.jpg 548w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_1_inline-644x450.jpg 644w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_1_inline-266x186.jpg 266w" sizes="(max-width: 680px) 100vw, 680px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3131241">For deep brain stimulation, thin wires that contain electrodes were inserted deep into Jon Nelson&#39;s brain, where they are thought to change the activity of neural pathways.</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3131241">The Nash Family Center for Advanced Circuit Therapeutics, Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai</span></figcaption></figure><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The darkness of depression</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Jon&#39;s a sharp, funny middle-aged guy, a self-described “character,” who lives in a picturesque small town northeast of Philadelphia. He&#39;s a dad with three busy kids and a garage packed with hockey sticks, softball catcher pads, golf clubs, balls of all sorts, bikes, in-line skates, a mesh goal and a supercute white motor scooter. He&#39;s a coach (hockey and softball) known for dispensing “isms” and the phrase, “I&#39;m going to give you some life advice.” He&#39;s a husband who worries about his wife doing too much and not taking care of herself. He&#39;s in advertising, a people person who used to love having his friends over to hang around his fire pit.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> For a decade, Jon let his outgoing personality carry him as he struggled to overcome his depression. His disease, and the suicidal thoughts it forced on him, grew worse in the last five years. On the outside, Jon was the hypersocial, high-functioning guy everyone expected him to be. But inside, his profound depression was a private hell, he says. “I&#39;d be the one standing in front of everybody leading a champagne toast, and then I&#39;d be driving home and wanting to slam my car into a tree.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Jon fantasized about other deaths: A mugging, a plane crash. Until Jon&#39;s son asked if he would see Jon again, on the evening before the procedure, Jon even nurtured a little bit of hope that he might die during the brain surgery he volunteered for.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Jon&#39;s depression also stole his motivation, leaving him wrung out and isolated from his family. He overate, overslept and drank too much. His worst stretches, he suspects, left his family traumatized.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Talk therapy, antidepressants, antipsychotics, ketamine, cannabis, <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/snap-crackle-and-feel-good">transcranial magnetic stimulation</a> (in which magnetic fields target nerve cells through the skull), several residential treatment stints, even electroconvulsive therapy, which left him with intense memory loss — none of these treatments reliably worked for him.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> An estimated 280 million people worldwide have major depression. A subset of that giant number will ultimately fall into a hopeless-sounding diagnosis: “treatment-resistant depression” or “intractable depression.” In the United States, an estimated 2.8 million people have that diagnosis.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Jon is one of them. For him and his family, deep brain stimulation was a last-ditch, desperate maneuver. It was his Hail Mary.</p><hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" /><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <em>If you or someone you know is facing a suicidal crisis or emotional distress, call or text the 988 Suicide &amp; Crisis Lifeline at 988.</em></p><hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" /><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <em>The next article in the series <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/depression-treatment-resistant-help-dbs">follows Jon&#39;s search for relief</a> from the disease he describes as “poison in every single bit of my body.”</em></p><p class="has-gray-light-background-color has-background" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <em>This series was made possible with funding from the Alfred P. Sloan Foundation.</em></p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_1_feat-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="115115" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_1_feat-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title> Today&#39;s depression treatments don&#39;t help everyone</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/depression-treatment-resistant-help-dbs<dc:creator><![CDATA[Laura Sanders]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Thu, 21 Sep 2023 13:36:38 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Neuroscience]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3131317 </guid><description><![CDATA[In the second story in the series, deep brain stimulation is a last resort for some people with depression.]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<div class="wp-block-sciencenews-content-sidebar"><div class="wp-block-image is-style-rounded has-alignleft" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><figure class="mobile-wrap alignleft size-thumbnail is-resized"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-186x186.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-3131518" width="93" height="93" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-186x186.jpg 186w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-383x383.jpg 383w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-450x450.jpg 450w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-768x768.jpg 768w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-580x580.jpg 580w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-776x776.jpg 776w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-214x214.jpg 214w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square.jpg 1080w" sizes="(max-width: 93px) 100vw, 93px" /></figure></div><h3 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Electricity Saved My Brain</h3><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <em>This is the second part in a series on deep brain stimulation for depression. <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/brain-implant-depression-electrode-stimulation-surgery">Read from the beginning</a> .</em></p></div><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <em>[Content note: This story contains discussion of suicide.]</em></p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Jon Nelson&#39;s depression was poison. “I had poison in every single bit of my body. It literally ran throughout every cell in my body. My blood carried the poison, and it crushed everything in me.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Melancholia, one of depression&#39;s early names, comes from the ancient Greek word for “black bile,” a diseased liquid believed to flood a body. It was once thought that bloodletting and other ways to let the corrupting fluids out could ease people&#39;s minds.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Today, doctors have much better options to treat depression. Antidepressant drugs and talk therapy can be effective for many people. But these options don&#39;t help everyone.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Jon has treatment-resistant depression. So does Amanda, an app and web designer and artist in her 30s who lives in New York City. Amanda can also rattle off a long list of therapies she has tried for the deep depression she&#39;s felt since she was 13. She has been on 21 different antidepressant drugs. Her brain has been zapped with powerful magnets in a therapy called transcranial magnetic stimulation. She has had IV infusions of <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/ketamine-new-nerve-cell-connections-mice-depression">ketamine</a> . </p><div class="wp-block-image  has-alignleft" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><figure class="alignleft size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="450" height="450" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_2_inline-1-450x450.jpg" alt="An image of Cartoon Amanda under a pile of medicine bottles with numbers on them." class="wp-image-3131335" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_2_inline-1-450x450.jpg 450w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_2_inline-1-383x383.jpg 383w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_2_inline-1-186x186.jpg 186w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_2_inline-1-580x580.jpg 580w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_2_inline-1-214x214.jpg 214w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_2_inline-1.jpg 680w" sizes="(max-width: 450px) 100vw, 450px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3131335">Amanda tried a huge variety of treatments, including 21 kinds of medication, for her severe depression. Her art, including depictions of “Cartoon Amanda,” became an escape.</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3131335">Courtesy of Amanda</span></figcaption></figure></div><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Amanda, who to protect her privacy requested her last name not be used, has also had 40 rounds of electroconvulsive therapy, or ECT. The “gold standard” treatment for people who aren&#39;t helped by other therapies, ECT is often done several times a week for three or four weeks. For unknown reasons, the resulting mini-seizures in the brain can sometimes provide relief.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “The electroconvulsive therapy helped a little bit,” Amanda says. “But for it to help, I had to do it so frequently that I got memory damage. I was like, &#39;Whoa, whoa, whoa, I don&#39;t remember where my sock drawer is. I don&#39;t remember what subway stations are near my apartment. I don&#39;t remember how to use the software I&#39;ve been using for 10 years,&#39;” she told me. “I have to stop.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Jon&#39;s depression was poison; Amanda&#39;s was a vortex. And when ECT was no longer an option, that vortex nearly consumed her. After a suicide attempt, she spent six weeks in the hospital and then another six weeks receiving outpatient care. “It was at that point that [doctors] were like, &#39;There&#39;s nothing else we can do for you. You&#39;ve tried literally everything that&#39;s out there. If ECT doesn&#39;t work, that&#39;s it,&#39;” Amanda says.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> As with Jon and others I talked with, her doctors had given up, Amanda says. “When you get to that place where they say there&#39;s nothing else we can do for you, and yet you have to keep living your life, that&#39;s a hard place to get to.”</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The last hope</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Desperate for help, Amanda called the <a href="https://www.mountsinai.org/care/psychiatry/services/depression-anxiety-disorders/trd-program" target="_blank" rel="noopener">treatment-resistant depression program at Mount Sinai</a> . After describing all of her unsuccessful treatments, Amanda was once again passed along to different doctors. “They had decided that you really have tried everything,” she says.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> That last handoff is what delivered Amanda to the DBS research program. As Martijn Figee, a psychiatrist and DBS researcher at the Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai, explained the procedure, the research and the risks, Amanda listened carefully. She arrived at appointments prepared with an eight-page-long list of questions that covered the practical (“What should I avoid forever once I have it? Running? Hanging my head upside down? Trampolines?”) and the profound (“What makes a person want to be alive?”). Questions answered and fully informed, Amanda agreed to have DBS surgery.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The DBS program that Amanda and Jon are a part of looks vastly different from earlier iterations. In 2008, neurologist Helen Mayberg and many colleagues around the country had just begun a large, double-blind DBS clinical trial to test the technique. Called the Broaden trial, the six-month study followed people with depression, some of whom had electrical stimulation on and others who were implanted with electrodes but had the stimulation off.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> All told, 90 people with severe depression were implanted with brain stimulation devices in the trial. But in 2013, testing stopped early because of poorer-than-expected results. The sponsor and maker of the DBS device, St. Jude Medical Inc., determined that the trial wasn&#39;t likely to hit its goals. Along with another unsuccessful trial, which included 30 people who received stimulation in a different part of the brain, those lackluster results represented a real setback for DBS as a treatment for depression.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Those disappointing findings fueled criticisms of the method, underscored by stories of people who had negative experiences with DBS. And potential conflicts of interest exist, as they do for many medical treatments that depend on medical device companies. Mayberg, for instance, receives fees for consulting and licensing intellectual property from Abbott Laboratories, the company that bought St. Jude Medical.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Despite setbacks and criticism though, the research didn&#39;t stop; it matured. Brain-imaging methods got better, allowing researchers to see exactly which highways of white matter fibers, message-sending bundles that emanate from nerve cells, are influenced by the electrodes. Other aspects of care, including follow-up sessions with mental health experts and therapists, have evolved. In a small trial of 11 people with severe depression, for instance, <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/28397839/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">nine had their symptoms improve</a> , researchers reported in 2018. And DBS as a depression treatment has been able to borrow heavily from progress in treating other disorders. </p><figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><iframe loading="lazy" title="‘I tried 21 antidepressants before deep brain stimulation’ | Science News" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/qc1v35kgJPs?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe></div><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> Watch a video of Amanda describing how she uses art to process her experience with intense depression and DBS.</figcaption></figure><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> How widespread is DBS?</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Globally, DBS electrodes have been implanted in an estimated 230,000 people&#39;s brains. DBS was approved by the US Food and Drug Administration in 1997 to treat tremor, and in 2002 to treat Parkinson&#39;s disease. DBS is also used by doctors for severe cases of epilepsy, obsessive-compulsive disorder and dystonia, or involuntary muscle contractions.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> DBS&#39;s reach is expanding fast. In smaller experimental trials, people have been implanted with electrodes for pain, eating disorders, addiction, traumatic brain injuries and post-traumatic stress disorder. Researchers are working on stimulation systems to restore movement to paralyzed people and speech to people unable to talk.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Jon heard about the procedure in 2021. He called the Mount Sinai program from a residential treatment facility, only to learn that he didn&#39;t qualify because, at the time, he hadn&#39;t yet tried ECT. So he did 12 rounds of the therapy in early 2022. ECT helps many people. But it didn&#39;t help Jon, and the experience shook him. “It was horrific. Zero relief. My memory loss is still pervasive to this day,” he says. It was utter misery, but he qualified for the DBS trial.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> And with that, Jon&#39;s surgery date was set: August 22, 2022.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> In the run-up to the surgery, Jon&#39;s wife, Barbara, worried about both the surgery and the outcome. “What if they slip or they sneeze and they ruin his brain?” she recalls wondering. “What if it doesn&#39;t work? What do we do next? This was so much like the last resort that if it didn&#39;t work, then we were going to be looking at potentially years more of trying.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> She adds, “And there&#39;s no option of giving up.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Even so, Barbara didn&#39;t fully believe the surgery was going to happen until it was right around the corner. “I think my brain just did not catch up to the reality of it until we were very close to the actual surgery,” she told me. “A couple of days before, I was like, &#39;Oh I&#39;m a mess.&#39; I do weird things when I&#39;m really that stressed out, rearranging furniture, doing things that seem to take too much energy.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Jon, however, was not worried. “I didn&#39;t care that I was having my head cut open,” he says. “I had the same level of anxiety that you would have if you were getting your teeth cleaned.”</p><hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" /><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <em>If you or someone you know is facing a suicidal crisis or emotional distress, call or text the 988 Suicide &amp; Crisis Lifeline at 988.</em></p><hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" /><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <em>In the next article in the series,<a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/brain-implant-depression-electrode-stimulation-target">read about Jon&#39;s surgery and the big changes that followed for him and his family</a> .</em></p><p class="has-gray-light-background-color has-background" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <em>This series was made possible with funding from the Alfred P. Sloan Foundation.</em></p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_2_feat-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="214528" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_2_feat-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title> The science behind deep brain stimulation for depression</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/brain-implant-depression-electrode-stimulation-target<dc:creator><![CDATA[Laura Sanders]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Thu, 21 Sep 2023 13:35:35 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Health & Medicine]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3131347 </guid><description><![CDATA[The third part of the series explores the promising brain areas to target for deep brain stimulation for depression. ]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<div class="wp-block-sciencenews-content-sidebar"><div class="wp-block-image is-style-rounded has-alignleft" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><figure class="mobile-wrap alignleft size-thumbnail is-resized"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-186x186.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-3131518" width="93" height="93" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-186x186.jpg 186w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-383x383.jpg 383w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-450x450.jpg 450w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-768x768.jpg 768w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-580x580.jpg 580w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-776x776.jpg 776w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-214x214.jpg 214w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square.jpg 1080w" sizes="(max-width: 93px) 100vw, 93px" /></figure></div><h3 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Electricity Saved My Brain</h3><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <em>This is the third part in a series on deep brain stimulation for depression. <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/brain-implant-depression-electrode-stimulation-surgery">Read from the beginning</a> .</em></p></div><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Early in the morning on August 22, 2022, Jon&#39;s medical team told him that neurologist Helen Mayberg would check in with him just before his deep brain stimulation surgery. “Everybody is like, &#39;Dr. Mayberg is going to come in and give you a pumped-up speech.&#39;” She&#39;d explain how everything ought to go and what the team needed from Jon. She didn&#39;t disappoint, Jon says. “She came in and gave me the pep talk: &#39;All I need you to do is to be present,&#39;” she told him. “She was really adamant about that.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> In the middle of the surgery, the medical team woke Jon up from anesthesia. It was a hazy time, but Jon remembers it. “I&#39;m so awake, and I was so myself,” he recalls. “Dr. Mayberg is right in your face right away, and she&#39;s like, &#39;Jon, it&#39;s Dr. Mayberg and Dr. Figee.&#39; And I said, &#39;Doc, I need to tell you something.&#39; And she was so concerned, like, &#39;Yes, yes, yes?&#39; And I was like, &#39;I&#39;m present!&#39;</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “I&#39;m just busting her chops, and she&#39;s sitting there laughing. But that&#39;s how completely normal you are.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The day after surgery, Jon sat with Mayberg and another clinician as they began to turn on and off electrodes, searching for the pattern of stimulation that would influence nerve cells in the right way and in the right spot. Each time, Mayberg would ask him two key questions: Did he feel like walking his dog? And did he want to have friends over to sit around his fire pit? Jon&#39;s wife, Barbara, his dad and a crowd of doctors and researchers watched a video feed of this process from an overflow room.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> After trying a series of stimulation patterns and getting “yes” to their questions, the researchers settled on an electrical pattern, and Jon went home to Pennsylvania. “The next day, bandaged up on my head, I not only took the dog on a walk, I asked my son and my wife to come with me. I enjoyed the walk. I enjoyed the conversation. I enjoyed coming back home. I sat outside and had coffee. It&#39;s just surreal.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> As we talk, about six months after his surgery, Jon has no doubt about the outcome: “Instantaneously overnight I was healed,” he says. “I have been in remission from depression since the moment they turned that on.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Barbara, Jon&#39;s wife, has seen the shift from the outside. His motivation is back, she says. He&#39;s not as fidgety as he was. He&#39;s easier to talk to. He cooks elaborate dinners for the family. He even looks different. When he is sick, Jon has a clammy, pale, almost puffy look to him, Barbara says. “I haven&#39;t seen that look in six months, which is amazing,” she says. “He just looks healthier.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “He has the old Jon voice back. He annoys me more,” she says. “He&#39;s a super high-energy, outgoing person, and I&#39;m the quiet, withdrawn person who needs more time alone. I&#39;m like, &#39;Oh my God, would you just stop talking?&#39; That&#39;s a good thing, though, that&#39;s a good thing, because for a long time, he didn&#39;t want to talk at all.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> When Barbara and Jon got together in their early 20s, she thought Jon was the happiest and nicest person she had ever met. Now, “the person I met 20-something years ago is back,” she says. “I feel like he was lost for a long time.” </p><figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="680" height="492" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_3_inline.jpg" alt="Barbara hugs Jon Nelson in photo from early in their relationship." class="wp-image-3131439" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_3_inline.jpg 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_3_inline-529x383.jpg 529w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_3_inline-622x450.jpg 622w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_3_inline-257x186.jpg 257w" sizes="(max-width: 680px) 100vw, 680px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3131439">Barbara and Jon Nelson are shown here in the first picture they took together. Barbara says Jon&#39;s depression “probably shaped so much of who I am and how I am now in so many ways.”</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3131439">Courtesy of J. Nelson</span></figcaption></figure><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Changes after DBS</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Jon has no shortage of words to describe his recovery.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Amanda, the artist in New York City, who had DBS surgery on October 20, 2022, has trouble describing the immediate change. “Maybe it was like a little spark of energy. I was more chatty. It was easier to talk to people, just because it felt like there was a little something inside pushing.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Like Jon, her recovery has been incredibly fast. “I left the hospital on a Friday,” Amanda recalls. “By Sunday, I could tell it was working. By Wednesday … that&#39;s when I got completely better.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “I can&#39;t even describe the relief. I&#39;ve never felt relief so profound in my life,” she says. “You get used to living in pain. And when the pain is all of a sudden gone, you&#39;re like, &#39;What is this?&#39;”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Part of her life now includes what she calls “weird experiences” — taking pleasure in things. Candles, for instance. “I never enjoyed smells before. And now I have these candles, and they smell so good. Candles never smelled good before.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> A similar sentiment comes from Emily Hollenbeck, who also lives in New York City and had DBS surgery in 2021, about a year and a half before I spoke with her. When a certain pattern of brain stimulation was turned on during the surgery, she started to think about bacon. “I was tasting the bacon in my mind. I could taste that salt and the fat and the crispiness. I started to feel that sense of hunger.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Her depression had taken away any anticipation of upcoming pleasure. “My mouth won&#39;t water,” she says. “I won&#39;t really think about it.” With the stimulation, the contrast between disinterest and intense craving was “so immediate and so strong,” she says. “That&#39;s why it struck me.” In the days after the surgery, she also noticed she began to feel restless, like she wanted to go to the library. “I had these impulses to move, to do things, to enjoy things,” she says.</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> What brain areas does DBS hit?</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Jon, Amanda and Emily have been receiving constant brain stimulation targeted to a brain area called the subcallosal cingulate, or SCC. That&#39;s the same area that was targeted in the Broaden clinical trial, which was stopped prematurely because of poor early results.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> So, what&#39;s different now?</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Since Broaden, and armed with better brain-imaging techniques, scientists have learned a lot more about the SCC and how it connects to other parts of the brain. The area is not a uniform glob of brain tissue; it holds a confluence of diverse white matter tracts, nerve bundles that speed information to and fro.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> A recent presentation from Mayberg&#39;s research group described the outcomes of about 50 patients from the Broaden trial, people who continued to be stimulated and monitored after the trial officially ended. It turns out that the people who got better had their electrodes implanted in a fortuitous spot in the SCC, one that hit four key white matter tracts. “It was really about targeting,” Mayberg says.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The SCC — and the signals it sends to other brain areas — seems to have a role in generating negative emotions, immobility, cognitive sluggishness and heavy physical feelings. Stimulating there, researchers suspect, can overwhelm those nerve cells, tiring them out and making them effectively fall silent. That silence then has ripple effects at many different levels, from single cells to entire cohorts of brain areas. Those changes, the thinking goes, somehow turn down the negative malaise.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> It&#39;s a bit like taking off the parking brake, allowing energy and motivation to flow once more. This aspect of the SCC&#39;s job may explain why Jon went for a walk in the hospital halls and at home with his family, why Amanda felt a spark of energy and why Emily had an itch to get up and go to the library. </p><figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="680" height="282" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_4_inline-1-1.jpg" alt="Side-by-side brain scans with electrodes marked by a blue line and red dot and white matter tracks visible in yellow on the left and in green on the right." class="wp-image-3131441" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_4_inline-1-1.jpg 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_4_inline-1-1-330x137.jpg 330w" sizes="(max-width: 680px) 100vw, 680px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3131441">Deep brain stimulation for depression changes signals near the electrodes (red) and signals moving along brain fibers called white matter tracts (yellow and green). The subcallosal cingulum (left) and the ventral capsule/ventral striatum (right) are two current targets.</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3131441">SA Sheth and HS Mayberg/ <em>Annual Review of Neuroscience</em> 2023</span></figcaption></figure><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> But Mayberg and her colleagues at Mount Sinai aren&#39;t the only people conducting trials on DBS for depression, nor is their target the only one under consideration. Another promising target, called the ventral capsule/ventral striatum, or VC/VS, is more involved in feelings of reward. Stimulating there may be turning up the positive as opposed to dialing down the negative. Its connections to other brain regions are extensive, perhaps even more numerous than the SCC&#39;s.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Some of the big questions, says Sameer Sheth, a neurosurgeon and DBS researcher at Baylor College of Medicine in Houston, are about personalizing the technique: Which patients would benefit from which target in the brain and what type of stimulation? The SCC and the VC/VS both seem promising. In a way, the debate mirrors a similar one in DBS for Parkinson&#39;s disease, where several brain structures are possible targets. To determine where electrodes should be implanted, doctors now consider factors like how advanced the disease is, whether a patient needs to reduce their medication and if tremor is the main problem.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> To better understand the neural circuits related to mood, Sheth and his colleagues are conducting a clinical trial for depression that is using implanted electrodes to listen in on many parts of the brain. The study is designed, in part, to uncover how various types of stimulation, pointed toward various neural spots, affect the brain. Eventually, the team hopes, this knowledge could lead to personalized stimulation — bespoke electrical patterns tailored to each person. (Sheth has received consulting fees from various medical companies, including Boston Scientific and NeuroPace, and cofounded a neurotechnology company.)</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> I talked with one of the people in this trial, a man who wanted to remain anonymous. He was the first person to undergo this massive brain eavesdropping effort by Sheth and colleagues. As such, he became Patient 001, a designation he grew fond of, he says. He traveled to Houston from New York City, where he was living at the time, and was scheduled for surgery on March 9, 2020. His surgery squeaked through, just days before all nonemergency surgeries were canceled in the area because of the growing COVID pandemic.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> During surgery at Baylor St. Luke&#39;s Medical Center in Houston, Patient 001 was implanted with four electrode wires, two in the SCC and two in the VC/VS. He got 10 extra electrodes, too, implanted in areas connected to the SCC and VC/VS. These extras were temporary, there only to listen to his brain activity over a 10-day stay in the hospital. “I&#39;m not going to say the 10-day stay in the hospital was a walk in the park, because it wasn&#39;t,” he says. “But when you have nothing to lose and you&#39;re in hell, you&#39;ll do anything.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Like Jon, Patient 001 went through a similar testing phase with his electrodes. At one point, he felt something big. “I said, &#39;I don&#39;t know what you did, but it feels like I&#39;m online again. I&#39;m online.&#39; If you think of your brain as a computer, it felt like I had a virus, and then my hard drive crashed. And all of a sudden — boom. They control all the leads, and they reboot you, and you&#39;re OK again. I remember the doctor and the people in the OR literally laughing, like, &#39;That&#39;s a new one.&#39;</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “We laugh about it, but it came out of my heart,” he says. “It&#39;s how I felt.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> These stories all sound remarkable, and in all sorts of ways, they truly are. The four people with depression I&#39;ve told you about were pulled out of deep suffering and restored to themselves — for now, and for what Jon and the researchers expect will be a very long time.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> But like any story, this one has its moments of despair.</p><hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" /><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <em>In the next article in the series, <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/dbs-deep-brain-stimulation-depression">find out why the road to recovery is not always smooth</a> .</em></p><p class="has-gray-light-background-color has-background" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <em>This series was made possible with funding from the Alfred P. Sloan Foundation.</em></p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_3_feat-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="175210" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_3_feat-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title> What&#39;s it like to live with deep brain stimulation for depression?</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/dbs-deep-brain-stimulation-depression<dc:creator><![CDATA[Laura Sanders]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Thu, 21 Sep 2023 13:35:00 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Neuroscience]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3131393 </guid><description><![CDATA[The fourth article in the series explores the physical and emotional challenges of experimental brain implants for depression.]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<div class="wp-block-sciencenews-content-sidebar"><div class="wp-block-image is-style-rounded has-alignleft" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><figure class="mobile-wrap alignleft size-thumbnail is-resized"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-186x186.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-3131518" width="93" height="93" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-186x186.jpg 186w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-383x383.jpg 383w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-450x450.jpg 450w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-768x768.jpg 768w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-580x580.jpg 580w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-776x776.jpg 776w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-214x214.jpg 214w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square.jpg 1080w" sizes="(max-width: 93px) 100vw, 93px" /></figure></div><h3 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Electricity Saved My Brain</h3><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <em>This is the fourth part in a series on deep brain stimulation for depression. <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/brain-implant-depression-electrode-stimulation-surgery">Read from the beginning</a> .</em></p></div><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <em>[Content note: This story contains discussion of suicide.]</em></p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “The only thing I&#39;ll slightly complain about — and it&#39;s very vain — I only wish the batteries in your chest didn&#39;t show up so much,” says Patient 001.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> There is an intense physicality to deep brain stimulation for depression. Participants have two slight bumps on their head, wires under the skin of their neck and a battery-powered control unit implanted under the skin in their chest.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Because he was implanted with two sets of electrodes, Patient 001 has two battery packs, one on each side of his upper chest. He lives in a hot place near the ocean. “It just sucks I can&#39;t take my shirt off at the beach and not be self-conscious about that.” Sometimes the devices in his chest feel alien to him when he&#39;s going to sleep. “I put my hand on it to be comfortable,” he says.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Amanda has a strained relationship with the device, too. “I don&#39;t like the idea of it. I don&#39;t like how it feels. Every time I accidentally touch the wire in my neck, I&#39;m like, &#39;Ugh, ugh, I don&#39;t like it,&#39;” she says. “It&#39;s getting better, but sometimes I can still feel that thing in my chest just sitting there.” </p><div class="wp-block-image  has-alignleft" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><figure class="alignleft size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="680" height="680" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_4_inline-2.png" alt="An illustration of the top half of a person with two wires in their brain and a gray box in their chest connected to those wires." class="wp-image-3131383" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_4_inline-2.png 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_4_inline-2-383x383.png 383w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_4_inline-2-450x450.png 450w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_4_inline-2-186x186.png 186w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_4_inline-2-580x580.png 580w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_4_inline-2-214x214.png 214w" sizes="(max-width: 680px) 100vw, 680px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3131383">In deep brain stimulation for depression, electrodes surgically implanted in the brain are connected via wires under the skin to a battery-powered control box in the chest. The programmable control box tells the electrodes when to send signals that stimulate the brain.</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3131383">Erin Otwell</span></figcaption></figure></div><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> She also points out the annoyingly low-tech charging process, which is done with a wireless charger draped around her neck. Her charger shows only 10 percent increments, and the screen is on for only a minute before it locks up, without indicating that the charging is done. “They can get better at that part,” she says.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> In addition to the charging, there are lots of tasks these volunteers complete as part of the research — surveys, mood ratings, video journals. Twice daily, Amanda clicks what looks like a TV remote at home to collect brain data. “I&#39;m Bluetooth-enabled,” she says with a laugh. “I upload from the computer to the server at the hospital.” She and others also make regular trips to the lab at Mount Sinai.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> These days, Jon takes the train from his house just outside Philadelphia to Mount Sinai so often that he knows exactly which crack in the sidewalk to stand by as he waits for his train at the New Jersey Transit station. On one of his visits to the lab, a mess of scalp electrodes were eavesdropping on his brain. The scientist doing the measurements, neuroscientist Allison Waters, mentioned that his electrode leads were zipping 130 pulses of electricity into his brain per second.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “She just said it off the cuff,” Jon says. Later, with his daughter, Jon did the math for a full day, doubling it for each side: “22 million, 500 thousand electrical pulses to my brain,” Jon says. “That&#39;s what has kept me alive.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> During Jon&#39;s surgery on August 22, 2022, doctors told him that his only job was to be present. After his incisions healed, he was given a new task: rehabbing his brain. Jon was initially dismissive of the new job. He already felt fantastic, cocky almost, and didn&#39;t buy that he needed to work hard on rehab. “In the back of my head, I&#39;m like, &#39;OK, weirdos. I&#39;m not sick. This is great. I&#39;m good. I got this.&#39;”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> But about six weeks after his surgery, everything fell apart.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> A malaise crept in, and Jon freaked out. “Oh my God, I feel it,” he said. “I feel it in my body.” He snapped right back into the habits that depression solidified: overeating, sleeping too much and hiding away from his family. “My wife, I&#39;ll never forget it, was like, &#39;Hey, we got an appointment at the school.&#39;” But Jon told her he couldn&#39;t make it; he was busy. It was a lie. “I didn&#39;t have anything going on,” he says.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Jon knew that as part of the study protocol, around the sixth month, researchers would turn off his stimulation, a looming event that made him intensely anxious. His shift alarmed him so much that on the night of October 6, he sent an email to the Mount Sinai psychiatrist Martijn Figee to ask if his stimulation had been turned off earlier than planned. “Is there an earlier part of the program where it gets shut off too, such as now, and that is also part of the experiment?” Jon wrote. “Even if it was shut off, could you even tell me that?”<br><br> An hour and a half later, the email back was clear: “Your device is absolutely on <em>.”</em> His psychologist would address it with him at their next appointment.</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Relearning to live with emotions</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> As brain implants are used more and more, the risks of DBS have become somewhat clear. Regardless of why a person is getting it or where in the brain it targets,the technique can, like any medical procedure, go sideways. Electrode leads in the brain can break; the chest controller can fail; batteries can die. Infections, in both the head and chest, are a risk, as is wire tethering, a painful condition, also called bowstringing, in which scar tissue grows around the wire in the neck.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> DBS can also carry risks that are distinct from other surgeries. Electrical stimulation in certain parts of the brain has been linked to unwanted behavioral changes. For people receiving stimulation for Parkinson&#39;s disease, there have been cases of gambling problems and hypersexual behavior.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> In one unusual case, a Dutch man treated for obsessive-compulsive disorder developed a <a href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fnbeh.2014.00152/full" target="_blank" rel="noopener">brand-new and intense affinity for Johnny Cash hits</a> , especially “Ring of Fire,” “Folsom Prison Blues” and “Sunday Morning Coming Down.” When his stimulations diminish or his batteries die, the man subconsciously switches back to listening to his old favorites — Dutch-language songs and classics by the Beatles and the Rolling Stones.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> People being treated with DBS for depression have experienced relapses when the device accidentally stops working, for instance due to a battery failure or a wire breaking. But that&#39;s not what happened to Jon.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Worries over spiraling dark moods surface among people with DBS for depression, says psychologist Shannon O&#39;Neill, who works with Jon and other people treated with DBS at Mount Sinai. “We often talk significantly about the difference for them of how they can distinguish between depression and normal everyday sadness,” O&#39;Neill says. This is the rehab part, she says. People who have lived with severe depression for years need to relearn how to recognize and tolerate garden-variety emotions, including sorrow.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> As O&#39;Neill describes ordinary sadness, it reminds me of the analogy that emotions are like the weather. We can spend the morning under heavy cloud cover, and then maybe we luck out with a full-blast sunny afternoon. But it&#39;s fleeting. Likewise, our feelings are impermanent, O&#39;Neill says. “Negative emotions come and go, just like positive emotions come and go. It can be passing and not ever-present.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Emily Hollenbeck, whose DBS surgery was in 2021, says her recovery took time. “You&#39;re letting your brain relearn how to live in the world without the constant threat of severe negativity, suicidality, all of that.” She had to learn how to cope with emotions, and trust that she&#39;ll get through bad situations. “Basically, I&#39;m relearning how to ride the bike, you know?”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Understanding that these feelings are transitory — that ups and downs happen — is something people with severe depression haven&#39;t practiced, because they hadn&#39;t had to. They&#39;ve been perpetually stuck under heavy cloud cover. Emerging into an emotional landscape with those ups and downs can be intensely unsettling.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “At first it was scary,” says Amanda, who had DBS surgery last fall. “At first I felt like I was standing on the edge of a cliff.” An artist, Amanda draws her experiences to help her think them through. One of her pictures shows a cartoon Amanda wearing a rainbow shirt, standing high on a ledge of bright green grass with blue sky overhead. But she&#39;s looking over the edge to the darkness below. “I had been pulled out of this giant pit, and I was worried that I would fall back in it again.” </p><figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1030" height="700" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_2_inline-2_REV.jpg" alt="An illustration of a smiling Cartoon Amanda floating on top of the sea while the sun shines down and a one-ton weight has sunk to the sea floor." class="wp-image-3131552" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_2_inline-2_REV.jpg 1030w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_2_inline-2_REV-564x383.jpg 564w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_2_inline-2_REV-662x450.jpg 662w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_2_inline-2_REV-274x186.jpg 274w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_2_inline-2_REV-768x522.jpg 768w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_2_inline-2_REV-853x580.jpg 853w" sizes="(max-width: 1030px) 100vw, 1030px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3131552">Amanda, who received deep brain stimulation surgery in 2022, depicts her experience as art, often with a character named “cartoon Amanda.”</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3131552">Courtesy of Amanda</span></figcaption></figure><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> But she hasn&#39;t. When people recover from depression with DBS, they generally stay well, several studies suggest. Between three and six years after surgery, about 60 percent of <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/21285143/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">patients had sustained improvements</a> , Mayberg and colleagues reported in 2011 in the <em>American Journal of Psychiatry.</em> In a longer-term study, most of a group of 28 people who had deep brain stimulation for major depression or a type of bipolar disorder <a href="https://ajp.psychiatryonline.org/doi/10.1176/appi.ajp.2019.18121427" target="_blank" rel="noopener">saw benefits for more than eight years</a> , the researchers reported in 2019 in the same journal.</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Does DBS make people happy?</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The idea of a machine forcing happiness on us or taking away sorrow — that kind of mind control is unsettling for most of us. We are fiercely protective of the idea that our feelings originate inside of ourselves, that we are in charge here. So the idea that artificial happiness can be created by a computer that controls electrodes in our brain hooked to wires that snake down our neck? No thanks.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> That sentiment is understandable, but it&#39;s not what people with these implants experience. As I&#39;ve talked with people who had lived first with devastating depression and then with these devices, I have come to think that these implants do not make a person feel artificial joy. “DBS is not going to give you happiness,” O&#39;Neill says. Instead, “it just kind of clears the way.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Overcoming misconceptions about what this technology can and can&#39;t do is yet another burden for Jon and others. The patients I spoke with were incredibly candid about their depression and their treatment. They graciously tolerated my questions. But being open about their medical condition and treatment can exact a steep price.</p><hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" /><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <em>If you or someone you know is facing a suicidal crisis or emotional distress, call or text the 988 Suicide &amp; Crisis Lifeline at 988.</em></p><hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" /><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <em>The next articles<a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/brain-implant-depression-electrode-stimulation-stigma">dives into the tough topic of stigma around mental disorders and their treatments</a> .</em></p><p class="has-gray-light-background-color has-background" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <em>This series was made possible with funding from the Alfred P. Sloan Foundation.</em></p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_4_feat-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="126236" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_4_feat-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title> There&#39;s a stigma around brain implants and other depression treatments</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/brain-implant-depression-electrode-stimulation-stigma<dc:creator><![CDATA[Laura Sanders]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Thu, 21 Sep 2023 13:34:05 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Health & Medicine]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3131429 </guid><description><![CDATA[The fifth article in the series asks why people are so uncomfortable with changing the brain. ]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<div class="wp-block-sciencenews-content-sidebar"><div class="wp-block-image is-style-rounded has-alignleft" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><figure class="mobile-wrap alignleft size-thumbnail is-resized"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-186x186.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-3131518" width="93" height="93" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-186x186.jpg 186w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-383x383.jpg 383w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-450x450.jpg 450w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-768x768.jpg 768w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-580x580.jpg 580w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-776x776.jpg 776w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-214x214.jpg 214w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square.jpg 1080w" sizes="(max-width: 93px) 100vw, 93px" /></figure></div><h3 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Electricity Saved My Brain</h3><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <em>This is the fifth part in a series on deep brain stimulation for depression. <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/brain-implant-depression-electrode-stimulation-surgery">Read from the beginning</a> .</em></p></div><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Like many people who have struggled with a mental illness, Emily Hollenbeck had plenty of stories of people not quite getting it. One memorable instance happened as she was about to be anesthetized for an electroconvulsive therapy treatment. The anesthesiologist found out that she had a Ph.D. in psychology. “His eyes settle on me, and he goes, &#39;Oh, that&#39;s ironic.&#39;” Her academic background should have somehow prevented her illness, he seemed to imply.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> A palpable silence filled the room. “I remember literally biting my tongue,” she says, “being like, &#39;We&#39;re not going to sass the guy who&#39;s injecting the propofol.&#39;”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Being open about depression can bring judgment, and danger: “If you are honest about what you need for your mental health, you can suffer consequences,” says Emily, who had DBS surgery in 2021. That can include lost jobs, lost relationships and perhaps most crucially, lost health care.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Those consequences are why I&#39;m not identifying Patient 001 by his name. He works in an intensely intellectual and competitive field, and with a new baby at home, he can&#39;t risk losing business over people&#39;s mistaken assumptions.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> There&#39;s stigma surrounding depression, and there&#39;s stigma surrounding its treatments. When Patient 001 told his family he was getting experimental brain surgery, they didn&#39;t understand. “At first, they were like, &#39;You&#39;re crazy. It&#39;s unsafe.&#39;”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> In a way, their reaction tracks with people&#39;s suspicions toward other treatments for depression, and psychiatric disorders more generally, despite the fact that they work for many people. Since their rise to prominence in the 1990s, antidepressants have caught heat from people claiming the drugs change personalities and steal emotions. Electroconvulsive therapy is still crawling back after the damage done by portrayals like in the movie <em>One Flew Over the Cuckoo&#39;s Nest</em> . Even talk therapy can bring shame and secrecy.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> So perhaps it&#39;s not surprising that electrodes implanted into your brain raise a whole new set of assumptions, misgivings and judgments. People will live with these stigmas until society changes, until people start understanding what severe depression is like, and what treatments are like too.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “You&#39;re screaming for help, and they just don&#39;t understand,” Patient 001 tells me. “That&#39;s probably one of the reasons I&#39;m talking to you, even though I&#39;m doing it anonymously. I hope one day one kid reads what you&#39;re writing, and he finds DBS and he&#39;s cured.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Barbara, Jon&#39;s wife, is no stranger to people&#39;s uncomfortable reactions. “When we have told people that he has a pacemaker in his brain, basically, you get this sort of strange, &#39;Oh my God,&#39;…. They&#39;re like, &#39;What? You&#39;re going to let them do this to you?&#39;” There&#39;s this assumption, she says, that the brain is somehow different from other parts of the body. The heart can also need a device that delivers electrical stimulation. So why not the brain? “It&#39;s really interesting to see people, myself included, process that.” </p><figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><iframe loading="lazy" title="Depression &amp; DBS doesn’t just impact patients | Science News" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/ATQrx4FcNIA?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe></div><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> Watch a video of Barbara Nelson talking about her experience as a partner to someone with depression, and how DBS changed her family.</figcaption></figure><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> I&#39;ve been wondering the same thing: What sets the brain apart, and why are people so uncomfortable with attempts to change it?</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Here&#39;s what I think. Remember the Dutch guy who <a href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fnbeh.2014.00152/full" target="_blank" rel="noopener">all of a sudden loved Johnny Cash</a> after his implant was turned on? That story sounds a bit trivial. His new musical taste didn&#39;t bother him; it&#39;s a minor thing in the grand scheme of things. But that change, that switch, arguably bores straight to the core of our unease. So many of us, myself included, consider our brains — and the minds they create — the bedrock of our identity. So when a disease attacks the brain, or a treatment changes the brain, we get nervous.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> None of us like the thought of having a brain implant tell us what music we like, especially if we might not be aware of it. The stakes are much, much higher when it comes to how we feel.</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Does DBS change who you are?</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Reporting this story, I heard a lot of jokes about being a cyborg, Bluetooth-enabled, bionic. People would laugh as they said it. But I wondered if there was anything more to these offhand comments. Does this brain implant change who you are?</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Jon kindly tells me that he understands why I&#39;d ask. “I can only tell you that it is the exact opposite of that question,” he says. For him, DBS took away his poison. “It purely eliminates the disease…. That&#39;s it.”<br><br> Amanda echoes the sentiment: “Nothing I&#39;ve ever done has changed who I am or my personality,” she says, DBS included. “I&#39;m still the same person. I&#39;m just suffering more or less.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Emily flips my question on me in a beautifully philosophical twist: “What does that even mean? Where is the &#39;me&#39;?” Equating ourselves with our brains makes sense, she says, because much of what we experience comes through our brains. “But is that really where our selves are?” </p><figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="680" height="478" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_5_inline.jpg" alt="portrait of Emily Hollenbeck" class="wp-image-3131432" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_5_inline.jpg 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_5_inline-545x383.jpg 545w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_5_inline-640x450.jpg 640w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_5_inline-265x186.jpg 265w" sizes="(max-width: 680px) 100vw, 680px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3131432">Emily Hollenbeck, like other people with DBS implants, had to relearn how to cope with her new emotional range.</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3131432">Courtesy of Emily Hollenbeck</span></figcaption></figure><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Who she is, Emily says, is an activity, a choice. Her depression took away those choices and altered who she was. But now, “I don&#39;t have that feeling, so which of those is correct? I don&#39;t know. But I know which one I like better. I know that&#39;s not a satisfactory answer for your question, but what really gets to the heart of it is that I feel like I&#39;m untethered, and I have the ability now to focus on the things that I do really care about. And that&#39;s where my <em>self</em> lies.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> These days, Jon says, his sense of self is lighter. Without the poison coursing through his body, Jon feels better, more energized, more present in his life with wife, Barbara, their three kids, a dog, a cat and a bearded dragon named Lizzy. But, as his daily surveys make absolutely clear, he&#39;s still crabby. “There are certain things that you realize are the disease, and certain things that are innate in who you are,” he says. His irritability scores didn&#39;t budge after DBS. “I guess I&#39;m just a cranky middle-aged dude now.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Barbara may be one of the best judges of who Jon is now. Is he different somehow with DBS and without severe depression? “I don&#39;t feel like he&#39;s changed,” Barbara says. “I don&#39;t feel like I have a different person living in my house. It&#39;s not that creepy, sci-fi way, like there&#39;s this new person,” she says. It&#39;s just him, the Jon she met all those years ago.</p><hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" /><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <em>Our final article in the series <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/future-deep-brain-stimulation-depression">looks to the future for Jon and his family, and for deep brain stimulation</a> .</em></p><p class="has-gray-light-background-color has-background" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <em>This series was made possible with funding from the Alfred P. Sloan Foundation.</em></p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_5_feat-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="160038" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_5_feat-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title> What&#39;s the future of deep brain stimulation for depression?</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/future-deep-brain-stimulation-depression<dc:creator><![CDATA[Laura Sanders]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Thu, 21 Sep 2023 13:33:32 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Neuroscience]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3131448 </guid><description><![CDATA[The final story of the series describes efforts to simplify and improve brain implants for severe depression.]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<div class="wp-block-sciencenews-content-sidebar"><div class="wp-block-image is-style-rounded has-alignleft" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><figure class="mobile-wrap alignleft size-thumbnail is-resized"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-186x186.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-3131518" width="93" height="93" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-186x186.jpg 186w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-383x383.jpg 383w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-450x450.jpg 450w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-768x768.jpg 768w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-580x580.jpg 580w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-776x776.jpg 776w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-214x214.jpg 214w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square.jpg 1080w" sizes="(max-width: 93px) 100vw, 93px" /></figure></div><h3 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Electricity Saved My Brain</h3><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <em>This is the final part in a series on deep brain stimulation for depression. <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/brain-implant-depression-electrode-stimulation-surgery">Read from the beginning</a> .</em></p></div><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Neurologist Helen Mayberg cringes at the slow pace of DBS research. Her <a href="https://www.cell.com/neuron/fulltext/S0896-6273(05)00156-X?_returnURL=https%3A%2F%2Flinkinghub.elsevier.com%2Fretrieve%2Fpii%2FS089662730500156X%3Fshowall%3Dtrue" target="_blank" rel="noopener">first paper describing DBS for depression</a> in the subcallosal cingulate (then called Brodmann Area 25) appeared in the journal <em>Neuron</em> in 2005. Almost 20 years later, she almost can&#39;t believe that researchers are not further along in bringing this technique to people who would benefit from it.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “On the other hand, we&#39;ve learned so much that maybe it&#39;s not so bad,” Mayberg says. Still, she feels impatient. “We don&#39;t have a lot of time,” she says. “People are dying now, so let&#39;s fix them. And then we can make something better.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Mayberg hopes to see the treatment become streamlined. The first heart pacemaker was an incredible piece of technology, but it was giant and clunky. Today, the powerful device, usually about the size of a matchbook, sits near millions of people&#39;s hearts, keeping them beating. As with the heart, for the brain, “how do you go from complicated to simple? Everything is about the prototyping and the simplification,” she says.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> What&#39;s next? “What&#39;s the future of this, the future three steps ahead?” Mayberg says. “I have no idea.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Despite stories from Jon Nelson and others, deep brain stimulation still has its stigma to overcome, even in the research world. Questions of autonomy — of control over feelings and actions — crop up in ethics discussions of brain technology. But to Martijn Figee, the psychiatrist and DBS researcher who has worked with many people implanted with electrodes, those questions are a “luxury problem.” That framing ignores the idea that mental illness itself takes away a person&#39;s control. “People who work in DBS are always a little frustrated by these discussions,” Figee says. “We&#39;re always like, &#39;Talk to the patients.&#39;”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Figee, who receives consulting fees from Medtronic, a device company that makes brain implants, and his colleagues asked people before and after surgery for DBS for obsessive-compulsive disorder and Parkinson&#39;s about their feelings of being in control of themselves. People did not report a loss of feeling in control of themselves after the procedure. In fact, the people treated for OCD reported a bigger jump in autonomy and control than the Parkinson&#39;s patients. “That&#39;s not something that bothered them at all,” Figee says, “because the OCD was more of a prison to them than the fact that they have this implant.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Psychologist Shannon O&#39;Neill, who treats people with DBS at Mount Sinai, says she hopes that the procedure will be more readily understood in the future: “What I&#39;d love is a shift toward not making it a last resort,” she says. “I wonder if we wait too long to give an individual DBS.” She doesn&#39;t mean that brain implants would be an early treatment, but instead, she wants other health care professionals to have more awareness of the procedure so that they can refer people who have run out of hope.</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> What are the open questions?</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> What&#39;s next will almost certainly include nuanced and complex science. Big questions remain about where in the brain to stimulate, for which people and what kind of stimulation. Jon and Amanda are participating in follow-up studies searching for signs of recovery in their brains, bodies and microexpressions on their faces, and even in their voices. “The commitments are out of control,” Jon jokes. He spends eight minutes twice a day recording his brain waves, along with video journals and daily, weekly and monthly surveys. His brain is imaged regularly.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Researchers are searching for a hallmark, a signature, that can tell them the method is working. “I need to know when the depression is away, and I need to have a way to discriminate,” Mayberg says. “When are you having a bad day and when are you relapsing? Those are not the same thing.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Mayberg and her colleagues just described one such hallmark in six people who underwent DBS for depression. A <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-023-06541-3#Sec7" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">collection of changes</a> in brain behavior can indicate when a person has recovered, the researchers reported September 20 in <em>Nature</em> .</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> A handful of trials are putting a spin on the typical DBS approach and studying what&#39;s called adaptive DBS, which kicks in only when a certain pathological brain activity pattern is detected. That approach has <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/brain-implant-severe-depression-activity-stimulation">worked well for a woman named Sarah with severe depression</a> . Researchers at the University of California, San Francisco <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41591-021-01480-w" target="_blank" rel="noopener">published the details of her improvements</a> in 2021.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Similar on-demand efforts are happening for other disorders, including binge eating and post-traumatic stress disorder. Jay Gill, a brain researcher and medical student at UCLA told me that one man, a veteran with PTSD, described having an aura, a sort of premonition, just before his symptoms would get bad. With his adaptive DBS system in place, he still gets triggered and feels the aura, but instead of feeling worse, a feeling of calm sets in.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The optimal DBS approach for depression may be similar to the approach for PTSD, OCD, addiction and other psychiatric disorders. Or maybe not. There&#39;s still so much to learn.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Not everyone thinks about depression, or any illness for that matter, as a battle. Jon does. And there were days — lots of days — when he thought he&#39;d lose it. </p><figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="680" height="419" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_6_inline.jpg" alt="A photo of Jon Nelson standing on an ice rink next to a red hockey goal." class="wp-image-3131450" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_6_inline.jpg 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_6_inline-622x383.jpg 622w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_6_inline-302x186.jpg 302w" sizes="(max-width: 680px) 100vw, 680px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3131450">Jon Nelson&#39;s deep brain stimulation treatment hasn&#39;t made him happy all the time, but he now enjoys experiences more, including moments like coaching hockey and softball.</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3131450">AIDAN KAHN</span></figcaption></figure><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> These days, the Nelson house is bright. It&#39;s full of laughter, riddles, good-natured teasing, homemade pizza — and an energetic kid on in-line skates who twirls and glides through the kitchen loop. It&#39;s also full of hope for a future that&#39;s better than the past. That makes me reluctant to ask Barbara a question that I know will be hard for her to answer: Is she worried that Jon&#39;s DBS treatment will stop working?</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “That&#39;s always in the back of my mind a little bit,” she tells me. Over the years, Barbara has learned to temper her expectations for the future. “You just never really know what&#39;s going to happen,” she says. In a way, she&#39;s still guarded. “I don&#39;t know if this is going to work forever,” she says.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “But my perspective is that even if something changes, we have had this time with him.… And if it keeps going forever, that&#39;s amazing. It&#39;s amazing. I hope it does.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> On the drives home from softball, field hockey, golf, basketball and ice hockey, Jon and whichever kids are around have chats. “I always call it &#39;car talk with the kids.&#39;” In one of these car talks, Jon&#39;s youngest piped up. “He&#39;s like, &#39;Dad, I&#39;m so happy you just kept fighting for us.&#39; These little comments that come out of nowhere. I&#39;m like, &#39;Oh my God. They get it. They understand it.&#39; It&#39;s a trip.”</p><p class="has-gray-light-background-color has-background" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <em>This series was made possible with funding from the Alfred P. Sloan Foundation.</em></p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_6_feat-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="214800" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_6_feat-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item></channel></rss>