<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/" xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/" xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"><channel><title> חדשות המדע </title><atom:link href="https://www.sciencenews.org/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org<description> עיתונאות עצמאית מאז 1921</description><lastbuilddate> יום ה&#39;, 21 בספטמבר 2023 21:21:16 +0000</lastbuilddate><language> en-US</language><sy:updateperiod> מדי שעה</sy:updateperiod><sy:updatefrequency> 1</sy:updatefrequency><generator> https://wordpress.org/?v=6.2.2</generator><item><title> OSIRIS-REx של נאס&quot;א מוכן להחזיר חלקים מהאסטרואיד Bennu לכדור הארץ</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/nasa-osiris-rex-return-asteroid-bennu-earth<dc:creator><![CDATA[James R. Riordon]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Fri, 22 Sep 2023 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Space]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3131719 </guid><description><![CDATA[Asteroid dirt from Bennu could help reveal clues about the material that came together to make the solar system — and possibly where life comes from.]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<p>שבע שנים הן הרבה זמן לחכות לשירות הספק שלך כדי לספק חבילה. זה כמה זמן עבר מאז<a href="https://solarsystem.nasa.gov/missions/osiris-rex/in-depth/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">החללית OSIRIS-REx של נאס&quot;א</a> יצאה לדרך לאסוף סלעים ואבק מהאסטרואיד בנו. אבל החבילה כמעט יצאה למשלוח.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> ב-24 בספטמבר, החללית תטוס ליד כדור הארץ ותפיל קפסולה המכילה חומר <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/nasa-osiris-rex-spacecraft-asteroid-bennu-sample-collection">שנאסף מבנו</a> באוקטובר 2020 - אם הכל ילך כשורה ( <em>SN: 21/10/20</em> ).</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> זוהי המשימה השלישית לשלוף חלקים מאסטרואיד, והראשונה עבור נאס&quot;א וארה&quot;ב. כמות חומרי האסטרואידים על הסיפון הפעם עולה בהרבה על המיקרוגרם שחללית <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/blog/deleted-scenes/hayabusa-asteroid-sample-return-mission-lands-australia">Hayabusa של יפן החזירה ב-2005</a> , מהאסטרואיד איטוקאווה, וחמשת הגרם ש- <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/japan-hayabusa2-asteroid-dirt-sample-clues-early-solar-system">Hayabusa2 אסף ב-2018</a> מ-Ryugu ( <em>SN: 14/6/10; SN: 12/7 /20</em> ).</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> מדגם בנו אמור להגיע בתזמון ובדיוק שיגרמו למרבית שירותי המשלוחים היבשתיים לקנא. לאחר מסע של שלוש שנים חזרה מהאסטרואיד, הקפסולה צריכה להיכנס לאטמוספירה בשעה 10:42 בבוקר EDT, אומרת נאס&quot;א. בעקבות ירידה לוהטת בתחילה, הקפסולה תשחרר מצנח ותרד ליעדה בבסיס חיל האוויר היל ליד אוגדן, יוטה.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> סיקור חי של האירוע יהיה זמין <a href="https://www.nasa.gov/nasalive" target="_blank" rel="noopener">באתר האינטרנט של נאס&quot;א</a> החל מהשעה 10 בבוקר EDT.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> אם פיסות האסטרואידים ישרדו את הירידה, הם יכולים לעזור לחשוף איזה סוג של חומרים חברו יחד לבניית מערכת השמש שלנו. התבוננות טובה בחומר שממנו בנוי עשויה לספק תובנות לגבי הסיכונים שהאסטרואידים הסמוכים מהווים לנו, במקרה שהם במסלול התנגשות עם כדור הארץ. מטען האסטרואיד עשוי אפילו להכיל רמזים שיעזרו לענות על אחת השאלות הגדולות ביותר במדע - איך התחילו החיים?</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> &quot;אני באמת מרוכז ב... לנסות להבין אם סוגים אלה של אסטרואידים עשירים בפחמן אולי סיפקו את זרעי החיים&quot;, אומר מדען הפלנטה דנטה לורטה מאוניברסיטת אריזונה בטוסון, שמוביל את משימת OSIRIS-REx. &quot;אז אנחנו מחפשים דברים כמו חומצות אמינו שנמצאות בחלבונים שלנו וחומצות גרעין&quot;, אבני הבניין של ההוראות הגנטיות שמאפשרות חיים על כדור הארץ.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> לורטה אומרת שבעצם אין סיכוי למצוא משהו חי על אסטרואידים כמו בנו. אבל בסלעים ובאבק שנאספו, &quot;יכולנו באמת לראות כיצד כימיה מולקולרית אורגנית יכולה להתפתח לפני שהחיים מופיעים.&quot; </p><figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" width="680" height="414" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092123_jr_bennu-return_inline.jpg" alt="איור של חללית OSIRIS-REx של נאס&quot;א נוגעת קלות באסטרואיד בנו." class="wp-image-3131722" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092123_jr_bennu-return_inline.jpg 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092123_jr_bennu-return_inline-629x383.jpg 629w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092123_jr_bennu-return_inline-306x186.jpg 306w" sizes="(max-width: 680px) 100vw, 680px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3131722">החללית OSIRIS-REx של נאס&quot;א (מתוארת נוגעת קלות באסטרואיד בנו) אמורה להוריד את דגימת האסטרואיד שלה ביוטה לאחר נסיעה של שלוש שנים חזרה הביתה.</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3131722">נאס&quot;א</span></figcaption></figure><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> בערך 250 גרם, דגימת האסטרואידים בקפסולת ההחזרה של OSIRIS-REx היא רק קצת יותר כבדה מכוס קפה. אבל זה מטמון עצום של חומר אסטרואיד, מבחינת מדעני המשימה. גודל המדגם עולה בהרבה על הכמות שציפתה לה בתחילה, אומרת לורטה.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> &quot;המצאנו 15 גרם&quot; כגודל מדגם סביר לניתוח, הוא אומר, &quot;שזו כמות עצומה של חומר בכימיה אנליטית בימינו&quot;. אבל נאס&quot;א מאפשרת ללורטה ולצוות שלו לשמור רק רבע מהמדגם לשימוש עצמי. חלק מהחלק הנותר יופץ למדענים ברחבי העולם, והשאר יישמר למחקרים עתידיים.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> זה אומר שאיסוף 60 גרם מבנו היה מספיק כדי להבטיח שלורטה ועמיתיו יש את הדגימה המקווה שלהם. &quot;העובדה שהתגברנו ארבע פעמים זה פשוט מוצלח בצורה פנומנלית&quot;, אומרת לורטה.</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> מתכון לאסטרואיד</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> החוקרים כבר מדמיינים את כל מה שהם יכולים ללמוד מבנו.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> הפיזיקאי Mikael Granvik מאוניברסיטת הלסינקי מקווה שניתוחים של החומר Bennu יסייעו לחשוף את הפוטנציאל לכריית אסטרואידים עבור מים וחומרי גלם שיכולים לספק משימות חלל עתידיות.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> פיסות האסטרואיד יכולות גם לסייע בחקירותיו לגבי עד כמה שברירי כמה סלעי חלל עשויים להיות. &quot;מה קורה לאסטרואידים מאותו סוג של בנו כשהם מתקרבים לשמש?&quot; אומר גרנוויק, שאינו חבר בצוות OSIRIS-REx. הוא ועמיתיו מציעים שהאינטראקציה עם השמש גורמת ל&quot;אסטרואידים של ערימת הריסות&quot; כאלה, העשויים מחומר קשור רופף, להתפרק. ההשערה יכולה להסביר מדוע יש פחות אסטרואידים של ערימות הריסות במסלולים ליד השמש מהצפוי.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> כדי לבדוק את הרעיון, גרנוויק חושף דגימות לתנאים קשים שמעריכים איך זה יהיה ליד השמש, ובעצם הורס את החומר. מסיבה זו, הוא לא מצפה להשתמש באף אחד מסלע בנו היקר. במקום זאת, Granvik מקווה ללמוד את מתכון האסטרואידים של Bennu ואז להזמין אנלוגים לאסטרואידים מספקים שימזגו יחד חומרים המחקים את תערובת Bennu. זו דוגמה לאופן שבו המדגם שהוחזר יכול להרחיב את הזדמנויות המחקר אפילו עבור מדענים שלא מקבלים חלק מהדבר האמיתי. </p><figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><iframe loading="lazy" title="כיצד OSIRIS-REx של נאס&quot;א יחזיר חלקים של אסטרואיד לכדור הארץ | חדשות המדע" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/SEJ-Ed1_UQ4?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe></div><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> לאחר מסע של שלוש שנים על סיפון החללית OSIRIS-REx, קפסולה המכילה אבק וסלעים מהאסטרואיד Bennu תבצע צלילה לוהטת לאטמוספירה של כדור הארץ ב-24 בספטמבר, כפי שניתן לראות בסימולציה זו. ברגע שהוא משחרר את הקפסולה, OSIRIS-REx יירה את המטוסים שלו כדי להסיט את עצמו הלאה לאסטרואיד אפופיס תחת השם החדש OSIRIS-APEX. בינתיים, הקפסולה תעוף לכיוון כדור הארץ כמו כדור אש. למרות שנדחף במהלך הירידה הגסה, הדגימה תהיה מוגנת מהטמפרטורות העזה של כניסה חוזרת על ידי מגן החום של הקפסולה. כשהקפסולה מתקרבת לקרקע, היא תקפיץ מצנח ותיסחף בעדינות את שארית הדרך למטה ביוטה, שם, אם הכל ילך כשורה, מדענים יכולים לאסוף את המשלוח המיוחל שלהם.</figcaption></figure><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> סיפורים שבנו יכול לספר</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> עבור המדענית הפלנטרית ג&#39;סיקה סנשיין מאוניברסיטת מרילנד בקולג&#39; פארק, חלק ניכר מהערך במשימות החזרה לדוגמה הוא בסיפורים שאסטרואידים יכולים לספר לנו על היווצרות כדור הארץ ומערכת השמש. &quot;אנחנו חושבים עליהם כעל סוג של סלעים מתים, והם לא. כלומר, הם עברו אבולוציה משמעותית, כימית ופיזית כאחד, ב-4.5 מיליארד השנים מאז היווצרותם&quot;, אומר סאנשיין.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> כמו לורטה, Sunshine מקווה ללמוד כיצד תהליכים אלה הובילו בסופו של דבר למקורות החיים, אך חקר אסטרואידים קרובים לכדור הארץ הוא חיוני להבנת האיומים שגם אסטרואידים מהווים. &quot;באופן עקרוני, הם יכלו לתת לנו חיים והם יכלו לקחת אותם&quot;, אומרת סאנשיין, &quot;כלומר, מנקודת המבט של הדינוזאור, הם כן לקחו אותם.&quot;</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Sunshine חבר בצוות ששלח את חללית ה-DART<a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/dart-mission-deflected-asteroid-for-planetary-defense">לדחוף את האסטרואיד דימורפוס</a> למסלול חדש כדי לראות אם אפשר לדחוף אסטרואידים ממסלולים המאיימים על כדור הארץ ( <em>SN: 10/11/22</em> ). &quot;אם אתה מודאג לגבי בעיית סכנת האסטרואידים, אנחנו די טוב יותר להבין מהי השונות הפיזית וההרכבה של כל הדברים האלה שעלולים לפגוע בנו&quot;, אומר Sunshine. &quot;כי תלוי ממה הם עשויים ואיך הם עשויים, זה ישנה את ההשפעה שלהם כשהם פוגעים בנו. אם אי פעם יפגעו בנו&quot;.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> ייתכן שבקפסולת ההחזרה יהיו יותר מחלקים בלבד של בנו, אומר האסטרונום הומברטו קמפינס מאוניברסיטת מרכז פלורידה באורלנדו, שהוא חבר בצוות OSIRIS-REx. כמה סלעים מחזירי אור בבנו אינם תואמים את שאר האסטרואיד, שהוא חשוך מאוד. הסיבה הסבירה ביותר, אומר קמפינס, היא שהנתחים הבהירים מגיעים מהתנגשויות עם אסטרואידים אחרים.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> &quot;אין שום ערובה, אבל אני מקווה שבדגימה שלנו יהיו חלקים, חלקים, גרגרים שמקורם באסטרואידים האחרים האלה&quot;, אומר קמפינס. ניתוחים מרוחקים מצביעים על כך שחלק מהחלקים הבהירים בבנו מתאימים לאסטרואיד וסטה. &quot;אז תהיה לנו החזרה מדגם לא רק מבנו, אלא אולי מווסטה&quot;, אומר קמפינס, &quot;או מי יודע איזה עוד אסטרואיד.&quot;</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> למרות שזו תהיה החזרת הדגימה הראשונה של נאס&quot;א של אסטרואיד, <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/dust-nabbed-spacecraft-may-be-outside-solar-system">משימת אבק כוכבים</a> בשנת 2006 החזירה בהצלחה דגימות של השביט Wild-2, גם ליוטה ( <em>SN: 14/8/14</em> ).</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> התחנה הבאה: אסטרואיד אפופיס</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> המשימה של OSIRIS-REx לא תסתיים עם משלוח החבילות ביוטה. &quot;אחרי שהורדנו את הקפסולה&quot;, אומרת לורטה, &quot;החללית עדיין בריאה. זה הולך לירות תמרון סטיה, ואז הוא במסלול לאסטרואיד אחר - אסטרואיד אפופיס&quot;, שנמצא בערך כמו בנו רחוק מכדור הארץ.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> בשלב זה, הלוויין יקבל שם חדש, OSIRIS-APEX, והוא יוגדר להקיף את אפופיס ברגע שיגיע באפריל 2029, אם הכל ילך כמתוכנן. אבל זה לא יחזיר עוד דגימות לכדור הארץ. בניגוד למשאיות המשלוחים המקומיות שלך, OSIRIS-REx תוכנן לשאת רק חבילה אחת ולבצע משלוח בודד. לאחר יום ראשון מסתיימים ימי האספקה ​​של החללית.</p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092123_jr_bennu-return_feat-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="227398" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092123_jr_bennu-return_feat-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title> הקלטת פה היא אולי פריצת שינה טרנדית, אבל המדע מאחורי זה דק</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/mouth-taping-trend-sleep-science-slim<dc:creator><![CDATA[Meghan Rosen]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Fri, 22 Sep 2023 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Health & Medicine]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3131593 </guid><description><![CDATA[Mouth taping is big on social media, but few studies have evaluated it. Some evidence suggests that sealing the lips shut may help people with sleep apnea.]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<p>אולי TikTok הראה לכם אנשים שמים סרט קטן על השפתיים שלהם. או אולי אינסטגרם הגישה לכם מודעות לרצועות פה דביקות. ברשתות החברתיות ומחוצה לה, טרנד שנקרא הדבקת פה הוא לסתום את הפה של אנשים בלילה - לעזור להם לנשום דרך האף.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> זאק פורד, בן 38, ניסה לראשונה את הטרנד בחודש שעבר, לאחר שהחלים מניתוח למחיצה סטיה. הניתוח שיפר את נשימת האף שלו, אבל בלילה הוא עדיין שאב אוויר דרך שפתיו. בבקרים, אומר פורד, הוא היה מתעורר עם פה יבש וגרון שרוט.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> פורד העלה את הקלטת הפה במהלך פגישה עם הרופא שלו, שלא חשב שיש נזק בניסיון. באותו ערב, פורד הניח ריבוע קטן של סרט ניתוח על אמצע שפתיו והתיישב במיטה. זו הייתה שנת הלילה הטובה ביותר שהיה לו בזיכרון האחרון, הוא אומר. &quot;כשהתעוררתי, הייתי כמו, &#39;הולי, זה עובד!&#39;&quot;</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> היתרונות של הדבקת הפה הוכרזו עבור כל דבר, החל מרופא שיניים ועד לשינה. אנשים עשויים לסתום את הפה שלהם כדי למנוע חריקת שיניים, ריח רע מהפה, נחירות ודום נשימה בשינה - או אפילו כדי להגביר את הכושר או לקבל לסת חזקה יותר.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> אבל יש <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41415-023-6039-7" target="_blank" rel="noopener">עדיין מעט נתונים שתומכים בטענות כאלה</a> , כתב רופא השיניים ג&#39;ונתן קוויגלי במכתב ב-23 ביוני ב- <em>British Dental Journal.</em> לפני שייעץ למטופלים, קוויגלי, שעובדת במרפאת שיניים באנגליה, רוצה לראות מחקרים נוספים ולהבין טוב יותר את הסיכונים והיתרונות הפוטנציאליים.</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> האם הדבקת הפה יכולה לשפר את השינה של אנשים?</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> כמה ראיות מצביעות על כך שהדבקת הפה עשויה להועיל לסייע בטיפול במחלה אחת לפחות: דום נשימה בשינה. אפילו כאן, המדע דל, והשיטות מגוונות. מרצועה דקה על השפתיים ועד כתם שחור על פני הפה, סוגי הקלטת והטכניקות יכולים להיות שונים בין אנשים, מותגים ומחקרים, מה שמקשה על הסקת מסקנות רחבות.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> למרות שזכה לפופולריות לאחרונה באמצעות המדיה החברתית והספר <em>Breath</em> משנת 2020, הרעיון להשתמש במכשיר כדי לסתום את הפה בזמן השינה הוא לא כל כך חדש. במשך שנים, רופאים השתמשו ברצועות סנטר כדי לעזור לחלק מחולי דום נשימה בשינה לשמור על פיותיהם סגורים במהלך לחץ מתמשך בדרכי הנשימה, או טיפול CPAP, אומרת קרישנה סונדאר, רופאת ריאות ורופאת רפואת שינה המנהלת את מרכז השינה והתעוררות באוניברסיטת יוטה. בסולט לייק סיטי.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> אנשים הסובלים מהמצב עלולים להיתקל בבעיות נשימה בזמן שינה: השרירים נרגעים, הלשון נשמטת לאחור ורקמות רכות בגרון קורסות, וחוסמות את דרכי הנשימה. CPAP הוא הטיפול בסטנדרט הזהב. המכונה מספקת לחץ אוויר באמצעות מסכה המולבשת על הפנים. זה כמו לשאוב צמיג, אומר סונדאר. הפעל אותו, ודרכי הנשימה התקלות מתנפחות. עם זאת, אם מסכות מכסות רק את האף, אוויר יכול לדלוף מהפה. רצועות סנטר יכולות לשמור על הפה סגור ולמנוע דליפת אוויר. אבל הם לא עובדים כל כך טוב ויש אנשים שמוצאים אותם לא בנוח, אומר סונדאר. </p><figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="677" height="450" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/091523_MR_mouth-taping_chin-strap_inline-677x450.jpg" alt="תמונה של גבר לבן שוכב במיטה עם מכונת CPAP קשורה לראשו ומכסה את אפו." class="wp-image-3131598" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/091523_MR_mouth-taping_chin-strap_inline-677x450.jpg 677w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/091523_MR_mouth-taping_chin-strap_inline-576x383.jpg 576w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/091523_MR_mouth-taping_chin-strap_inline-280x186.jpg 280w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/091523_MR_mouth-taping_chin-strap_inline.jpg 680w" sizes="(max-width: 677px) 100vw, 677px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3131598">טיפול אחד לדום נשימה בשינה הוא מכונת CPAP, אשר שואבת אוויר לאף באמצעות מסיכת פנים. רופאים לפעמים משלבים אותו עם רצועת סנטר כדי למנוע מהאוויר לצאת מהפה.</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3131598">Alina555/E+/Getty Images Plus</span></figcaption></figure><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> במחקרי שינה במעבדה שלו, אם אדם שטופל ב-CPAP מוציא אוויר דרך הפה, הצוות של סונדאר ידביק פס זעיר של סרט על השפתיים כדי לשמור אותן סגורות. &quot;נראה שהקלטת העשרה הזו עושה את העבודה טוב יותר מרצועת סנטר גדולה&quot;, הוא אומר. זה הופך את ה-CPAP ליעיל יותר, מה שיכול לעזור לאנשים לישון טוב יותר בלילה. סונדאר מכנה את סרט הפה אחד הכלים בערכות הכלים של הרופאים, אם כי הוא היה רוצה לראות יותר נתונים על מידת היעילות שלו.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> אחת ההשפעות שמומחה לרפואת שינה אנדרו וולמן שם לב היא שעם השפתיים של אנשים צמודות זו לזו, אוויר שנשאב לתוך האף שלהם זורם לפעמים אל הפה ונופח את הלחיים. &quot;הם נראים כאילו הם נושפים לתוך סקסופון&quot;, אומר וולמן, מבית הספר לרפואה בהרווארד ובית החולים בריגהם אנד נשים בבוסטון. מדענים אחרים הבחינו גם<a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC9992075/#CR16" target="_blank" rel="noopener">בתופעת &quot;נפיחת הפה&quot;</a> הזו, אם כי הצוות של וולמן עדיין לא יודע כיצד היא משפיעה על דום נשימה בשינה. זה לא מסוכן, הוא אומר, אבל זה עלול להעיר אותך.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> הוא ועמיתיו שילבו את הקלטת הפה לא רק עם CPAP, אלא גם עם מכשיר לקידום הלסת התחתונה לטיפול בהפרעה. המכשיר מחליק לתוך הפה כמו מגן פה ודוחף את הלסת התחתונה קדימה, מושך את הלשון מהחלק האחורי של הגרון. אבל המכשיר יכול לגרום לאנשים לנשום דרך הפה, מה שעלול להפוך את הטיפול לפחות יעיל, אומר וולמן.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <a href="https://www.atsjournals.org/doi/10.1513/AnnalsATS.202109-1050OC?url_ver=Z39.88-2003&amp;rfr_id=ori:rid:crossref.org&amp;rfr_dat=cr_pub%20%200pubmed" target="_blank" rel="noopener">במחקר שנערך על 21 אנשים עם דום נשימה בשינה,</a> הצוות של וולמן כיסה את שפתי המשתתפים ברצועות דביקות שקופות מתוצרת SomniFix, חברת ייצור במרילנד שתמכה בעבודה. שילוב הרצועות עם המכשיר דמוי מגן הפה הציע שיפור לעומת המכשיר בלבד, והפחית את מספר הפעמים שאנשים הפסיקו לנשום בשעה, דיווח הצוות של וולמן בשנת 2022. זה היה &quot;שיפור קטן&quot;, הוא מציין. &quot;אנחנו צריכים מחקר גדול יותר.&quot;</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> יש צורך בניסויים גדולים יותר כדי לבדוק את יעילות הדבקת הפה</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> זה נראה כמכנה משותף של מחקר הקלטת הפה עד כה. הכל מחקרים ראשוניים קטנים, אומר וולמן. &quot;אין לנו את הניסויים הקליניים הגדולים... זה מה שחסר.&quot;</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> מחקר משנת 2015 מצא שרק <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/25450408/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">טלאי נקבובי על הפה לבדו עזר לטפל בדום נשימה קל בשינה ובנחירות</a> . <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC9498537/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">ומחקר בשנה שעברה על קלטת מסוג אחר</a> דיווח על משהו דומה. אבל המחקרים האלה היו זעירים, עם 30 משתתפים בלבד או פחות. היעדר נתונים מניסויים גדולים יותר פירושו שדעתם של מומחים על הקלטת הפה עשויה להיות על כל המפה, אומר וולמן. &quot;כשאתה שואל רופא על זה, אתה הולך לקבל כל תשובות שונות,&quot; הוא אומר.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> מומחה האוזניים, האף והגרון אריך וויגט, למשל, אינו משוכנע שהקלטת הפה מועילה - או אפילו בטוחה. הטרנד &quot;בהחלט מעלה כמה דגלים אדומים&quot;, אומר Voigt, מ-NYU Langone Health. הוא חושש שאנשים עלולים לעכב את הנשימה שלהם או לשאוף בטעות את הסרט ולהיחנק, אם כי עדיין לא מחקרים גדולים עקבו אחר זה.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> הדבקת פה עשויה להיות כדאית בתרחיש הנכון, אומר Voigt, אבל הוא ממליץ על גישה זהירה לכל מי שמנסה אופנה בריאותית חדשה מ-TikTok. &quot;זה כנראה רעיון טוב [לאנשים] לדבר על זה עם הרופא שלהם לפני שהם עושים את זה בעצמם.&quot;</p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/091523_MR_mouth-taping_man-sleeping_feature-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="99306" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/091523_MR_mouth-taping_man-sleeping_feature-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title> כיצד שתלי מוח מטפלים בדיכאון</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/brain-implant-depression-electrode-stimulation-surgery<dc:creator><![CDATA[Laura Sanders]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Thu, 21 Sep 2023 13:37:04 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Health & Medicine]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3131233 </guid><description><![CDATA[This six-part series follows people whose lives have been changed by an experimental treatment called deep brain stimulation.]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<div class="wp-block-sciencenews-content-sidebar"><div class="wp-block-image is-style-rounded has-alignleft" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><figure class="mobile-wrap alignleft size-thumbnail is-resized"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-186x186.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-3131518" width="93" height="93" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-186x186.jpg 186w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-383x383.jpg 383w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-450x450.jpg 450w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-768x768.jpg 768w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-580x580.jpg 580w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-776x776.jpg 776w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-214x214.jpg 214w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square.jpg 1080w" sizes="(max-width: 93px) 100vw, 93px" /></figure></div><h3 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> חשמל הציל את המוח שלי</h3><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <em>זהו החלק הראשון בסדרה על גירוי מוחי עמוק לדיכאון.</em></p></div><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <em>[אזהרת תוכן: הסיפור הזה מכיל דיון על התאבדות.]</em></p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> ביום ראשון חם ושטוף אחר הצהריים במנהטן, הזמן קפא לג&#39;ון נלסון. הוא עמד על המדרכה ונפרד משלושת ילדיו, שסבא שלהם הגיע לעיר מלונג איילנד כדי לאסוף אותם.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> כמו כל הורה, ג&#39;ון מכוון עמוקות למוזרויות של ילדיו. המבוגר שלו? לפעמים שקט אבל מצחיק עד ביס. הילד האמצעי שלו? מדרג את אבא ב-10 מתוך 10 בסולם המבוכה ואינו זקוק לחיבוק. בנו בן ה-10, תינוק המשפחה, הוא הרגשי. &quot;הבן הצעיר שלי היה מטפס בחזרה אל הרחם של אשתי אם היה יכול&quot;, אומר ג&#39;ון. &quot;הוא הילד הזה.&quot;</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> מצעד בלתי צפוי גרר את התנועה, אז ג&#39;ון חנה באופן לא חוקי לאורך שפת מדרכה צהובה ברחוב 36, ליד המקום שבו חיכה חמו. הגיע הזמן ללכת. הצעיר שלו נתן את החיבוק האחרון. &quot;הוא הרים את מבטו, מפוחד ועצוב,&quot; אומר ג&#39;ון, ושאל, &quot;אבא, אני הולך לראות אותך שוב?&quot;</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> השאלה הזאת עצרה את השעון. &quot;הייתי כמו, &#39;אוי גבר&#39;,&quot; אומר ג&#39;ון. &quot;זה היה אחד מהרגעים האלה שבהם חייתי את זה דרך העיניים שלו. ואני נבהלתי בפעם הראשונה&quot;.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> עד אותה פרידה, ג&#39;ון לא רצה לחיות. במשך שנים, הייתה לו כמיהה מתמדת למות - הוא מדבר על זה כאילו זו הייתה התמכרות - בעודו נלחם בדיכאון עמוק ומתיש. אבל השאלה של בנו פילחה את הכובד הזה והגיעה למשהו בתוכו. &quot;זו הייתה הפעם הראשונה שחשבתי על זה באמת. הייתי כמו, &#39;אני קצת מקווה שאני לא אמות&#39;. כל כך הרבה זמן לא הייתה לי התחושה הזו&quot;.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> החיבוק הזה קרה בסביבות השעה 17:00 ב-21 באוגוסט 2022. 12 שעות לאחר מכן, ג&#39;ון הוכנס לחדר ניתוח.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> שם, בבית החולים של הר סיני, ממש דרומית מערבית לסנטרל פארק, חברי צוות הניתוח הדביקו את ראשו של ג&#39;ון לתוך מסגרת כדי להחזיק אותו בשקט. אחר כך הרדימו אותו וקדח שני חורים קטנים בחלק העליון של הגולגולת שלו, אחד מכל צד. דרך כל חור, מנתח צלל חוט ארוך ודק מנוקד בקצהו באלקטרודות עמוק לתוך מוחו. החיווט, שהושחל מתחת לעורו, התפתל סביב החלק החיצוני של גולגולתו של ג&#39;ון ושקע מאחורי אוזנו. משם, חוט כרוך בחזית, פוגש תיבת בקרה המופעלת על ידי סוללה שהמנתחים השתילו בחזה שלו, ממש מתחת לעצם הבריח שלו.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> במהלך הניתוח ובימים שאחרי, הרופאים שלחו פולסים קטנים של חשמל למוחו של ג&#39;ון. בדרכים שעדיין לא ברורות, ההתעסקות החשמלית הזו משנה את המסרים הנעים בין אזורי מוח שונים. לרופאים ולחוקרים הייתה מה שנראה כמו מטרה נועזת: הם רצו שהדופקים האלה יוציאו את ג&#39;ון מאפלת הדיכאון.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> ג&#39;ון הוא אחד מעשרות האנשים בארצות הברית הנמצאים כעת בניסויים קליניים שמטרתם לרפא הפרעות נפשיות באמצעות שתלי מוח. הטכניקה נקראת גירוי מוחי עמוק, והיא בנויה על ההנחה המדעית שגירוי חשמלי יכול לאפס מוחות שנמצאים באחיזה של הפרעות פסיכיאטריות חזקות והרסניות <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/chemical-imbalance-explain-depression">כמו דיכאון</a> , הפרעה אובססיבית-קומפולסיבית והפרעת דחק פוסט-טראומטית. </p><figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><iframe loading="lazy" title="ג&#39;ון נלסון רוצה שתדע איך החשמל הציל את מוחו | חדשות המדע" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/SwZWsi1-4eM?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe></div><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> צפו בסרטון של ג&#39;ון המתאר את הדיכאון שלו, הניסיון שלו עם DBS וכיצד הבריאות הנפשית שלו משפיעה על משפחתו.</figcaption></figure><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> הצגת גירוי מוחי עמוק</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> שמעתי לראשונה על גירוי מוחי עמוק, או DBS, לפני יותר מעשור, בשנת 2010. ככתב מדע, ישבתי בחדר ישיבות גדוש במדעני מוח בסן דייגו. הקשבנו למצגת של <a href="https://profiles.mountsinai.org/helen-s-mayberg" target="_blank" rel="noopener">הלן מייברג, נוירולוגית ומדעית מוח</a> שהייתה אז באוניברסיטת אמורי באטלנטה. בזמן שדיברה, מייברג הובילה את הקהל דרך הרציונל המדעי לרעיון שאלקטרודות הנדחפות מטה לתוך המוח יכולות להקל על דיכאון חמור.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> לקראת סוף המצגת שלה, מייברג הציגה סרטון של אישה שסבלה מדיכאון קשה. יום לפני צילום הסרטון, הרופאים השתילו אלקטרודות במוחה של האישה. החוקרים בסרטון הפעילו את הגירוי, ותוך דקה, סתם כך, האישה רצתה לחייך ולצחוק. השינוי הזה ריצף אותי, ואם לשפוט לפי תגובת הקהל, גם הרבה אנשים אחרים.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> בנובמבר 2022, תפסתי את מייברג, שוב בפגישה למדעי המוח, שוב בסן דייגו. דיברנו על מה שקרה בשנים שחלפו מאז אותה מצגת ולאן המחקר הזה הולך. זו לא הייתה דרך קלה, אומר מייברג, שמנהל כעת את המרכז המשפחתי של נאש לטיפול במעגלים מתקדמים בבית הספר לרפואה של איקאן בהר סיני. המדע של DBS לקח הרבה פיתולים.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> כך גם מסעותיהם של אנשים שהשתתפו במחקר זה. כדי לשמוע את אחד מהסיפורים האלה, מייברג יצרה אותי בקשר עם ג&#39;ון.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> לסדרה הזו שוחחתי איתו ועם אשתו, כמו גם שלושה אנשים אחרים שחיו עם דיכאון חמור ומטופלים כעת בגירוי מוחי עמוק. הדרכים של האנשים האלה היו קשות להפליא. ולמרות שהם עדיין מתמודדים עם אתגרים, הם היו ברורים לגבי מה ש-DBS עשתה עבורם: ניתוח המוח הניסיוני הזה החזיר להם את חייהם. </p><figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="680" height="475" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_1_inline.jpg" alt="בדיקת CT של אלקטרודות במוח של אדם" class="wp-image-3131241" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_1_inline.jpg 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_1_inline-548x383.jpg 548w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_1_inline-644x450.jpg 644w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_1_inline-266x186.jpg 266w" sizes="(max-width: 680px) 100vw, 680px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3131241">לגירוי מוחי עמוק, חוטים דקים המכילים אלקטרודות הוכנסו עמוק לתוך מוחו של ג&#39;ון נלסון, שם הם חושבים שהם משנים את הפעילות של מסלולים עצביים.</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3131241">המרכז המשפחתי של נאש לטיפול במעגלים מתקדמים, בית הספר לרפואה איקאן בהר סיני</span></figcaption></figure><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> האפלה של דיכאון</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> ג&#39;ון הוא בחור חד ומצחיק בגיל העמידה, &quot;דמות&quot; המתואר בעצמו, שחי בעיירה קטנה וציורית צפונית מזרחית לפילדלפיה. הוא אבא עם שלושה ילדים עסוקים ומוסך עמוס במקלות הוקי, משטחי לוכד כדור סופט, אלות גולף, כדורים מכל הסוגים, אופניים, גלגיליות מקוונות, גול רשת וקטנוע לבן וסופר חמוד. הוא מאמן (הוקי וסופטבול) הידוע בכך שהוא מחלק &quot;איזמים&quot; ובמשפט, &quot;אני אתן לך עצה לחיים&quot;. הוא בעל שדואג שאשתו תעשה יותר מדי ולא תדאג לעצמה. הוא בפרסום, אדם שנהג לאהוב את החברים שלו להסתובב סביב בור האש שלו.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> במשך עשור, ג&#39;ון נתן לאישיות היוצאת שלו לשאת אותו בעודו נאבק להתגבר על הדיכאון שלו. מחלתו, והמחשבות האובדניות שהיא כפתה עליו, החמירו בחמש השנים האחרונות. כלפי חוץ, ג&#39;ון היה הבחור ההיפר-חברתי ובעל תפקוד גבוה שכולם ציפו ממנו להיות. אבל בפנים, הדיכאון העמוק שלו היה גיהנום פרטי, הוא אומר. &quot;אני אהיה זה שעומד מול כולם מוביל טוסט שמפניה, ואז אסע הביתה ורוצה לטרוק את המכונית שלי בעץ.&quot;</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> ג&#39;ון פינטז על מקרי מוות אחרים: שוד, התרסקות מטוס. עד שבנו של ג&#39;ון שאל אם יראה את ג&#39;ון שוב, בערב שלפני ההליך, ג&#39;ון אפילו טיפח מעט תקווה שהוא עלול למות במהלך ניתוח המוח שאליו התנדב.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> הדיכאון של ג&#39;ון גם גנב את המוטיבציה שלו, והותיר אותו סחוט ומבודד ממשפחתו. הוא אכל יותר מדי, ישן יותר מדי ושתה יותר מדי. המתיחה הקשה ביותר שלו, הוא חושד, הותירו את משפחתו בטראומה.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> טיפול בשיחות, תרופות נוגדות דיכאון, תרופות אנטי-פסיכוטיות, קטמין, קנאביס, <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/snap-crackle-and-feel-good">גירוי מגנטי טרנסגולגולתי</a> (בו שדות מגנטיים מכוונים לתאי עצב דרך הגולגולת), מספר נסיונות טיפול בבית מגורים, אפילו טיפול בנזעי חשמל, שהותירו אותו עם אובדן זיכרון אינטנסיבי - אף אחד מהטיפולים הללו לא עבד בצורה מהימנה בשבילו.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> לפי הערכות, כ-280 מיליון אנשים ברחבי העולם סובלים מדיכאון גדול. תת-קבוצה של המספר הענק הזה תיפול בסופו של דבר לאבחנה חסרת תקווה: &quot;דיכאון עמיד לטיפול&quot; או &quot;דיכאון בלתי פתיר&quot;. בארצות הברית, על פי ההערכות 2.8 מיליון אנשים סובלים מאבחון זה.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> ג&#39;ון הוא אחד מהם. עבורו ועבור משפחתו, גירוי מוחי עמוק היה תמרון אחרון ונואש. זה היה שלום מרי שלו.</p><hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" /><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <em>אם אתה או מישהו שאתה מכיר מתמודד עם משבר אובדני או מצוקה רגשית, התקשר או שלח הודעת טקסט לקו 988 התאבדות ומשבר בטלפון 988.</em></p><hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" /><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <em>המאמר הבא בסדרה <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/depression-treatment-resistant-help-dbs">עוקב אחר חיפושיו של ג&#39;ון להקלה</a> מהמחלה שהוא מתאר כ&quot;רעל בכל חלק בגוף שלי&quot;.</em></p><p class="has-gray-light-background-color has-background" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <em>סדרה זו התאפשרה במימון מקרן אלפרד פ. סלואן.</em></p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_1_feat-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="115115" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_1_feat-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title> טיפולי הדיכאון של היום לא עוזרים לכולם</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/depression-treatment-resistant-help-dbs<dc:creator><![CDATA[Laura Sanders]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Thu, 21 Sep 2023 13:36:38 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Neuroscience]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3131317 </guid><description><![CDATA[In the second story in the series, deep brain stimulation is a last resort for some people with depression.]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<div class="wp-block-sciencenews-content-sidebar"><div class="wp-block-image is-style-rounded has-alignleft" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><figure class="mobile-wrap alignleft size-thumbnail is-resized"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-186x186.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-3131518" width="93" height="93" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-186x186.jpg 186w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-383x383.jpg 383w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-450x450.jpg 450w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-768x768.jpg 768w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-580x580.jpg 580w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-776x776.jpg 776w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-214x214.jpg 214w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square.jpg 1080w" sizes="(max-width: 93px) 100vw, 93px" /></figure></div><h3 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> חשמל הציל את המוח שלי</h3><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <em>זהו החלק השני בסדרה על גירוי מוחי עמוק לדיכאון. <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/brain-implant-depression-electrode-stimulation-surgery">קרא מההתחלה</a> .</em></p></div><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <em>[הערת תוכן: הסיפור הזה מכיל דיון על התאבדות.]</em></p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> הדיכאון של ג&#39;ון נלסון היה רעל. &quot;היה לי רעל בכל חלק בגוף שלי. זה ממש רץ בכל תא בגוף שלי. הדם שלי נשא את הרעל, והוא ריסק בי הכל&quot;.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> מלנכוליה, אחד השמות המוקדמים של דיכאון, מקורה במילה היוונית העתיקה ל&quot;מרה שחורה&quot;, נוזל חולה שנחשד כמציף גוף. פעם חשבו שהקזת דם ודרכים אחרות לשחרר את הנוזלים המשחיתים יכולים להקל על דעתם של אנשים.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> כיום, לרופאים יש אפשרויות הרבה יותר טובות לטיפול בדיכאון. תרופות נוגדות דיכאון וטיפול בשיחות יכולים להיות יעילים עבור אנשים רבים. אבל האפשרויות האלה לא עוזרות לכולם.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> לג&#39;ון יש דיכאון עמיד לטיפול. כך גם אמנדה, מעצבת אפליקציות ואתרים ואמנית בשנות ה-30 לחייה שמתגוררת בניו יורק. אמנדה יכולה גם לטרטר שורה ארוכה של טיפולים שניסתה לדיכאון העמוק שחשה מאז שהייתה בת 13. היא קיבלה 21 תרופות נוגדות דיכאון שונות. המוח שלה נדחף עם מגנטים רבי עוצמה בטיפול שנקרא גירוי מגנטי טרנסגולגולתי. היא קיבלה עירוי IV של <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/ketamine-new-nerve-cell-connections-mice-depression">קטמין</a> . </p><div class="wp-block-image  has-alignleft" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><figure class="alignleft size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="450" height="450" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_2_inline-1-450x450.jpg" alt="תמונה של קריקטורה אמנדה מתחת לערימה של בקבוקי תרופות עם מספרים עליהם." class="wp-image-3131335" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_2_inline-1-450x450.jpg 450w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_2_inline-1-383x383.jpg 383w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_2_inline-1-186x186.jpg 186w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_2_inline-1-580x580.jpg 580w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_2_inline-1-214x214.jpg 214w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_2_inline-1.jpg 680w" sizes="(max-width: 450px) 100vw, 450px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3131335">אמנדה ניסתה מגוון עצום של טיפולים, כולל 21 סוגים של תרופות, לדיכאון החמור שלה. האמנות שלה, כולל תיאורים של &quot;קריקטורה אמנדה&quot;, הפכה לבריחה.</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3131335">באדיבות אמנדה</span></figcaption></figure></div><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> אמנדה, שכדי להגן על פרטיותה ביקשה לא להשתמש בשם משפחתה, עברה גם 40 סבבים של טיפול בנזעי חשמל, או ECT. טיפול &quot;סטנדרט הזהב&quot; עבור אנשים שאינם נעזרים בטיפולים אחרים, ECT נעשה לעתים קרובות מספר פעמים בשבוע במשך שלושה או ארבעה שבועות. מסיבות לא ידועות, המיני-התקפים שנוצרו במוח יכולים לפעמים לספק הקלה.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> &quot;הטיפול בנזעי חשמל עזר מעט&quot;, אומרת אמנדה. &quot;אבל כדי שזה יעזור, הייתי צריך לעשות את זה לעתים קרובות כל כך עד שנגרם לי נזק לזיכרון. הייתי כמו, &#39;וואו, וואו, וואו, אני לא זוכר איפה מגירת הגרביים שלי. אני לא זוכר אילו תחנות רכבת תחתית נמצאות ליד הדירה שלי. אני לא זוכרת איך משתמשים בתוכנה שאני משתמשת בה כבר 10 שנים&#39;&quot;, אמרה לי. &quot;אני חייב להפסיק.&quot;</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> הדיכאון של ג&#39;ון היה רעל; של אמנדה הייתה מערבולת. וכאשר ECT כבר לא הייתה אופציה, המערבולת הזו כמעט כילתה אותה. לאחר ניסיון התאבדות, היא בילתה שישה שבועות בבית החולים ולאחר מכן שישה שבועות נוספים קיבלה טיפול חוץ. &quot;בשלב הזה [רופאים] אמרו, &#39;אין שום דבר אחר שאנחנו יכולים לעשות בשבילך. ניסית ממש כל מה שיש בחוץ. אם ECT לא עובד, זה הכל&#39;&quot;, אומרת אמנדה.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> כמו עם ג&#39;ון ואחרים שדיברתי איתם, הרופאים שלה התייאשו, אומרת אמנדה. &quot;כשאתה מגיע למקום שבו אומרים שאין שום דבר אחר שאנחנו יכולים לעשות עבורך, ובכל זאת אתה צריך להמשיך לחיות את חייך, זה מקום שקשה להגיע אליו.&quot;</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> התקווה האחרונה</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> נואשת לעזרה, אמנדה התקשרה <a href="https://www.mountsinai.org/care/psychiatry/services/depression-anxiety-disorders/trd-program" target="_blank" rel="noopener">לתוכנית דיכאון עמיד לטיפול בהר סיני</a> . לאחר שתיארה את כל הטיפולים הלא מוצלחים שלה, אמנדה הועברה שוב לרופאים שונים. &quot;הם החליטו שבאמת ניסית הכל&quot;, היא אומרת.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> המסר האחרון הוא מה שהעביר את אמנדה לתוכנית המחקר של DBS. כשמרטין פיגי, פסיכיאטר וחוקר DBS בבית הספר לרפואה איקאן בהר סיני, הסביר את ההליך, המחקר והסיכונים, אמנדה הקשיבה היטב. היא הגיעה לפגישות מוכנה עם רשימה של שמונה עמודים של שאלות שכיסו את השאלות המעשיות (&quot;ממה עלי להימנע לנצח ברגע שיש לי את זה? ריצה? תליית ראש הפוך? טרמפולינות?&quot;) והעמוקה (&quot;מה עושה אדם רוצה להיות בחיים?&quot;). לשאלות שקיבלו מענה ומידע מלא, אמנדה הסכימה לעבור ניתוח DBS.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> תוכנית DBS שאמנדה וג&#39;ון הם חלק ממנה נראית שונה בתכלית מאיטרציות קודמות. בשנת 2008, הנוירולוגית הלן מייברג ועמיתים רבים ברחבי הארץ החלו זה עתה בניסוי קליני DBS כפול סמיות גדול כדי לבדוק את הטכניקה. המחקר, שנקרא משפט Broaden, עקב אחרי אנשים עם דיכאון, שלחלקם היה גירוי חשמלי ואחרים שהושתלו להם אלקטרודות אך הגירוי כבוי.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> בסך הכל, ל-90 אנשים עם דיכאון חמור הושתלו בניסוי מכשירים לגירוי מוח. אבל בשנת 2013, הבדיקות הופסקו מוקדם בגלל תוצאות גרועות מהצפוי. נותנת החסות והיצרנית של מכשיר ה-DBS, St. Jude Medical Inc., קבעה שהניסוי לא צפוי להגיע למטרותיו. יחד עם עוד ניסוי לא מוצלח, שכלל 30 אנשים שקיבלו גירוי בחלק אחר של המוח, התוצאות החסרות הללו ייצגו כישלון אמיתי עבור DBS כטיפול בדיכאון.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> הממצאים המאכזבים הללו עוררו ביקורות על השיטה, שהודגשו בסיפורים של אנשים שחוו חוויות שליליות עם DBS. וניגודי עניינים פוטנציאליים קיימים, כפי שהם קיימים לטיפולים רפואיים רבים התלויים בחברות מכשור רפואי. מייברג, למשל, מקבל עמלות עבור ייעוץ ורישוי קניין רוחני ממעבדות אבוט, החברה שקנתה את סנט ג&#39;וד מדיקל.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> למרות כישלונות וביקורת, המחקר לא נעצר; זה התבגר. שיטות הדמיית המוח השתפרו, ומאפשרות לחוקרים לראות בדיוק אילו כבישים מהירים של סיבי חומר לבן, צרורות שליחת מסרים הנובעים מתאי עצב, מושפעים מהאלקטרודות. היבטים אחרים של טיפול, כולל מפגשי מעקב עם מומחים ומטפלים בבריאות הנפש, התפתחו. בניסוי קטן של 11 אנשים עם דיכאון חמור, למשל, <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/28397839/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">התסמינים שלהם השתפרו</a> , דיווחו חוקרים בשנת 2018. ו-DBS כטיפול בדיכאון הצליח להשאיל הרבה מהתקדמות בטיפול בהפרעות אחרות. </p><figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><iframe loading="lazy" title="&quot;ניסיתי 21 תרופות נוגדות דיכאון לפני גירוי מוחי עמוק&quot; | חדשות המדע" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/qc1v35kgJPs?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe></div><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> צפו בסרטון של אמנדה המתארת ​​כיצד היא משתמשת באמנות כדי לעבד את החוויה שלה עם דיכאון עז ו-DBS.</figcaption></figure><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> עד כמה DBS נפוצה?</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> בעולם, אלקטרודות DBS הושתלו בכ-230,000 מוחות של אנשים. DBS אושרה על ידי מינהל המזון והתרופות האמריקאי בשנת 1997 לטיפול ברעד, ובשנת 2002 לטיפול במחלת פרקינסון. DBS משמש גם על ידי רופאים למקרים חמורים של אפילפסיה, הפרעה אובססיבית-קומפולסיבית ודיסטוניה, או התכווצויות שרירים לא רצוניות.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> טווח ההגעה של DBS מתרחב במהירות. בניסויים ניסיוניים קטנים יותר הושתלו לאנשים אלקטרודות לכאב, הפרעות אכילה, התמכרות, פציעות מוח טראומטיות והפרעת דחק פוסט טראומטית. חוקרים עובדים על מערכות גירוי כדי להחזיר תנועה לאנשים משותקים ודיבור לאנשים שאינם מסוגלים לדבר.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Jon heard about the procedure in 2021. He called the Mount Sinai program from a residential treatment facility, only to learn that he didn&#39;t qualify because, at the time, he hadn&#39;t yet tried ECT. So he did 12 rounds of the therapy in early 2022. ECT helps many people. But it didn&#39;t help Jon, and the experience shook him. “It was horrific. Zero relief. My memory loss is still pervasive to this day,” he says. It was utter misery, but he qualified for the DBS trial.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> And with that, Jon&#39;s surgery date was set: August 22, 2022.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> In the run-up to the surgery, Jon&#39;s wife, Barbara, worried about both the surgery and the outcome. “What if they slip or they sneeze and they ruin his brain?” she recalls wondering. “What if it doesn&#39;t work? What do we do next? This was so much like the last resort that if it didn&#39;t work, then we were going to be looking at potentially years more of trying.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> She adds, “And there&#39;s no option of giving up.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Even so, Barbara didn&#39;t fully believe the surgery was going to happen until it was right around the corner. “I think my brain just did not catch up to the reality of it until we were very close to the actual surgery,” she told me. “A couple of days before, I was like, &#39;Oh I&#39;m a mess.&#39; I do weird things when I&#39;m really that stressed out, rearranging furniture, doing things that seem to take too much energy.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Jon, however, was not worried. “I didn&#39;t care that I was having my head cut open,” he says. “I had the same level of anxiety that you would have if you were getting your teeth cleaned.”</p><hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" /><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <em>If you or someone you know is facing a suicidal crisis or emotional distress, call or text the 988 Suicide &amp; Crisis Lifeline at 988.</em></p><hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" /><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <em>In the next article in the series,<a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/brain-implant-depression-electrode-stimulation-target">read about Jon&#39;s surgery and the big changes that followed for him and his family</a> .</em></p><p class="has-gray-light-background-color has-background" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <em>This series was made possible with funding from the Alfred P. Sloan Foundation.</em></p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_2_feat-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="214528" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_2_feat-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title> The science behind deep brain stimulation for depression</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/brain-implant-depression-electrode-stimulation-target<dc:creator><![CDATA[Laura Sanders]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Thu, 21 Sep 2023 13:35:35 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Health & Medicine]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3131347 </guid><description><![CDATA[The third part of the series explores the promising brain areas to target for deep brain stimulation for depression. ]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<div class="wp-block-sciencenews-content-sidebar"><div class="wp-block-image is-style-rounded has-alignleft" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><figure class="mobile-wrap alignleft size-thumbnail is-resized"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-186x186.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-3131518" width="93" height="93" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-186x186.jpg 186w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-383x383.jpg 383w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-450x450.jpg 450w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-768x768.jpg 768w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-580x580.jpg 580w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-776x776.jpg 776w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-214x214.jpg 214w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square.jpg 1080w" sizes="(max-width: 93px) 100vw, 93px" /></figure></div><h3 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Electricity Saved My Brain</h3><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <em>This is the third part in a series on deep brain stimulation for depression. <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/brain-implant-depression-electrode-stimulation-surgery">Read from the beginning</a> .</em></p></div><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Early in the morning on August 22, 2022, Jon&#39;s medical team told him that neurologist Helen Mayberg would check in with him just before his deep brain stimulation surgery. “Everybody is like, &#39;Dr. Mayberg is going to come in and give you a pumped-up speech.&#39;” She&#39;d explain how everything ought to go and what the team needed from Jon. She didn&#39;t disappoint, Jon says. “She came in and gave me the pep talk: &#39;All I need you to do is to be present,&#39;” she told him. “She was really adamant about that.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> In the middle of the surgery, the medical team woke Jon up from anesthesia. It was a hazy time, but Jon remembers it. “I&#39;m so awake, and I was so myself,” he recalls. “Dr. Mayberg is right in your face right away, and she&#39;s like, &#39;Jon, it&#39;s Dr. Mayberg and Dr. Figee.&#39; And I said, &#39;Doc, I need to tell you something.&#39; And she was so concerned, like, &#39;Yes, yes, yes?&#39; And I was like, &#39;I&#39;m present!&#39;</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “I&#39;m just busting her chops, and she&#39;s sitting there laughing. But that&#39;s how completely normal you are.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The day after surgery, Jon sat with Mayberg and another clinician as they began to turn on and off electrodes, searching for the pattern of stimulation that would influence nerve cells in the right way and in the right spot. Each time, Mayberg would ask him two key questions: Did he feel like walking his dog? And did he want to have friends over to sit around his fire pit? Jon&#39;s wife, Barbara, his dad and a crowd of doctors and researchers watched a video feed of this process from an overflow room.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> After trying a series of stimulation patterns and getting “yes” to their questions, the researchers settled on an electrical pattern, and Jon went home to Pennsylvania. “The next day, bandaged up on my head, I not only took the dog on a walk, I asked my son and my wife to come with me. I enjoyed the walk. I enjoyed the conversation. I enjoyed coming back home. I sat outside and had coffee. It&#39;s just surreal.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> As we talk, about six months after his surgery, Jon has no doubt about the outcome: “Instantaneously overnight I was healed,” he says. “I have been in remission from depression since the moment they turned that on.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Barbara, Jon&#39;s wife, has seen the shift from the outside. His motivation is back, she says. He&#39;s not as fidgety as he was. He&#39;s easier to talk to. He cooks elaborate dinners for the family. He even looks different. When he is sick, Jon has a clammy, pale, almost puffy look to him, Barbara says. “I haven&#39;t seen that look in six months, which is amazing,” she says. “He just looks healthier.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “He has the old Jon voice back. He annoys me more,” she says. “He&#39;s a super high-energy, outgoing person, and I&#39;m the quiet, withdrawn person who needs more time alone. I&#39;m like, &#39;Oh my God, would you just stop talking?&#39; That&#39;s a good thing, though, that&#39;s a good thing, because for a long time, he didn&#39;t want to talk at all.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> When Barbara and Jon got together in their early 20s, she thought Jon was the happiest and nicest person she had ever met. Now, “the person I met 20-something years ago is back,” she says. “I feel like he was lost for a long time.” </p><figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="680" height="492" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_3_inline.jpg" alt="Barbara hugs Jon Nelson in photo from early in their relationship." class="wp-image-3131439" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_3_inline.jpg 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_3_inline-529x383.jpg 529w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_3_inline-622x450.jpg 622w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_3_inline-257x186.jpg 257w" sizes="(max-width: 680px) 100vw, 680px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3131439">Barbara and Jon Nelson are shown here in the first picture they took together. Barbara says Jon&#39;s depression “probably shaped so much of who I am and how I am now in so many ways.”</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3131439">Courtesy of J. Nelson</span></figcaption></figure><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Changes after DBS</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Jon has no shortage of words to describe his recovery.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Amanda, the artist in New York City, who had DBS surgery on October 20, 2022, has trouble describing the immediate change. “Maybe it was like a little spark of energy. I was more chatty. It was easier to talk to people, just because it felt like there was a little something inside pushing.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Like Jon, her recovery has been incredibly fast. “I left the hospital on a Friday,” Amanda recalls. “By Sunday, I could tell it was working. By Wednesday … that&#39;s when I got completely better.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “I can&#39;t even describe the relief. I&#39;ve never felt relief so profound in my life,” she says. “You get used to living in pain. And when the pain is all of a sudden gone, you&#39;re like, &#39;What is this?&#39;”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Part of her life now includes what she calls “weird experiences” — taking pleasure in things. Candles, for instance. “I never enjoyed smells before. And now I have these candles, and they smell so good. Candles never smelled good before.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> A similar sentiment comes from Emily Hollenbeck, who also lives in New York City and had DBS surgery in 2021, about a year and a half before I spoke with her. When a certain pattern of brain stimulation was turned on during the surgery, she started to think about bacon. “I was tasting the bacon in my mind. I could taste that salt and the fat and the crispiness. I started to feel that sense of hunger.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Her depression had taken away any anticipation of upcoming pleasure. “My mouth won&#39;t water,” she says. “I won&#39;t really think about it.” With the stimulation, the contrast between disinterest and intense craving was “so immediate and so strong,” she says. “That&#39;s why it struck me.” In the days after the surgery, she also noticed she began to feel restless, like she wanted to go to the library. “I had these impulses to move, to do things, to enjoy things,” she says.</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> What brain areas does DBS hit?</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Jon, Amanda and Emily have been receiving constant brain stimulation targeted to a brain area called the subcallosal cingulate, or SCC. That&#39;s the same area that was targeted in the Broaden clinical trial, which was stopped prematurely because of poor early results.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> So, what&#39;s different now?</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Since Broaden, and armed with better brain-imaging techniques, scientists have learned a lot more about the SCC and how it connects to other parts of the brain. The area is not a uniform glob of brain tissue; it holds a confluence of diverse white matter tracts, nerve bundles that speed information to and fro.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> A recent presentation from Mayberg&#39;s research group described the outcomes of about 50 patients from the Broaden trial, people who continued to be stimulated and monitored after the trial officially ended. It turns out that the people who got better had their electrodes implanted in a fortuitous spot in the SCC, one that hit four key white matter tracts. “It was really about targeting,” Mayberg says.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The SCC — and the signals it sends to other brain areas — seems to have a role in generating negative emotions, immobility, cognitive sluggishness and heavy physical feelings. Stimulating there, researchers suspect, can overwhelm those nerve cells, tiring them out and making them effectively fall silent. That silence then has ripple effects at many different levels, from single cells to entire cohorts of brain areas. Those changes, the thinking goes, somehow turn down the negative malaise.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> It&#39;s a bit like taking off the parking brake, allowing energy and motivation to flow once more. This aspect of the SCC&#39;s job may explain why Jon went for a walk in the hospital halls and at home with his family, why Amanda felt a spark of energy and why Emily had an itch to get up and go to the library. </p><figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="680" height="282" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_4_inline-1-1.jpg" alt="Side-by-side brain scans with electrodes marked by a blue line and red dot and white matter tracks visible in yellow on the left and in green on the right." class="wp-image-3131441" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_4_inline-1-1.jpg 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_4_inline-1-1-330x137.jpg 330w" sizes="(max-width: 680px) 100vw, 680px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3131441">Deep brain stimulation for depression changes signals near the electrodes (red) and signals moving along brain fibers called white matter tracts (yellow and green). The subcallosal cingulum (left) and the ventral capsule/ventral striatum (right) are two current targets.</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3131441">SA Sheth and HS Mayberg/ <em>Annual Review of Neuroscience</em> 2023</span></figcaption></figure><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> But Mayberg and her colleagues at Mount Sinai aren&#39;t the only people conducting trials on DBS for depression, nor is their target the only one under consideration. Another promising target, called the ventral capsule/ventral striatum, or VC/VS, is more involved in feelings of reward. Stimulating there may be turning up the positive as opposed to dialing down the negative. Its connections to other brain regions are extensive, perhaps even more numerous than the SCC&#39;s.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Some of the big questions, says Sameer Sheth, a neurosurgeon and DBS researcher at Baylor College of Medicine in Houston, are about personalizing the technique: Which patients would benefit from which target in the brain and what type of stimulation? The SCC and the VC/VS both seem promising. In a way, the debate mirrors a similar one in DBS for Parkinson&#39;s disease, where several brain structures are possible targets. To determine where electrodes should be implanted, doctors now consider factors like how advanced the disease is, whether a patient needs to reduce their medication and if tremor is the main problem.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> To better understand the neural circuits related to mood, Sheth and his colleagues are conducting a clinical trial for depression that is using implanted electrodes to listen in on many parts of the brain. The study is designed, in part, to uncover how various types of stimulation, pointed toward various neural spots, affect the brain. Eventually, the team hopes, this knowledge could lead to personalized stimulation — bespoke electrical patterns tailored to each person. (Sheth has received consulting fees from various medical companies, including Boston Scientific and NeuroPace, and cofounded a neurotechnology company.)</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> I talked with one of the people in this trial, a man who wanted to remain anonymous. He was the first person to undergo this massive brain eavesdropping effort by Sheth and colleagues. As such, he became Patient 001, a designation he grew fond of, he says. He traveled to Houston from New York City, where he was living at the time, and was scheduled for surgery on March 9, 2020. His surgery squeaked through, just days before all nonemergency surgeries were canceled in the area because of the growing COVID pandemic.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> During surgery at Baylor St. Luke&#39;s Medical Center in Houston, Patient 001 was implanted with four electrode wires, two in the SCC and two in the VC/VS. He got 10 extra electrodes, too, implanted in areas connected to the SCC and VC/VS. These extras were temporary, there only to listen to his brain activity over a 10-day stay in the hospital. “I&#39;m not going to say the 10-day stay in the hospital was a walk in the park, because it wasn&#39;t,” he says. “But when you have nothing to lose and you&#39;re in hell, you&#39;ll do anything.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Like Jon, Patient 001 went through a similar testing phase with his electrodes. At one point, he felt something big. “I said, &#39;I don&#39;t know what you did, but it feels like I&#39;m online again. I&#39;m online.&#39; If you think of your brain as a computer, it felt like I had a virus, and then my hard drive crashed. And all of a sudden — boom. They control all the leads, and they reboot you, and you&#39;re OK again. I remember the doctor and the people in the OR literally laughing, like, &#39;That&#39;s a new one.&#39;</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “We laugh about it, but it came out of my heart,” he says. “It&#39;s how I felt.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> These stories all sound remarkable, and in all sorts of ways, they truly are. The four people with depression I&#39;ve told you about were pulled out of deep suffering and restored to themselves — for now, and for what Jon and the researchers expect will be a very long time.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> But like any story, this one has its moments of despair.</p><hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" /><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <em>In the next article in the series, <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/dbs-deep-brain-stimulation-depression">find out why the road to recovery is not always smooth</a> .</em></p><p class="has-gray-light-background-color has-background" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <em>This series was made possible with funding from the Alfred P. Sloan Foundation.</em></p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_3_feat-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="175210" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_3_feat-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title> What&#39;s it like to live with deep brain stimulation for depression?</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/dbs-deep-brain-stimulation-depression<dc:creator><![CDATA[Laura Sanders]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Thu, 21 Sep 2023 13:35:00 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Neuroscience]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3131393 </guid><description><![CDATA[The fourth article in the series explores the physical and emotional challenges of experimental brain implants for depression.]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<div class="wp-block-sciencenews-content-sidebar"><div class="wp-block-image is-style-rounded has-alignleft" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><figure class="mobile-wrap alignleft size-thumbnail is-resized"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-186x186.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-3131518" width="93" height="93" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-186x186.jpg 186w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-383x383.jpg 383w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-450x450.jpg 450w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-768x768.jpg 768w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-580x580.jpg 580w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-776x776.jpg 776w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-214x214.jpg 214w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square.jpg 1080w" sizes="(max-width: 93px) 100vw, 93px" /></figure></div><h3 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Electricity Saved My Brain</h3><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <em>This is the fourth part in a series on deep brain stimulation for depression. <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/brain-implant-depression-electrode-stimulation-surgery">Read from the beginning</a> .</em></p></div><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <em>[Content note: This story contains discussion of suicide.]</em></p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “The only thing I&#39;ll slightly complain about — and it&#39;s very vain — I only wish the batteries in your chest didn&#39;t show up so much,” says Patient 001.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> There is an intense physicality to deep brain stimulation for depression. Participants have two slight bumps on their head, wires under the skin of their neck and a battery-powered control unit implanted under the skin in their chest.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Because he was implanted with two sets of electrodes, Patient 001 has two battery packs, one on each side of his upper chest. He lives in a hot place near the ocean. “It just sucks I can&#39;t take my shirt off at the beach and not be self-conscious about that.” Sometimes the devices in his chest feel alien to him when he&#39;s going to sleep. “I put my hand on it to be comfortable,” he says.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Amanda has a strained relationship with the device, too. “I don&#39;t like the idea of it. I don&#39;t like how it feels. Every time I accidentally touch the wire in my neck, I&#39;m like, &#39;Ugh, ugh, I don&#39;t like it,&#39;” she says. “It&#39;s getting better, but sometimes I can still feel that thing in my chest just sitting there.” </p><div class="wp-block-image  has-alignleft" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><figure class="alignleft size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="680" height="680" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_4_inline-2.png" alt="An illustration of the top half of a person with two wires in their brain and a gray box in their chest connected to those wires." class="wp-image-3131383" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_4_inline-2.png 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_4_inline-2-383x383.png 383w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_4_inline-2-450x450.png 450w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_4_inline-2-186x186.png 186w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_4_inline-2-580x580.png 580w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_4_inline-2-214x214.png 214w" sizes="(max-width: 680px) 100vw, 680px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3131383">In deep brain stimulation for depression, electrodes surgically implanted in the brain are connected via wires under the skin to a battery-powered control box in the chest. The programmable control box tells the electrodes when to send signals that stimulate the brain.</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3131383">Erin Otwell</span></figcaption></figure></div><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> She also points out the annoyingly low-tech charging process, which is done with a wireless charger draped around her neck. Her charger shows only 10 percent increments, and the screen is on for only a minute before it locks up, without indicating that the charging is done. “They can get better at that part,” she says.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> In addition to the charging, there are lots of tasks these volunteers complete as part of the research — surveys, mood ratings, video journals. Twice daily, Amanda clicks what looks like a TV remote at home to collect brain data. “I&#39;m Bluetooth-enabled,” she says with a laugh. “I upload from the computer to the server at the hospital.” She and others also make regular trips to the lab at Mount Sinai.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> These days, Jon takes the train from his house just outside Philadelphia to Mount Sinai so often that he knows exactly which crack in the sidewalk to stand by as he waits for his train at the New Jersey Transit station. On one of his visits to the lab, a mess of scalp electrodes were eavesdropping on his brain. The scientist doing the measurements, neuroscientist Allison Waters, mentioned that his electrode leads were zipping 130 pulses of electricity into his brain per second.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “She just said it off the cuff,” Jon says. Later, with his daughter, Jon did the math for a full day, doubling it for each side: “22 million, 500 thousand electrical pulses to my brain,” Jon says. “That&#39;s what has kept me alive.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> During Jon&#39;s surgery on August 22, 2022, doctors told him that his only job was to be present. After his incisions healed, he was given a new task: rehabbing his brain. Jon was initially dismissive of the new job. He already felt fantastic, cocky almost, and didn&#39;t buy that he needed to work hard on rehab. “In the back of my head, I&#39;m like, &#39;OK, weirdos. I&#39;m not sick. This is great. I&#39;m good. I got this.&#39;”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> But about six weeks after his surgery, everything fell apart.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> A malaise crept in, and Jon freaked out. “Oh my God, I feel it,” he said. “I feel it in my body.” He snapped right back into the habits that depression solidified: overeating, sleeping too much and hiding away from his family. “My wife, I&#39;ll never forget it, was like, &#39;Hey, we got an appointment at the school.&#39;” But Jon told her he couldn&#39;t make it; he was busy. It was a lie. “I didn&#39;t have anything going on,” he says.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Jon knew that as part of the study protocol, around the sixth month, researchers would turn off his stimulation, a looming event that made him intensely anxious. His shift alarmed him so much that on the night of October 6, he sent an email to the Mount Sinai psychiatrist Martijn Figee to ask if his stimulation had been turned off earlier than planned. “Is there an earlier part of the program where it gets shut off too, such as now, and that is also part of the experiment?” Jon wrote. “Even if it was shut off, could you even tell me that?”<br><br> An hour and a half later, the email back was clear: “Your device is absolutely on <em>.”</em> His psychologist would address it with him at their next appointment.</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Relearning to live with emotions</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> As brain implants are used more and more, the risks of DBS have become somewhat clear. Regardless of why a person is getting it or where in the brain it targets,the technique can, like any medical procedure, go sideways. Electrode leads in the brain can break; the chest controller can fail; batteries can die. Infections, in both the head and chest, are a risk, as is wire tethering, a painful condition, also called bowstringing, in which scar tissue grows around the wire in the neck.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> DBS can also carry risks that are distinct from other surgeries. Electrical stimulation in certain parts of the brain has been linked to unwanted behavioral changes. For people receiving stimulation for Parkinson&#39;s disease, there have been cases of gambling problems and hypersexual behavior.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> In one unusual case, a Dutch man treated for obsessive-compulsive disorder developed a <a href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fnbeh.2014.00152/full" target="_blank" rel="noopener">brand-new and intense affinity for Johnny Cash hits</a> , especially “Ring of Fire,” “Folsom Prison Blues” and “Sunday Morning Coming Down.” When his stimulations diminish or his batteries die, the man subconsciously switches back to listening to his old favorites — Dutch-language songs and classics by the Beatles and the Rolling Stones.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> People being treated with DBS for depression have experienced relapses when the device accidentally stops working, for instance due to a battery failure or a wire breaking. But that&#39;s not what happened to Jon.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Worries over spiraling dark moods surface among people with DBS for depression, says psychologist Shannon O&#39;Neill, who works with Jon and other people treated with DBS at Mount Sinai. “We often talk significantly about the difference for them of how they can distinguish between depression and normal everyday sadness,” O&#39;Neill says. This is the rehab part, she says. People who have lived with severe depression for years need to relearn how to recognize and tolerate garden-variety emotions, including sorrow.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> As O&#39;Neill describes ordinary sadness, it reminds me of the analogy that emotions are like the weather. We can spend the morning under heavy cloud cover, and then maybe we luck out with a full-blast sunny afternoon. But it&#39;s fleeting. Likewise, our feelings are impermanent, O&#39;Neill says. “Negative emotions come and go, just like positive emotions come and go. It can be passing and not ever-present.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Emily Hollenbeck, whose DBS surgery was in 2021, says her recovery took time. “You&#39;re letting your brain relearn how to live in the world without the constant threat of severe negativity, suicidality, all of that.” She had to learn how to cope with emotions, and trust that she&#39;ll get through bad situations. “Basically, I&#39;m relearning how to ride the bike, you know?”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Understanding that these feelings are transitory — that ups and downs happen — is something people with severe depression haven&#39;t practiced, because they hadn&#39;t had to. They&#39;ve been perpetually stuck under heavy cloud cover. Emerging into an emotional landscape with those ups and downs can be intensely unsettling.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “At first it was scary,” says Amanda, who had DBS surgery last fall. “At first I felt like I was standing on the edge of a cliff.” An artist, Amanda draws her experiences to help her think them through. One of her pictures shows a cartoon Amanda wearing a rainbow shirt, standing high on a ledge of bright green grass with blue sky overhead. But she&#39;s looking over the edge to the darkness below. “I had been pulled out of this giant pit, and I was worried that I would fall back in it again.” </p><figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1030" height="700" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_2_inline-2_REV.jpg" alt="An illustration of a smiling Cartoon Amanda floating on top of the sea while the sun shines down and a one-ton weight has sunk to the sea floor." class="wp-image-3131552" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_2_inline-2_REV.jpg 1030w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_2_inline-2_REV-564x383.jpg 564w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_2_inline-2_REV-662x450.jpg 662w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_2_inline-2_REV-274x186.jpg 274w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_2_inline-2_REV-768x522.jpg 768w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_2_inline-2_REV-853x580.jpg 853w" sizes="(max-width: 1030px) 100vw, 1030px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3131552">Amanda, who received deep brain stimulation surgery in 2022, depicts her experience as art, often with a character named “cartoon Amanda.”</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3131552">Courtesy of Amanda</span></figcaption></figure><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> But she hasn&#39;t. When people recover from depression with DBS, they generally stay well, several studies suggest. Between three and six years after surgery, about 60 percent of <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/21285143/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">patients had sustained improvements</a> , Mayberg and colleagues reported in 2011 in the <em>American Journal of Psychiatry.</em> In a longer-term study, most of a group of 28 people who had deep brain stimulation for major depression or a type of bipolar disorder <a href="https://ajp.psychiatryonline.org/doi/10.1176/appi.ajp.2019.18121427" target="_blank" rel="noopener">saw benefits for more than eight years</a> , the researchers reported in 2019 in the same journal.</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Does DBS make people happy?</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The idea of a machine forcing happiness on us or taking away sorrow — that kind of mind control is unsettling for most of us. We are fiercely protective of the idea that our feelings originate inside of ourselves, that we are in charge here. So the idea that artificial happiness can be created by a computer that controls electrodes in our brain hooked to wires that snake down our neck? No thanks.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> That sentiment is understandable, but it&#39;s not what people with these implants experience. As I&#39;ve talked with people who had lived first with devastating depression and then with these devices, I have come to think that these implants do not make a person feel artificial joy. “DBS is not going to give you happiness,” O&#39;Neill says. Instead, “it just kind of clears the way.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Overcoming misconceptions about what this technology can and can&#39;t do is yet another burden for Jon and others. The patients I spoke with were incredibly candid about their depression and their treatment. They graciously tolerated my questions. But being open about their medical condition and treatment can exact a steep price.</p><hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" /><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <em>If you or someone you know is facing a suicidal crisis or emotional distress, call or text the 988 Suicide &amp; Crisis Lifeline at 988.</em></p><hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" /><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <em>The next articles<a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/brain-implant-depression-electrode-stimulation-stigma">dives into the tough topic of stigma around mental disorders and their treatments</a> .</em></p><p class="has-gray-light-background-color has-background" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <em>This series was made possible with funding from the Alfred P. Sloan Foundation.</em></p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_4_feat-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="126236" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_4_feat-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title> There&#39;s a stigma around brain implants and other depression treatments</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/brain-implant-depression-electrode-stimulation-stigma<dc:creator><![CDATA[Laura Sanders]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Thu, 21 Sep 2023 13:34:05 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Health & Medicine]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3131429 </guid><description><![CDATA[The fifth article in the series asks why people are so uncomfortable with changing the brain. ]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<div class="wp-block-sciencenews-content-sidebar"><div class="wp-block-image is-style-rounded has-alignleft" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><figure class="mobile-wrap alignleft size-thumbnail is-resized"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-186x186.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-3131518" width="93" height="93" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-186x186.jpg 186w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-383x383.jpg 383w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-450x450.jpg 450w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-768x768.jpg 768w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-580x580.jpg 580w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-776x776.jpg 776w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-214x214.jpg 214w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square.jpg 1080w" sizes="(max-width: 93px) 100vw, 93px" /></figure></div><h3 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Electricity Saved My Brain</h3><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <em>This is the fifth part in a series on deep brain stimulation for depression. <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/brain-implant-depression-electrode-stimulation-surgery">Read from the beginning</a> .</em></p></div><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Like many people who have struggled with a mental illness, Emily Hollenbeck had plenty of stories of people not quite getting it. One memorable instance happened as she was about to be anesthetized for an electroconvulsive therapy treatment. The anesthesiologist found out that she had a Ph.D. in psychology. “His eyes settle on me, and he goes, &#39;Oh, that&#39;s ironic.&#39;” Her academic background should have somehow prevented her illness, he seemed to imply.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> A palpable silence filled the room. “I remember literally biting my tongue,” she says, “being like, &#39;We&#39;re not going to sass the guy who&#39;s injecting the propofol.&#39;”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Being open about depression can bring judgment, and danger: “If you are honest about what you need for your mental health, you can suffer consequences,” says Emily, who had DBS surgery in 2021. That can include lost jobs, lost relationships and perhaps most crucially, lost health care.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Those consequences are why I&#39;m not identifying Patient 001 by his name. He works in an intensely intellectual and competitive field, and with a new baby at home, he can&#39;t risk losing business over people&#39;s mistaken assumptions.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> There&#39;s stigma surrounding depression, and there&#39;s stigma surrounding its treatments. When Patient 001 told his family he was getting experimental brain surgery, they didn&#39;t understand. “At first, they were like, &#39;You&#39;re crazy. It&#39;s unsafe.&#39;”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> In a way, their reaction tracks with people&#39;s suspicions toward other treatments for depression, and psychiatric disorders more generally, despite the fact that they work for many people. Since their rise to prominence in the 1990s, antidepressants have caught heat from people claiming the drugs change personalities and steal emotions. Electroconvulsive therapy is still crawling back after the damage done by portrayals like in the movie <em>One Flew Over the Cuckoo&#39;s Nest</em> . Even talk therapy can bring shame and secrecy.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> So perhaps it&#39;s not surprising that electrodes implanted into your brain raise a whole new set of assumptions, misgivings and judgments. People will live with these stigmas until society changes, until people start understanding what severe depression is like, and what treatments are like too.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “You&#39;re screaming for help, and they just don&#39;t understand,” Patient 001 tells me. “That&#39;s probably one of the reasons I&#39;m talking to you, even though I&#39;m doing it anonymously. I hope one day one kid reads what you&#39;re writing, and he finds DBS and he&#39;s cured.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Barbara, Jon&#39;s wife, is no stranger to people&#39;s uncomfortable reactions. “When we have told people that he has a pacemaker in his brain, basically, you get this sort of strange, &#39;Oh my God,&#39;…. They&#39;re like, &#39;What? You&#39;re going to let them do this to you?&#39;” There&#39;s this assumption, she says, that the brain is somehow different from other parts of the body. The heart can also need a device that delivers electrical stimulation. So why not the brain? “It&#39;s really interesting to see people, myself included, process that.” </p><figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><iframe loading="lazy" title="Depression &amp; DBS doesn’t just impact patients | חדשות המדע" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/ATQrx4FcNIA?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe></div><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> Watch a video of Barbara Nelson talking about her experience as a partner to someone with depression, and how DBS changed her family.</figcaption></figure><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> I&#39;ve been wondering the same thing: What sets the brain apart, and why are people so uncomfortable with attempts to change it?</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Here&#39;s what I think. Remember the Dutch guy who <a href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fnbeh.2014.00152/full" target="_blank" rel="noopener">all of a sudden loved Johnny Cash</a> after his implant was turned on? That story sounds a bit trivial. His new musical taste didn&#39;t bother him; it&#39;s a minor thing in the grand scheme of things. But that change, that switch, arguably bores straight to the core of our unease. So many of us, myself included, consider our brains — and the minds they create — the bedrock of our identity. So when a disease attacks the brain, or a treatment changes the brain, we get nervous.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> None of us like the thought of having a brain implant tell us what music we like, especially if we might not be aware of it. The stakes are much, much higher when it comes to how we feel.</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Does DBS change who you are?</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Reporting this story, I heard a lot of jokes about being a cyborg, Bluetooth-enabled, bionic. People would laugh as they said it. But I wondered if there was anything more to these offhand comments. Does this brain implant change who you are?</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Jon kindly tells me that he understands why I&#39;d ask. “I can only tell you that it is the exact opposite of that question,” he says. For him, DBS took away his poison. “It purely eliminates the disease…. That&#39;s it.”<br><br> Amanda echoes the sentiment: “Nothing I&#39;ve ever done has changed who I am or my personality,” she says, DBS included. “I&#39;m still the same person. I&#39;m just suffering more or less.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Emily flips my question on me in a beautifully philosophical twist: “What does that even mean? Where is the &#39;me&#39;?” Equating ourselves with our brains makes sense, she says, because much of what we experience comes through our brains. “But is that really where our selves are?” </p><figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="680" height="478" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_5_inline.jpg" alt="portrait of Emily Hollenbeck" class="wp-image-3131432" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_5_inline.jpg 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_5_inline-545x383.jpg 545w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_5_inline-640x450.jpg 640w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_5_inline-265x186.jpg 265w" sizes="(max-width: 680px) 100vw, 680px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3131432">Emily Hollenbeck, like other people with DBS implants, had to relearn how to cope with her new emotional range.</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3131432">Courtesy of Emily Hollenbeck</span></figcaption></figure><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Who she is, Emily says, is an activity, a choice. Her depression took away those choices and altered who she was. But now, “I don&#39;t have that feeling, so which of those is correct? I don&#39;t know. But I know which one I like better. I know that&#39;s not a satisfactory answer for your question, but what really gets to the heart of it is that I feel like I&#39;m untethered, and I have the ability now to focus on the things that I do really care about. And that&#39;s where my <em>self</em> lies.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> These days, Jon says, his sense of self is lighter. Without the poison coursing through his body, Jon feels better, more energized, more present in his life with wife, Barbara, their three kids, a dog, a cat and a bearded dragon named Lizzy. But, as his daily surveys make absolutely clear, he&#39;s still crabby. “There are certain things that you realize are the disease, and certain things that are innate in who you are,” he says. His irritability scores didn&#39;t budge after DBS. “I guess I&#39;m just a cranky middle-aged dude now.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Barbara may be one of the best judges of who Jon is now. Is he different somehow with DBS and without severe depression? “I don&#39;t feel like he&#39;s changed,” Barbara says. “I don&#39;t feel like I have a different person living in my house. It&#39;s not that creepy, sci-fi way, like there&#39;s this new person,” she says. It&#39;s just him, the Jon she met all those years ago.</p><hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" /><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <em>Our final article in the series <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/future-deep-brain-stimulation-depression">looks to the future for Jon and his family, and for deep brain stimulation</a> .</em></p><p class="has-gray-light-background-color has-background" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <em>This series was made possible with funding from the Alfred P. Sloan Foundation.</em></p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_5_feat-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="160038" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_5_feat-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title> What&#39;s the future of deep brain stimulation for depression?</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/future-deep-brain-stimulation-depression<dc:creator><![CDATA[Laura Sanders]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Thu, 21 Sep 2023 13:33:32 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Neuroscience]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3131448 </guid><description><![CDATA[The final story of the series describes efforts to simplify and improve brain implants for severe depression.]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<div class="wp-block-sciencenews-content-sidebar"><div class="wp-block-image is-style-rounded has-alignleft" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><figure class="mobile-wrap alignleft size-thumbnail is-resized"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-186x186.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-3131518" width="93" height="93" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-186x186.jpg 186w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-383x383.jpg 383w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-450x450.jpg 450w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-768x768.jpg 768w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-580x580.jpg 580w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-776x776.jpg 776w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square-214x214.jpg 214w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/newsletter-signup-background_REV_square.jpg 1080w" sizes="(max-width: 93px) 100vw, 93px" /></figure></div><h3 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Electricity Saved My Brain</h3><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <em>This is the final part in a series on deep brain stimulation for depression. <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/brain-implant-depression-electrode-stimulation-surgery">Read from the beginning</a> .</em></p></div><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Neurologist Helen Mayberg cringes at the slow pace of DBS research. Her <a href="https://www.cell.com/neuron/fulltext/S0896-6273(05)00156-X?_returnURL=https%3A%2F%2Flinkinghub.elsevier.com%2Fretrieve%2Fpii%2FS089662730500156X%3Fshowall%3Dtrue" target="_blank" rel="noopener">first paper describing DBS for depression</a> in the subcallosal cingulate (then called Brodmann Area 25) appeared in the journal <em>Neuron</em> in 2005. Almost 20 years later, she almost can&#39;t believe that researchers are not further along in bringing this technique to people who would benefit from it.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “On the other hand, we&#39;ve learned so much that maybe it&#39;s not so bad,” Mayberg says. Still, she feels impatient. “We don&#39;t have a lot of time,” she says. “People are dying now, so let&#39;s fix them. And then we can make something better.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Mayberg hopes to see the treatment become streamlined. The first heart pacemaker was an incredible piece of technology, but it was giant and clunky. Today, the powerful device, usually about the size of a matchbook, sits near millions of people&#39;s hearts, keeping them beating. As with the heart, for the brain, “how do you go from complicated to simple? Everything is about the prototyping and the simplification,” she says.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> What&#39;s next? “What&#39;s the future of this, the future three steps ahead?” Mayberg says. “I have no idea.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Despite stories from Jon Nelson and others, deep brain stimulation still has its stigma to overcome, even in the research world. Questions of autonomy — of control over feelings and actions — crop up in ethics discussions of brain technology. But to Martijn Figee, the psychiatrist and DBS researcher who has worked with many people implanted with electrodes, those questions are a “luxury problem.” That framing ignores the idea that mental illness itself takes away a person&#39;s control. “People who work in DBS are always a little frustrated by these discussions,” Figee says. “We&#39;re always like, &#39;Talk to the patients.&#39;”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Figee, who receives consulting fees from Medtronic, a device company that makes brain implants, and his colleagues asked people before and after surgery for DBS for obsessive-compulsive disorder and Parkinson&#39;s about their feelings of being in control of themselves. People did not report a loss of feeling in control of themselves after the procedure. In fact, the people treated for OCD reported a bigger jump in autonomy and control than the Parkinson&#39;s patients. “That&#39;s not something that bothered them at all,” Figee says, “because the OCD was more of a prison to them than the fact that they have this implant.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Psychologist Shannon O&#39;Neill, who treats people with DBS at Mount Sinai, says she hopes that the procedure will be more readily understood in the future: “What I&#39;d love is a shift toward not making it a last resort,” she says. “I wonder if we wait too long to give an individual DBS.” She doesn&#39;t mean that brain implants would be an early treatment, but instead, she wants other health care professionals to have more awareness of the procedure so that they can refer people who have run out of hope.</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> What are the open questions?</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> What&#39;s next will almost certainly include nuanced and complex science. Big questions remain about where in the brain to stimulate, for which people and what kind of stimulation. Jon and Amanda are participating in follow-up studies searching for signs of recovery in their brains, bodies and microexpressions on their faces, and even in their voices. “The commitments are out of control,” Jon jokes. He spends eight minutes twice a day recording his brain waves, along with video journals and daily, weekly and monthly surveys. His brain is imaged regularly.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Researchers are searching for a hallmark, a signature, that can tell them the method is working. “I need to know when the depression is away, and I need to have a way to discriminate,” Mayberg says. “When are you having a bad day and when are you relapsing? Those are not the same thing.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Mayberg and her colleagues just described one such hallmark in six people who underwent DBS for depression. A <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-023-06541-3#Sec7" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">collection of changes</a> in brain behavior can indicate when a person has recovered, the researchers reported September 20 in <em>Nature</em> .</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> A handful of trials are putting a spin on the typical DBS approach and studying what&#39;s called adaptive DBS, which kicks in only when a certain pathological brain activity pattern is detected. That approach has <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/brain-implant-severe-depression-activity-stimulation">worked well for a woman named Sarah with severe depression</a> . Researchers at the University of California, San Francisco <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41591-021-01480-w" target="_blank" rel="noopener">published the details of her improvements</a> in 2021.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Similar on-demand efforts are happening for other disorders, including binge eating and post-traumatic stress disorder. Jay Gill, a brain researcher and medical student at UCLA told me that one man, a veteran with PTSD, described having an aura, a sort of premonition, just before his symptoms would get bad. With his adaptive DBS system in place, he still gets triggered and feels the aura, but instead of feeling worse, a feeling of calm sets in.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The optimal DBS approach for depression may be similar to the approach for PTSD, OCD, addiction and other psychiatric disorders. Or maybe not. There&#39;s still so much to learn.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Not everyone thinks about depression, or any illness for that matter, as a battle. Jon does. And there were days — lots of days — when he thought he&#39;d lose it. </p><figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="680" height="419" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_6_inline.jpg" alt="A photo of Jon Nelson standing on an ice rink next to a red hockey goal." class="wp-image-3131450" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_6_inline.jpg 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_6_inline-622x383.jpg 622w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_6_inline-302x186.jpg 302w" sizes="(max-width: 680px) 100vw, 680px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3131450">Jon Nelson&#39;s deep brain stimulation treatment hasn&#39;t made him happy all the time, but he now enjoys experiences more, including moments like coaching hockey and softball.</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3131450">AIDAN KAHN</span></figcaption></figure><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> These days, the Nelson house is bright. It&#39;s full of laughter, riddles, good-natured teasing, homemade pizza — and an energetic kid on in-line skates who twirls and glides through the kitchen loop. It&#39;s also full of hope for a future that&#39;s better than the past. That makes me reluctant to ask Barbara a question that I know will be hard for her to answer: Is she worried that Jon&#39;s DBS treatment will stop working?</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “That&#39;s always in the back of my mind a little bit,” she tells me. Over the years, Barbara has learned to temper her expectations for the future. “You just never really know what&#39;s going to happen,” she says. In a way, she&#39;s still guarded. “I don&#39;t know if this is going to work forever,” she says.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “But my perspective is that even if something changes, we have had this time with him.… And if it keeps going forever, that&#39;s amazing. It&#39;s amazing. I hope it does.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> On the drives home from softball, field hockey, golf, basketball and ice hockey, Jon and whichever kids are around have chats. “I always call it &#39;car talk with the kids.&#39;” In one of these car talks, Jon&#39;s youngest piped up. “He&#39;s like, &#39;Dad, I&#39;m so happy you just kept fighting for us.&#39; These little comments that come out of nowhere. I&#39;m like, &#39;Oh my God. They get it. They understand it.&#39; It&#39;s a trip.”</p><p class="has-gray-light-background-color has-background" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> <em>This series was made possible with funding from the Alfred P. Sloan Foundation.</em></p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_6_feat-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="214800" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/092323_neurotech_6_feat-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title> How drones are helping scientists find meteorites</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/how-ai-drones-find-meteorites<dc:creator><![CDATA[Katherine Kornei]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Thu, 21 Sep 2023 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Planetary Science]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3131355 </guid><description><![CDATA[Searching for fallen space rocks is labor intensive. A team of researchers in Australia is speeding things up with drones and machine learning. ]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<p>Meteorites offer tantalizing clues about what the early solar system was like. But finding them is far from rocket science. Often, researchers simply fan out across a landscape and walk for hours while staring at the ground. Now, some scientists are turning to drones and machine learning to help spot freshly fallen meteorites much more efficiently.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> A team of six people on a meteorite-hunting expedition can search about 200,000 square meters per day, says Seamus Anderson, a planetary scientist at Curtin University in Perth, Australia. But since the area over which a cluster of meteorites falls typically can&#39;t be pinpointed to better than a few million square meters, searching can take a while, he says. “It&#39;s quite slow.” </p><figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="674" height="450" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/091423_kk_drone_meteorites_inline-1-674x450.jpg" alt="Meteorite hunter Seamus Anderson sits in the back of a truck on his drone-based expedition in Western Australia in 2021." class="wp-image-3131358" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/091423_kk_drone_meteorites_inline-1-674x450.jpg 674w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/091423_kk_drone_meteorites_inline-1-574x383.jpg 574w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/091423_kk_drone_meteorites_inline-1-279x186.jpg 279w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/091423_kk_drone_meteorites_inline-1.jpg 680w" sizes="(max-width: 674px) 100vw, 674px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3131358">Seamus Anderson (pictured) and his colleagues used a drone to find a meteorite in Western Australia in 2021.</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3131358">The Desert Fireball Network</span></figcaption></figure><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Around 2016, Anderson began toying with the concept of using drones to take pictures of the ground to look for meteorites. That idea blossomed into a Ph.D. project. In 2022, he and his colleagues <a href="https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/2041-8213/ac66d4" target="_blank" rel="noopener">reported their first successful recovery of a meteorite</a> spotted with a drone. They&#39;ve since found <a href="https://www.hou.usra.edu/meetings/metsoc2023/pdf/6187.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">four more meteorites at a different site</a> , the team reported August 17 in Los Angeles at a meeting of the Meteoritical Society.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Drone-based searches are much faster than the standard way of doing things, Anderson says. “You&#39;re going from about 300 days of human effort down to about a dozen or so.” It&#39;s also fun and exciting work, he says, but there are challenges too.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Anderson and his collaborators have used drones to search for meteorites in remote parts of Western Australia and South Australia. The team is tipped off about a fall site by networks of ground-based cameras that track meteoroids flashing through Earth&#39;s atmosphere. Then, the hunt is on.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The researchers pack a four-wheel drive vehicle with drone and computer equipment, battery charging stations, generators, fuel, food, camping equipment, tables, chairs and more. The drive to the fall site can take more than a day, often on rough or nonexistent roads, Anderson says. “You hope you don&#39;t pop a tire.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> After arriving, the team flies its primary drone at an altitude of about 20 meters. Its camera takes an image of the ground once every second, and the researchers download the data every 40 minutes or so when the drone lands to receive fresh batteries.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> A typical day of flying can net over 10,000 images, which are then divided digitally into 100 million or so smaller sections. Those “tiles,” each 2 meters on a side, are fed into a machine learning algorithm that has been trained to recognize meteorites based on images of the real thing or terrestrial rocks spray-painted black. The latter are convincing stand-ins for real meteorites, Anderson says.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The algorithm is good but not perfect. It automatically discards most tiles — typically upwards of 99 percent — that don&#39;t contain any meteorite-looking objects. But that still leaves roughly 50,000 or so tiles after a day&#39;s worth of flights that must be manually checked by a human, Anderson says. </p><div class="wp-block-image  has-alignleft" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><figure class="alignleft size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="612" height="450" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/091423_kk_drone_meteorites_inline-2-612x450.jpg" alt="Sleeping kangaroos sleep in the desert in this drone image marked with yellow squares by a machine learning algorithm designed to identify space rocks." class="wp-image-3131359" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/091423_kk_drone_meteorites_inline-2-612x450.jpg 612w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/091423_kk_drone_meteorites_inline-2-521x383.jpg 521w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/091423_kk_drone_meteorites_inline-2-253x186.jpg 253w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/091423_kk_drone_meteorites_inline-2.jpg 680w" sizes="(max-width: 612px) 100vw, 612px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3131359">A machine learning algorithm, trained to identify potential meteorites in drone images, can mistake sleeping kangaroos (indicated with yellow squares) for space rocks. Researchers are working on improving the algorithm further.</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3131359">The Desert Fireball Network</span></figcaption></figure></div><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Most of the time, those tiles contain things that decidedly aren&#39;t meteorites: animal poop, tin cans, snakes or sleeping kangaroos, for instance. Those objects get flagged as potential meteorites simply because the algorithm isn&#39;t familiar with them, Anderson says, and it&#39;s up to the team to winnow out those false positives.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> For objects that still look convincing to the human eye, the researchers send out a smaller drone that flies much lower — about a meter off the ground — to investigate. Finally, the team goes out in person to examine promising candidates.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The researchers plan to train their algorithm to better avoid flagging things like poop and kangaroos as meteorites. And the team is working on making its computer code open-source so that other researchers can freely use it.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Anderson also hopes to see drones make an appearance in Antarctica, <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/machine-learning-meteorite-antarctica">a hotbed of meteorite sleuthing</a> ( <em>SN: 1/26/22</em> ). But the icy environment will present a whole new slew of challenges, Anderson says, such as making sure sensitive electronic equipment fares well in the frigid conditions and overcoming the logistics of working in such a remote place. “Antarctica is a whole different beast.”</p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/091423_kk_drone_meteorites_feat-800x450.jpeg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="1245639" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/091423_kk_drone_meteorites_feat-800x450.jpeg"></enclosure></item><item><title> Interlocking logs may be evidence of the oldest known wooden structure</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/logs-evidence-oldest-wood-structure<dc:creator><![CDATA[Richard Kemeny]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Wed, 20 Sep 2023 15:01:21 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Anthropology]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3131532 </guid><description><![CDATA[Roughly 480,000-year-old wooden find from Zambia suggests early hominids were more skilled at structuring their environments than scientists realized. ]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<p>Modified logs dating to about 476,000 years ago might be the oldest evidence of wooden structures, a new study finds.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Wooden artifacts decompose easily and are relatively scant in the archaeological record compared with stone or bone. The new finding, reported September 20 in <em>Nature,</em> suggests that the structural use of wood <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-023-06557-9" target="_blank" rel="noopener">may stretch</a> <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-023-06557-9" target="_blank" rel="noopener">far</a> <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-023-06557-9" target="_blank" rel="noopener">back</a> <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-023-06557-9" target="_blank" rel="noopener">into the</a> <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-023-06557-9" target="_blank" rel="noopener">history of human ancestors</a> , hinting at advanced cognitive skills and a less nomadic lifestyle for some hominids than previously thought.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “It&#39;s a challenge to preconceptions about what are considered sophisticated, complex behaviors,” says Larry Barham, an archaeologist at the University of Liverpool in England. “For me, settling into one place and changing the landscape, that is very sophisticated.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Humans and their ancestors have been using wood in some fashion for quite some time. The earliest known example of modified wood is <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/004724849190015N" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a polished plank from Israel</a> dating to around 780,000 years ago. <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/385807a0" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Wooden tools</a> don&#39;t appear in the historical record until about 400,000 years ago. Before this new study, the <a href="https://www.york.ac.uk/50/impact/star-carr-house/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">earliest known example of a wooden structure</a> was much more recent: around 9000 BC</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> During a dig in 2019, Barham and colleagues found five modified wooden objects in the exposed bank of a river flowing into the top of Kalambo Falls in Zambia. The area is rich with forest and has a consistently high water table. This makes it ideal for human habitation — and the water also blocks oxygen from buried wood. Since the 1950s, archaeologists have excavated ancient technologies here, though wooden objects couldn&#39;t be accurately placed in time and clear modifications had been worn away.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> This time the team used a technique <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/humans-first-settled-australia-early-65000-years-ago">known as luminescence dating</a> ( <em>SN: 7/19/17</em> ). Minerals buried underground gradually absorb background radiation like a battery taking up charge, which can be released later as light. This reveals how many years ago a sample last saw the sun. The team analyzed 16 sand samples‚ including from directly around the wooden objects, and grouped the artifacts into three chunks of time from 476,000 to 324,000 years ago.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> In the sands that are nearly half a million years old, the team found two large interlocking logs, with shaped ends and wide, carved notches at the point they overlap. Like an early version of Lincoln Logs, this would have held the wood together. Both logs showed evidence of chopping and scraping, and were buried near tools used for scraping or carving, hand axes and other crafting equipment. </p><div class="wp-block-image  has-alignleft" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><figure class="alignleft size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="434" height="450" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/091923_rk_oldest-wood-structure_inline-434x450.jpg" alt="A photo of two people examining an almost 480,000-year-old wooden log." class="wp-image-3131536" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/091923_rk_oldest-wood-structure_inline-434x450.jpg 434w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/091923_rk_oldest-wood-structure_inline-369x383.jpg 369w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/091923_rk_oldest-wood-structure_inline-179x186.jpg 179w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/091923_rk_oldest-wood-structure_inline-559x580.jpg 559w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/091923_rk_oldest-wood-structure_inline.jpg 680w" sizes="(max-width: 434px) 100vw, 434px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3131536">An ancient wooden artifact suggests early hominids living nearly half a million years ago may have shaped tree trunks into structures.</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3131536">Larry Barham/Univ. of Liverpool</span></figcaption></figure></div><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> These logs may have been part of a structure — a raised walkway, a place to store wood or somewhere to sit — that helped early hominids in their environment, the researchers suggest. Based on timing and location, the structure could be the handiwork of <em>Homo heidelbergensis</em> , a human ancestor that lived about 700,000 to 200,000 years ago. Other wooden objects recovered from the site include a wedge, a digging stick and a chopped log, dating from 390,000 to 324,000 years ago.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “This paper provides a wonderful peek into our past,” says Rebecca Biermann Gürbüz, a biological anthropologist at the University at Buffalo in New York who was not involved in the study. Other primates use wood and plants in a variety of ways, she says. “So the fact that [hominids] did so nearly half a million years ago is not surprising.”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> In fact, Barham wonders if Stone Age is even the right term for that era. “Let&#39;s say wood survived as much as bone does in the archaeological record,” he says. “Maybe we should relabel our Stone Age to the Woodworking Age, an Organic Age or something that reflects the reality of common behavior, which we can only really glimpse.”</p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/091923_rk_oldest-wood-structure_feat-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="283492" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/091923_rk_oldest-wood-structure_feat-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item><item><title> Why sewage may hold the key to tracking diseases far beyond COVID-19</title><link/> https://www.sciencenews.org/article/sewage-key-track-disease-covid-19-wastewater<dc:creator><![CDATA[Betsy Ladyzhets]]></dc:creator><pubDate> Wed, 20 Sep 2023 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate><category><![CDATA[Health & Medicine]]></category><guid ispermalink="false"> https://www.sciencenews.org/?p=3131090 </guid><description><![CDATA[COVID-19, mpox and many other pathogens are detectable in wastewater, but public health officials are still figuring out how best to use those data. ]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[




<p class="has-drop-cap">The future of disease tracking is going down the drain — literally. Flushed with success over detecting coronavirus in wastewater, and even specific variants of SARS-CoV-2, the virus that causes COVID-19, researchers are now eyeing our collective poop to monitor a wide variety of health threats.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Before the pandemic, wastewater surveillance was a smaller field, primarily focused on testing for drugs or mapping microbial ecosystems. But these researchers were tracking specific health threats in specific places — opioids in parts of Arizona, polio in Israel — and hadn&#39;t quite realized the potential for national or global public health.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Then COVID-19 hit.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The pandemic triggered an “incredible acceleration” of wastewater science, says Adam Gushgari, an environmental engineer who before 2020 worked on testing wastewater for opioids. He now develops a range of wastewater surveillance projects for Eurofins Scientific, a global laboratory testing and research company headquartered in Luxembourg.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> A subfield that was once a few handfuls of specialists has grown into more than enough scientists to pack a stadium, he says. And they come from a wide variety of fields — environmental science, analytical chemistry, microbiology, epidemiology and more — all collaborating to track the coronavirus, interpret the data and communicate results to the public. With other methods of monitoring COVID-19 on the decline, wastewater surveillance has become one of health experts&#39; primary sources for spotting new surges.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Hundreds of wastewater treatment plants across the United States are now part of COVID-19 testing programs, sending their data to the National Wastewater Surveillance System, or NWSS, a monitoring program launched in fall 2020 by the US Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Hundreds more such testing programs have launched globally, as tracked by the <a href="https://ucmerced.maps.arcgis.com/apps/dashboards/c778145ea5bb4daeb58d31afee389082" target="_blank" rel="noopener">COVIDPoops19 dashboard</a> run by researchers at the University of California, Merced.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> In the last year, wastewater scientists have started to consider what else could be tracked through this new infrastructure. They&#39;re looking at seasonal diseases like the flu, recently emerging diseases like bird flu and mpox, formerly called monkeypox, as well as drug-resistant pathogens like the fungus <em>Candida auris</em> . The scientists are even considering how to identify entirely new threats.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Wastewater surveillance will have health impacts “far broader than COVID,” predicts Amy Kirby, a health scientist at the CDC who leads NWSS.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> But there are challenges getting from promise to possible. So far, such sewage surveillance has been mostly a proof of concept, confirming data from other tracking systems. Experts are still determining how data from our poop can actually inform policy; that&#39;s true even for COVID-19, now the poster child for this monitoring. And they face public officials wary of its value and questions over whether, now that COVID-19 health emergencies have ended, the pipeline of funding will be cut off.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> This monitoring will hopefully become “one of the technologies that really evolves post-pandemic to be here to stay,” says Mariana Matus, cofounder of Biobot Analytics, a company based in Cambridge, Mass., that has tested sewage for the CDC and many other health agencies. But for that to happen, the technology needs continued buy-in from governments, research institutions and the public, Matus and other scientists say.</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> How wastewater testing works</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Wastewater-based epidemiology has a long history, tracing back at least to physician <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC7150208/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">John Snow&#39;s 1850s observations</a> that cholera outbreaks in London were connected to contaminated water.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> In the 1920s and &#39;30s, scientists began to take samples from sewage and study them in the lab, learning to isolate specific pathogens that cause disease. These early researchers focused on diseases that spread through contaminated water, such as polio and typhoid.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Today, automated machines typically retrieve sewage samples. The machines used to collect waste beneath maintenance hole covers are “like R2-D2 in terms of size” or smaller, says Erin Driver, an environmental engineer at Arizona State University in Tempe who works on collection methods.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Driver can plug this machine, or a larger version used for sampling at wastewater treatment plants, into a water pipe and program it to pull a small amount of sewage into an empty bottle at regular intervals, say, once an hour for 24 hours. She and colleagues are developing smaller versions of the automated sampler that could be better suited for more targeted sampling.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> What happens in the lab to that bottle of waste depends on what scientists are testing for. To test for opioids and other chemicals, scientists might filter large particles out of the sample with a vacuum system, extract the specific chemicals that they want to test, then run the results through a spectrometer, an instrument that measures chemical concentrations by analyzing the light the chemicals give off.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> To determine levels of SARS-CoV-2 or another virus, a scientist might separate liquid waste from solid waste with a centrifuge, isolate viral genetic material, and then test the results with a PCR machine, similar to testing someone&#39;s nose swab. Or, if scientists want to know which SARS-CoV-2 variants are present, they can put the material through a machine that identifies a variety of genetic sequences.</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Would the coronavirus even show up in waste?</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> In the panicked early days of the pandemic, an urgent basic question loomed. “Will this even work?” remembers Marlene Wolfe, an environmental microbiologist at Emory University in Atlanta. While polio is spread through fecal matter, there were early hints that the coronavirus mostly spreads through the air; scientists initially weren&#39;t even sure that it would show up in sewage.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> On the same day in 2020 that the San Francisco Bay Area went on lockdown, Wolfe and colleagues at Stanford University, where she was based at the time, got a grant to find out. The team was soon spending hours driving around the Bay Area to collect sewage samples, “navigating lockdown rules” and negotiating special permissions to use lab space, she says.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “We were anxiously waiting to see if our first samples would show a positive result for SARS-CoV-2,” Wolfe says.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Not only did the sewage samples test positive, Wolfe and her colleagues found that coronavirus levels in the Bay Area&#39;s <a href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/full/10.1021/acs.est.0c06191" target="_blank" rel="noopener">wastewater followed the same trends as reported cases</a> , the team reported in December 2020 in <em>Environmental Science &amp; Technology</em> . When case counts went up, more virus appeared in the sewage, and vice versa. Early projects in other parts of the country showed similar results.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> More than three years later, data on reported cases have become much less reliable. Fewer people are seeking out lab-based PCR tests in favor of easier-to-access at-home tests — with results often not reported. Wastewater trends have become the best proxy to provide early warnings of potential new COVID-19 surges, such as the increased spread this summer, to health officials and the public alike.</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Opening the tracking floodgates</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> In summer 2022, wastewater tracking got a new chance to prove itself. Mpox was rapidly spreading globally, including in the United States. But tests were limited, and the disease, which was spreading primarily through intimate contact between men, quickly drew social stigma, leading some people to hesitate in seeking medical care.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Within a few weeks of the start of the US outbreak, Wolfe and her colleagues, as well as research teams at Biobot and other companies, had developed tests to identify mpox in sewage.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Just as scientists had seen with COVID-19, <a href="https://www.nejm.org/doi/full/10.1056/NEJMc2213882" target="_blank" rel="noopener">mpox trends in wastewater matched trends in official case numbers</a> . In California, wastewater results even suggested that the disease may have spread farther than data from doctors&#39; offices suggested, Wolfe and collaborators reported in February in the <em>New England Journal of Medicine.</em></p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Like COVID-19, mpox doesn&#39;t transmit through the water, but sewage testing still picked up the virus. The early results from that summer outbreak convinced some health officials that wastewater technology could be used for many diseases, no matter how they spread, Matus says. </p><figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="680" height="499" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_wastewater_inline2.jpg" alt="A map of North America showing hundreds of blue dots and six gray dots with airplanes to mark wastewater sites." class="wp-image-3131155" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_wastewater_inline2.jpg 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_wastewater_inline2-522x383.jpg 522w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_wastewater_inline2-613x450.jpg 613w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_wastewater_inline2-253x186.jpg 253w" sizes="(max-width: 680px) 100vw, 680px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3131155">Hundreds of wastewater sites (blue dots), including some airports, monitor for SARS-CoV-2 in North America. With COVID-19 test reporting waning, this sewage surveillance is helping monitor surges in infections.</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3131155">CC Naughton, 2021. COVIDPoops19: Summary of Global SARS-CoV-2 Wastewater Monitoring Efforts by UC Merced Researchers. ESRI ArcGIS Online Dashboard. https://arcg.is/1aummW</span></figcaption></figure><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Scientists are starting to find more and more infectious diseases that can be tracked in sewage. “Honestly, everything that we&#39;ve tried so far has worked,” says Wolfe, who is now a principal investigator of <a href="https://wastewaterscan.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">WastewaterSCAN</a> , a national sewage testing project led by researchers at Stanford and Emory. The project team currently tests samples for six different viruses and is working on other tests that it can send out to the more than 150 sites in its monitoring network.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Through an informal literature <a href="https://biobot.io/pathogen-biomarkers-in-wastewater-stool-and-urine-nearly-endless-opportunities-for-the-future-of-wbe/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">review of pathogens important for public health</a> , scientists at Biobot found that previous research had identified 76 out of 80 of them in wastewater, stool or urine, suggesting that those pathogens could be monitored through sewage. The list ranges from the chicken pox virus to the microbes that cause sexually transmitted diseases like chlamydia to the tickborne bacteria that cause Lyme disease.</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Finding focus</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> With this much opportunity, the question on many researchers&#39; minds is not, “What <em>can</em> we test for?” but “What <em>should</em> we test for?”</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> In January, a report put out by the National Academies of Sciences, Engineering and Medicine came up with <a href="https://nap.nationalacademies.org/catalog/26767/wastewater-based-disease-surveillance-for-public-health-action" target="_blank" rel="noopener">three criteria</a> . The pathogen should threaten public health. It should be detectable in wastewater. And it should generate data that public health agencies can use to protect their communities.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Given all the threats and hints of what can be found in wastewater, the first two criteria don&#39;t narrow the field too much. So for now, researchers are taking cues from state and local public health officials on which pathogens to prioritize.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Biobot is working on tests for common diseases like the flu, RSV, hepatitis C and gonorrhea. And the CDC has its eye on some of the same common pathogens, as well as strategies for tracking antimicrobial resistance, a threat that has increased during the pandemic as health systems have been under strain.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Even if they choose the perfect targets, though, researchers also have to figure out how to generate useful data. For now, that&#39;s a sticking point.</p><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> How to use the data</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Tracking pathogens is one thing. But determining how the results correspond to actual numbers of sick people is another, even in the case of COVID-19, where researchers now have years of detailed data. As a result, many public health officials aren&#39;t yet ready to make policy decisions based on poop data.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> In New York City over the last three years, for example, the local government has poured more than $1 million into <a href="https://gothamist.com/news/wastewater-can-predict-covid-19-surges-but-nycs-data-remains-hard-to-find" target="_blank" rel="noopener">testing for COVID-19, mpox and polio in sewage</a> from the city&#39;s water treatment plants. But the city&#39;s health department hasn&#39;t been using the resulting data to inform local COVID-19 safety measures, so it&#39;s unclear what&#39;s being done with the data.</p><div class="wp-block-sciencenews-content-sidebar alignwide" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Confirmed COVID-19 cases vs. wastewater testing, 2020 </h4><figure class="wp-block-image alignwide"><picture class="sn-responsive-image"><source srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_wastewater_inline3_desktop-800x297.jpg 800w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_wastewater_inline3_desktop-680x253.jpg 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_wastewater_inline3_desktop-330x123.jpg 330w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_wastewater_inline3_desktop-768x286.jpg 768w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_wastewater_inline3_desktop.jpg 1030w" width="800" height="297" media="(min-width: 600px)" sizes="(max-width: 1023px) 100vw, (max-width: 1439px) 60vw, 894px"></source><source srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_wastewater_inline3_mobile-437x450.jpg 437w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_wastewater_inline3_mobile-372x383.jpg 372w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_wastewater_inline3_mobile-181x186.jpg 181w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_wastewater_inline3_mobile-563x580.jpg 563w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_wastewater_inline3_mobile.jpg 680w" width="437" height="450"></source><img src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_wastewater_inline3_mobile-437x450.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large" alt="" decoding="async" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_wastewater_inline3_mobile-437x450.jpg 437w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_wastewater_inline3_mobile-372x383.jpg 372w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_wastewater_inline3_mobile-181x186.jpg 181w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_wastewater_inline3_mobile-563x580.jpg 563w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_wastewater_inline3_mobile.jpg 680w" sizes="(max-width: 1023px) 100vw, (max-width: 1439px) 60vw, 894px" data-attachment-id="3131157" data-permalink="https://www.sciencenews.org/090923_wastewater_inline3_mobile" data-orig-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_wastewater_inline3_mobile.jpg" data-orig-size="680,700" data-comments-opened="0" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="090923_wastewater_inline3_mobile" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="&lt;p>;Results from early efforts in 2020 showed that wastewater tests (bottom) to detect COVID-19 mirrored new reported cases (top) in San Jose, Calif. Scientists estimate the virus can be detected in concentrations as low as 40 copies of virus per gram of dried sewage.&lt;/p>;
" data-medium-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_wastewater_inline3_mobile-372x383.jpg" data-large-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_wastewater_inline3_mobile-437x450.jpg" /></picture><figcaption> <span class="caption mobile-caption wp-caption-3131157">Results from early efforts in 2020 showed that wastewater tests (bottom) to detect COVID-19 mirrored new reported cases (top) in San Jose, Calif. Scientists estimate the virus can be detected in concentrations as low as 40 copies of virus per gram of dried sewage.</span> <span class="credit mobile-credit wp-credit-3131157">KE graham <em>et al</em> / <em>Environ. sci. technol.</em> 2020</span> <span class="caption desktop-caption wp-caption-3131156">Results from early efforts in 2020 showed that wastewater tests (right) to detect COVID-19 mirrored new reported cases (left) in San Jose, Calif. Scientists estimate the virus can be detected in concentrations as low as 40 copies of virus per gram of dried sewage.</span> <span class="credit desktop-credit wp-credit-3131156">KE graham <em>et al</em> / <em>Environ. sci. technol.</em> 2020</span></figcaption></figure></div><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Health officials are used to one swab per person, says Rachel Poretsky, a microbiologist at the University of Illinois Chicago. She also heads wastewater monitoring for the city of Chicago and the state of Illinois.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Public health training relies on identifying individual sick people and tracing how they became ill. But in wastewater surveillance, one data point could represent thousands of sick people — and the data come from the environment, rather than from hospitals and health clinics. What to do next when positive results turn up isn&#39;t as obvious.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Numbers collected from the health care system always represent patients, so a spike indicates a surge in cases. In the case of sewage data, however, environmental factors like weather, local industries and the coming and going of tourists also can create “weird outliers” that resist easy interpretation, Poretsky says. For instance, a massive rainstorm might dilute samples, or chemical runoff from a factory might interfere with a research team&#39;s analytical methods.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Data interpretation only gets more complicated when scientists begin testing wastewater for an increasing number of health threats. Every pathogen&#39;s data need to be interpreted differently.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> With coronavirus data, for example, wastewater tests consistently come back positive, so interpreting the data is all about looking for trends: Are viral concentrations going up or down? How does the amount of virus present compare with the past? A spike in a particular location might signal a surge in the community that hasn&#39;t yet been picked up by the health care system. The community might respond by boosting health resources, such as opening vaccine clinics, handing out free masks and at-home tests, or adding staff to local hospital emergency departments.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Mpox, on the other hand, has infected far fewer people, and positive tests have been rare after last summer&#39;s outbreaks ended. Now, researchers are simply watching to see whether the virus is present or absent in a given sewershed.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “It&#39;s more about having an early warning,” Matus says. If a sewershed suddenly tests positive for mpox after negative results for the last few months, health officials might alert local doctors and community organizations to look out for anyone with symptoms, aiming to identify any cases and prevent a potential outbreak.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Another complicated pathogen is <em>C. auris</em> , a fungus that has developed resistance to common drugs. It can spread rapidly in health care settings — and be detected in sewage. Researchers from Utah and Nevada reported in February in <em>Emerging Infectious Diseases</em> that it was <a href="https://wwwnc.cdc.gov/eid/article/29/2/22-1523_article" target="_blank" rel="noopener">possible to track <em>C. auris</em> in the sewage</a> from areas experiencing outbreaks.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> If hospitals or health officials could identify the presence of this fungus early, that information could guide public health actions to curb outbreaks, says Alessandro Rossi, a microbiologist at the Utah Public Health Laboratory in Salt Lake City. But interpreting the warnings isn&#39;t as clear-cut for <em>C. auris</em> as for viruses.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The fungus can grow in sewage after it leaves health care facilities, Rossi says. The pathogen has “the potential to replicate, form biofilms and colonize a sewershed.” In other words, <em>C. auris</em> can create its own data interference, potentially making wastewater results seem worse than they really are.</p><div class="wp-block-sciencenews-content-sidebar alignwide" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><h3 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Viral verification</h3><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> As mpox spread in the United States in 2022, scientists tested wastewater samples at nine sites in California for the virus. At five of those sites, the virus was detected before or within a day of the first case being confirmed in that sewershed.</p><h5 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Mpox DNA detection in wastewater solids, 2022 </h5><figure class="wp-block-image alignwide"><picture class="sn-responsive-image"><source srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_wastewater_inline4_desktop-800x189.jpg 800w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_wastewater_inline4_desktop-680x160.jpg 680w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_wastewater_inline4_desktop-330x78.jpg 330w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_wastewater_inline4_desktop-768x181.jpg 768w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_wastewater_inline4_desktop.jpg 1030w" width="800" height="189" media="(min-width: 600px)" sizes="(max-width: 1023px) 100vw, (max-width: 1439px) 60vw, 894px"></source><source srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_wastewater_inline4_mobile-451x450.jpg 451w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_wastewater_inline4_mobile-384x383.jpg 384w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_wastewater_inline4_mobile-187x186.jpg 187w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_wastewater_inline4_mobile-582x580.jpg 582w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_wastewater_inline4_mobile-214x214.jpg 214w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_wastewater_inline4_mobile.jpg 680w" width="451" height="450"></source><img src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_wastewater_inline4_mobile-451x450.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large" alt="" decoding="async" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_wastewater_inline4_mobile-451x450.jpg 451w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_wastewater_inline4_mobile-384x383.jpg 384w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_wastewater_inline4_mobile-187x186.jpg 187w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_wastewater_inline4_mobile-582x580.jpg 582w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_wastewater_inline4_mobile-214x214.jpg 214w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_wastewater_inline4_mobile.jpg 680w" sizes="(max-width: 1023px) 100vw, (max-width: 1439px) 60vw, 894px" data-attachment-id="3131116" data-permalink="https://www.sciencenews.org/090923_wastewater_inline4_mobile" data-orig-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_wastewater_inline4_mobile.jpg" data-orig-size="680,678" data-comments-opened="0" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="090923_wastewater_inline4_mobile" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_wastewater_inline4_mobile-384x383.jpg" data-large-file="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_wastewater_inline4_mobile-451x450.jpg" /></picture><figcaption> <span class="credit mobile-credit wp-credit-3131116">MK Wolfe <em>et al</em> / <em>NEJM</em> 2023</span> <span class="credit desktop-credit wp-credit-3131158">MK Wolfe <em>et al</em> / <em>NEJM</em> 2023</span></figcaption></figure></div><h4 class="wp-block-heading" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Moving wastewater into the future</h4><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Most current testing programs are reactive. By looking at health threats one at a time using specific PCR tests, the programs mostly confirm that pathogens we already are worrying about are getting people sick.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> But some scientists, like Wim Meijer, envision a future in which wastewater monitoring wades into the unknown and alerts us to unusual disease outbreaks. The microbiologist, of the University College Dublin, heads Ireland&#39;s wastewater surveillance program. Ideally, in this ahead-of-the-curve future, after detecting something alarming in sewage, his team could closely collaborate with health officials to study the pathogen and, if necessary, start combating the threat.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> One idea for turning the tech proactive is to prepare for new health threats that we can see coming. For example, Meijer and his colleagues are interested in screening Ireland&#39;s sewage for the H5N1 bird flu, but they are not yet doing this testing.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Another approach takes advantage of genetic testing technology to look at <em>everything</em> in our waste. Kartik Chandran, an environmental engineer at Columbia University who has mapped sewers&#39; microbial ecosystems with this technique, describes it as “trying to shine the light more broadly” rather than looking where the light is already shining brightest.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> Such an approach might identify new pathogens before sick people start going to the doctor&#39;s office, potentially leading to an earlier public health response. But with health officials still unsure of how best to use wastewater data, much more basic research is needed first. </p><div class="wp-block-image  has-alignleft" style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"><figure class="alignleft size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="600" height="450" src="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_wastewater_inline1-600x450.jpg" alt="A small automated machine perches at the edge of a maintenance hole, ready to retrieve wastewater samples from the Tempe, Ariz., sewage system." class="wp-image-3131154" srcset="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_wastewater_inline1-600x450.jpg 600w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_wastewater_inline1-511x383.jpg 511w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_wastewater_inline1-248x186.jpg 248w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_wastewater_inline1-263x197.jpg 263w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_wastewater_inline1-560x420.jpg 560w, https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_wastewater_inline1.jpg 680w" sizes="(max-width: 600px) 100vw, 600px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"> <span class="caption wp-caption-3131154">A small automated machine perches at the edge of a maintenance hole, ready to retrieve wastewater samples (like the one in the gray container) from the Tempe, Ariz., sewage system.</span> <span class="credit wp-credit-3131154">E. Driver/Arizona State Univ.</span></figcaption></figure></div><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> “People think wastewater surveillance is the answer to everything, and clearly that&#39;s not true,” says Kirby, of the CDC, reflecting concerns from the state and local officials that she collaborates with at NWSS. Before diving ahead into proactive surveillance, Kirby and her colleagues are working to set up basic wastewater standards and protocols for health agencies. Priorities include evaluating how sewage trends correlate to cases for different pathogens and developing standards for how to use the data.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The wastewater surveillance field also needs to keep growing if the goal is to monitor and contribute to global health, with more sites contributing data and more scientists to analyze it. All of this work requires sustained funding.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> The CDC&#39;s program so far has been funded by COVID-era legislation and will run out of money in 2025. While wastewater surveillance is more cost-effective than other types of testing, it still requires a lot of resources. Washington&#39;s state health department, for example, paid Biobot more than $500,000 for a one-year sewage testing contract, while the CDC has paid the company more than $23 million since 2020 for its work with NWSS.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> For the last few years, wastewater surveillance has been a giant, messy group project. Scientists have collaborated across fields and locations, across private and public institutions, through Zoom calls and through poop samples shipped on ice. They&#39;ve shown that waste might hold the key to a new way of tracking our collective health.</p><p style=";text-align:right;direction:rtl"> A lot of unanswered questions remain, and it could be some time before your local sewer can tell you exactly what disease risks you might be facing. But COVID-19 pushed thousands of experts to look into their toilets and start asking those questions. “Now, everyone&#39;s a believer,” says Driver, of ASU. “Everyone&#39;s doing the work.”</p> ]]>; </content:encoded><media:thumbnail url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_wastewater_feat-800x450.jpg"></media:thumbnail><enclosure length="341108" type="image/jpeg" url="https://www.sciencenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/090923_wastewater_feat-800x450.jpg"></enclosure></item></channel></rss>